[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: All of us are set
in our own little world view.
We think we see the
big picture, but we all
see a little slice of the
world surrounding the lens.
I would like to imagine that
people have the opportunity
to see a much wider set of
perspectives on the world,
and that games might
be the mechanism,
the vehicle brings that to them.
We can take almost
anything and make it
a fascinating
interactive experience.
What I'm really doing is,
I'm giving the player a toy,
and the player is
turning it into a game.
Every designer has
the opportunity
to create something
incredibly unique.
At the same time, every
designer faces the risk
of creating something that no
one will be able to understand.
As a designer, you're actually
dealing with two computers.
First, the electronic
one, sitting
on the table in front of you.
But more importantly,
the player's
imagination, the player's brain.
And that one is
far more complex,
and we have barely
scratched the surface of it.
During the course
of this class, I'm
going to expose you to a number
of kind of fundamental concepts
about game design.
Basically psychology
of the player,
the mental modeling
that goes on;
how to use game mechanics
as part of your tool set,
and how to develop your
tool set as a designer;
how to think about the overall
structure of what's going on
underneath the hood; how to
build emergence, surprise,
cool, detailed worlds; and
to try to predict what's
going to motivate
players of your games
and pull them in, and
get them emotionally
involved to the point where
they get into communities that
are built up around these.
And so there are many different
levels of game design,
and we're going to kind of
start with the fundamentals
and work our way outwards
towards larger and larger more
strategic levels of
thinking around it.
Every designer is
unique in some way,
and my games have
tended to be very
specific in terms of real
world simulations generally--
games that tend to encourage
player creativity, player
storytelling.
There are a lot of other
approaches to game design.
But I think a lot of the
fundamentals that I'll
be talking about
in this class are
going to be things that can
apply to any genre of game.
And I think by going down
to that fundamental level,
it's going to give you
a lot more opportunities
to kind of come up with
creative inspiration
to bring in new
approaches, new ideas.
Basically, how to amplify your
own internal creativity in ways
that are coming from a
fundamental level rather than
just the feature level.
I'm Will Wright, and this is
a simulation-- a simulation--
a simulation--
of my MasterClass.
So you're probably
watching this because you
have an interest in games.
But what are games?
We all know what games are.
We play games.
More recently with
electronic devices,
games have taken a totally
different kind of turn
and gotten much more elaborate,
more ubiquitous in our lives,
I think.
But games really are something
that have been around
for thousands of years.
Different cultures
have played games--
board games, social games--
for a long, long time,
for a lot of reasons.
Games, really, right now
have different genres.
We have things like
puzzle games, first person
shooters, strategy games.
These are different
subsets of the game space.
But games really are a subset
of a larger thing called play.
Play is just exploring.
Its experimenting.
It's trying different
things, usually
in some symbolic representation.
You know, some little toy of the
real world with a very low cost
for failure.
In a lot of ways, I think games
have been somewhat misaligned.
We've associated
games with violence.
You know, it's something
that little kids play.
But that's actually been
true of any kind of new media
that's come along.
In any kind of media--
you know, radio
was actually looking down on
film when film became popular.
Film looked down on television.
Television looked down at games.
So it's really-- games are
the up and coming thing
that in some sense is breaking
boundaries, doing new things.
And that's what makes
games interesting to me,
is kind of a topic as a medium.
Games borrow from so many
other different design fields,
you know.
Not just entertainment,
you know,
storytelling, things
like that, but also
things like architecture,
product design, fine art,
mathematics,
cognitive psychology.
Games incorporate all these
different design fields
in an interesting way.
And the more you
can expose yourself
to these different design
fields, the better a designer
you'll be.
I think game design is probably
one of the most challenging
design fields there is.
And I think to be a
good game designer,
you first and foremost
have to be a good designer.
And so I think just,
you know, getting
into the idea of the
mode of thinking of,
you know, how does a designer
think, how do they learn,
where they pull
inspiration from.
And don't close yourself
into just the gaming world,
you know, look at all
sorts of things all over.
I've learned so much from
weird fields like, you know,
Japanese gardening, or biology,
or economics, whatever,
you know.
You can pull all
these things in,
you know, and as a
designer, use these
as parts of your
creative palette.
One of the things that
I really would inspire--
try to inspire up and coming
game designers to do is, think
how do I learn continually?
You know, from other
people, learn from myself,
my own mistakes.
But then also, just do it.
Try it, you know.
You can do something as
simple as design a little game
on a piece of paper and go
show your friend, let's play
this game, here are the rules.
See-- you know, see
how that works out.
And the more you're doing
that, just always inventing
little games, you
know, even if it's
with toothpicks on
a tabletop, you're
going to learn a lot that way.
And that's much
better than just,
you know, sitting in
your head for two years
coming up with your master
design, and then one day
trying to realize
it and finding out
that it's too
complex to realize.
You'll be much better off doing
continual, ubiquitous, everyday
kind of local game design.
Any designer, basically, when
they're designing something,
has to look at a
number of factors.
You know, basically
you're trying
to balance all these
things against each other.
So think about just a chair
and all of the different things
that you kind of
would like a chair--
you know, different properties
you would like from a chair.
You want it to be, you know,
cheap, easy to move, easy
to produce, comfortable.
And these functions can
actually be kind of broken down
into a tree, you know.
So games have very
much the same property.
You know, there's certain
functional things about them.
There's certain things that are
economic about-- what does it
take to produce the game?
How much does it cost?
What kind of a team
do I have to build?
What kind of skills do I
have to have as a designer?
And the designer needs
to kind of understand
how to balance all
these different things
against each other,
because your final design
is going to be a balancing act.
You're basically
balancing all these plates
on top of each other, and
it's the designer's job
to make them balance well.
Now, as you're
exploring your design,
you're actually going through
this very large branching tree
of possible designs.
You know, there
are infinite number
of designs that you could
be building in your game,
and you can end up with
one very specific design.
And when you start
out, you might
have some sense about
where you're going
or kind of the area
you want to be,
but you do not know
exactly how to get there.
And you're basically exploring
this branching path of design
decisions, you know, starting
with very fundamental design
decisions.
You know, what kind
of a game am I making?
What's it about?
What are the controls?
Down to very incremental
design decisions.
You know, what color
is this button?
You know, how tall
is the character?
Very, very minor things.
And a lot of these
decisions are distributed
throughout your team.
And you need to make sure that
your team kind of understands
the vision so that
as they're balancing
their little parts of
that tree, that they
are in line with the creative
vision for the whole product.
Basically, as you're
exploring this tree,
there are a lot of
different methods
you have as a designer for
figuring out which direction
to go on what branch.
Now, you're really trying
to prune these branches
as efficiently as possible.
That's why when we
build a prototype
we want an answer
from that prototype.
We want to find out, you know,
do we go down path A or B?
If the prototype
can't answer that,
it's basically failed
as a prototype.
So we're really trying to
efficiently prune the branches
and continue down the right
path toward our final design.
You know, as I said, you don't
know exactly where you're
going to end up on this
tree, but the designer also
needs to kind of know
when you've gotten there.
A lot of times,
I've seen, you know,
game designs, or even other
designs where somebody went
a little bit too far, you know.
They, you know--
Some movies, you know, I
think had a perfect ending,
went a little bit too far.
And the designer
needs to kind of know
you've hit the sweet spot.
One of my design heroes
is Charles Eames.
Charles and Ray Eames were a
design team, husband and wife.
And he had a great
quote, which was simply
that "design is constraint."
You know, design really
is how do you, you know,
work around constraint.
And without constraint,
there's no design,
you know, it's just
pure imagination.
So, you know, to
be a good designer,
you have to kind of
embrace that constraint
and say, okay, within this
constraint, what can I
do that's really cool?
And, you know, that
constraint is really
going to become your foundation.
It's going to be, okay,
here was my starting point,
and within that constraint
I was able to do this.
The constraint
could be, you know,
the technology in front of
you, how fast the processor,
the graphics.
But the constraint
can also be, you
know, what does my player know?
What kind of skills
do they have?
Where does their
imagination take them?
Those are constraints
just as well.
And the more you understand
your constraints, you know,
the more you can now kind of
use that as your starting point
to go off and do
something really
cool that nobody else has done
against those same constraints.
In a competitive game, you
know, usually with two players,
there's a concept
of a zero sum game,
which is that if a player
wins, he gets, you know,
a positive 1.
The losing player
gets a negative 1.
If it's a tie, they both get 0.
So basically, the sum of
the two players is always 0.
You know, either I won,
you lost, you know,
and it sums to 0, or it
was a tie, sums to 0.
That's a zero sum game.
So you can't have two
winners or two losers,
you know, out of
a two-player game.
A non-zero sum game, you can.
Both people can win.
The kind of games I do are
not zero sum games at all.
In fact, most of the
things I do don't even
really have a clear win state.
When you play something
like "Sim City"
or "The Sims," what actually
I found very interesting
was to leave it to the player
to define the null state.
[GIBBERISH]
[SMOOCHING]
When a person sits down to play
"Sim City," I don't tell them
they have to build
the biggest city,
or have the happiest
people, or the least crime.
Players in their own
mind decide that.
You know, they think, okay, what
is, you know, my ideal city?
And they try to build that.
So the player is
actually the one
building the rule set
and the structure,
and the player is
the one scoring it.
I'm really just kind of
giving them an open-ended toy.
And then you get a lot of kind
of interesting different play
styles.
You know, certain players
trying to achieve things.
Other players don't
even really try
to achieve anything
thing at all,
but try to use it for creative
storytelling or creativity.
A lot of people were
playing "Spore,"
not really trying to get
through all the levels,
but trying to just make really
cool things within the game
that they would then go out
and share with other players.
So for them, the win
state was more social--
kind of make something really
cool in this game, maybe even
just tell a story that
other people really like.
And to me, that's the win state.
So, you know, I think
games have the opportunity
to go, you know, way beyond just
this kind of zero sum approach.
You can take almost any
technology that we have
and view it as an extension
of the human body.
For instance, you know,
television, telescope--
our eyes, our vision.
Telephone, you know, our speech.
Car really kind of
extends our legs.
If somebody hits
your car, you know,
you don't say that, you
know, my car was hit,
you say, somebody hit me
when I was driving, you know.
So me-- you know,
the car becomes me,
it becomes an
extension of your body.
I think that computers and
games and things that we're
dealing with on the
entertainment side
can extend a lot of
these in a lot of ways.
When I was watching players
play "The Sims" initially,
it was like, he was hungry, then
he did this, then he did that,
and they very
smoothly shifted to--
then I got tired and I went
to bed, and then I woke up.
So they kind of shifted
from he to I very smoothly.
We now, with these
little micro worlds,
have the ability to
basically externalize
what's in our imagination and
share it with other people.
You know, it used to
be that you had have,
you know, a very rich
skill set, like you
had to be a fine artist
to do that-- you know,
to paint something
in your imagination
and then share it
with other people.
But now with these tools, the
creative leverage they give us,
you know, average, casual
game players have the ability
to externalize, you
know, create things out
of their imagination, share
it with other players,
and actually have these
shared imaginary worlds.
In "Spore," we actually had all
these editors where the players
were making cool things.
In some of the levels, the
design of your creature
really influenced,
you know, the way
you would play that creature
in the world-- its performance.
Other parts of it, you know,
like designing your spaceship,
didn't really have
a whole lot to do
with the performance
of the spaceship,
it was purely aesthetic.
But people would spend
just as much time
crafting this very unique thing
that was part of their player
identity in the game.
And as they were playing
in the space level,
they were, you know, front
and foreground all the time
with this spaceship.
And so they really felt, you
know, like that was them.
When you get to the
space phase, there
are actually millions of
planets you can go to.
And we could never create
millions of creatures,
so we decided that every time
a player made a creature,
it would go up to
our server and we
would use it to populate
everybody else's world.
And we were hoping
to get, you know,
maybe 100,000 of these
creatures, you know,
in the first months,
you know, after we'd
uploaded the creature editor.
Instead, it was so popular
that we got a million
in the first week.
In fact, we passed, I
think, five or six million
in the first month, which is
more than the number of species
on Earth.
So it was, you know,
kind of extraordinary
how much players embraced that.
Basically, we were
turning the average player
into a Pixar artist.
They were able to
create, you know,
a brand new character
out of their imagination
and have it come to life.
And so I think that's one of the
examples of the computer giving
creative leverage--
a creative amplifier.
And a lot of people
are using computers
for different creative
fields, but same thing--