[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: I don't actually
start by concepting a new game.
I read a lot, I like learning
new things, and at some point
I'll just trip over a
subject or some material
that I find particularly
fascinating.
So it's not like I sit
down and say, okay, I'm
going to come up
with a new game idea.
It's more like I'm kind of just
exploring, browsing the world,
then it's like oh, maybe I
can make a game out of this.
When I went to college I studied
all these different things,
and I don't want to
become an architect
or an engineer or an artist.
And by being a game
designer, I found that I
could study whatever I want.
And my excuse is, I'm
making a game about it.
So for me, being a game designer
turned into a lifelong learning
process where I can go
off in any subject I want
to and it's tax deductible.
For me, it's usually some
kind of interesting thing
about the world or in the
world that as I dig deeper
it gets more
interesting, not less.
It didn't sound that
interesting to me,
but as I read about
it a little bit more
it actually sounded
kind of fascinating.
I read some more and it actually
really grabbed me and pulled me
in.
A lot of the games
I've done actually
were based upon cool subjects,
usually books that I read.
SimCity was very
influenced by the work
of a guy named Jay Forrester
who was the first person
to actually model cities
on the early computers
back in the 50s.
His models were
not spatial, they
were just like little numbers.
How many people
did the city have,
how much land, how many roads.
But he was actually
the father of what
became known as system
dynamics, which I'll
talk about a little bit later.
SimAnt was very much
inspired by the work
of Edward O Wilson, very famous
myrmecologist, studies ants.
He wrote this great book,
won the Pulitzer Prize,
called "The Ants".
But he actually, in
some sense, was reverse
engineering the way ants work.
Little ants are almost
like little robots,
and it's pretty
simple to figure out
in the presence
of this pheromone
the ant does that, in the
presence of that pheromone
he does this.
He actually reverse
engineered that and discovered
a whole level of emergence.
An ant colony, in fact,
is incredibly smart.
It's about as smart as a dog.
An individual ant is
incredibly stupid.
And so ant colonies
are really one
of the few forms of
intelligence that we
can deconstruct and
understand at that level,
and he was the guy who did it.
These kind of
subjects are things
that when you read about them,
they're kind of dry and boring,
they're filled with
technical jargon.
And what I always aspired to
do was to take these things
and make them approachable--
turn them into a toy.
How can I turn an
ant colony into a toy
so that people come in and
start interacting with it?
And when players are actually
manipulating these things
and building them,
they take ownership.
And they get so involved, so
much more emotionally connected
to these.
And then the subject
becomes utterly fascinating.
As soon as I built the very
first prototypes of SimCity
and I was running a
little simulation--
it was very coarse, very crude--
but still, my interest in
urban planning skyrocketed.
All of a sudden oh,
this is really cool.
I want to find out
about traffic modeling.
I want to find out about
this, that, and the other.
These things that would have
sounded incredibly boring to me
when I had a little Guinea
pig in my room to play with
became fascinating.
Likewise, other games
I did, The Sims,
was very much influenced by
Christopher Alexander's work
in architecture.
So for me personally, I find
a lot of inspiration in books,
also in fields I think that
are interdisciplinary, things
that are almost controversial.
Sim Earth was very much inspired
by James Lovelock's Gaia
hypothesis.
It's about the earth and
the way it regulates itself.
And usually that's where
the areas of science
are moving the fastest
and the most interesting.
And those are the things I
tended to gravitate toward.
This is me personally
as a designer.
I think every designer
is going to find
their own kind of
palette of inspiration,
their own direction,
their own kind of voice.
When I was starting
out in game design,
there wasn't this thing
around called the internet.
I actually had to go
to this place they
used to call
libraries where they
had these things called books.
And I would read these books
and learn about things that way.
Nowadays, it's so low
friction to go on the web
and find anything you want to,
anything at all about anything
you want to.
So I think that now designers
have so much less friction
to do research around
an idea that for me it's
almost magical that I can
kind of pick any topic
and go down any
little weird path
and find material about it.
On the simulation side, it
was really interesting to me
to kind of go back into
the history of simulation,
back into the 60s and 50s
and even all the way back
to Von Neumann
and Turing and see
what they were trying to do
with these super primitive
computers.
And some of the things
they were trying to do
were amazing, way, way beyond
anything a computer could do.
But they would imagine that one
day a computer could do this.
And right now, my watch has
much more power than they
ever envisioned.
At least as a
designer, I don't feel
like there are any
meaningful limitations
beyond my own imagination.
And so I think to me,
that's really the thing
that I have to kind of
flex and exercise and push
is my own imagination.
If I could do
that, it's actually
pretty straightforward
and easy for me
to figure out the research,
the technology, to do it.
It feels to me like so
many designers always
think about and even
communicate their game
idea relative to other games.
It's going to be World
of Warcraft on the moon.
It's going to be whatever.
I think that there's so
much more opportunity out
in the world to take things--
you can just take a rock off
the ground and look at it
the right way and it has
little microbes competing
on the surface for
territory, and there's
sunlight and environmental
consideration.
You could turn that into
something fascinating.
You can take almost anything,
and looking at it the right
way, make it a fascinating,
interactive experience.
With The Sims, it
wasn't really apparent
what I should be researching.
But as I started digging
into the game design,
we started getting into this
thing with the Sims motives,
and they had to go to
work and all this stuff.
It became pretty apparent
that this was really
kind of a game about time
management, in some sense,
on their side.
How do you manage their time
to maximize their motives
to make them happy?
And after quite
a bit of digging,
I came across the work of
a guy named James Robinson,
and he did all these time
studies of Americans,
how they spent their time.
He actually kept logs every day.
They spent 20 minutes of
time doing their stuff
in the morning to get ready.
This amount of time
with their kids.
in front of TV.
And he actually broke it down.
And it ended up that we were
matching those numbers fairly
closely.
We took the simulation and
tried to match the real numbers,
the percentage of time
that people actually
spend doing each of these
activities in The Sims.
So that was
something that wasn't
apparent that was something
we could even research.
Another area of research--
I forgot the name of
the guy who did this,
but he was interviewing
all these people
about what their most
prized possessions were
at different ages.
And it was actually
quite interesting stuff,
some of which kind of
made it into the game,
some of which didn't.
It turned out that for
kids and really old people,
their most prized
possession was their bed.
And in mid-life--
and TV was second.
Mid-life it was like
their car, their house,
all these other things.
But it was interesting
that the kids list
of their top possessions
was almost the same
as like an elderly
person's top possessions.
So some of this stuff will
become part of the game or not.
But still, as a designer,
if you understand and absorb
all this stuff, it helps
you think about directions
you might take it or
you could take it,
even if you don't
end up using it.
Even when I'm
initially imagining,
I'm making a game
about this thing,
I don't start by thinking
what's the game going to be
or what's going
to be like, I just
dive deeper and deeper into
the subject and the research.
And then I start trying to kind
of look at the components--
what are the different
aspects of this
that are interesting to me?
And it might be the process,
it might be the structure,
it might be the
science behind it,
whatever, historical context.
From those things,
I start imagining
how would I really like to view
this or manipulate it or play
with it or create it.
If this is a piece
of clay, how do I
want to sculpt it,
what are my tools?
I start just imagining 10
or 20 different perspectives
on that subject.
And I think the
perspectives are far more
valuable than particular
solutions or approaches.
So actually, after kind of
rotating this thing around
through 20 or 30 perspectives,
two or three usually
will start to get
traction in my head,
and I'll start exploring
those a little bit further.
So I'm trying to describe
something that in my head
is really a much more
abstract process,
but that's how it feels to me.
But I in some sense, I'm
kind of circling the idea
and slowly zeroing in on it.
I don't dive right at it,
but I sit there and just
let it turn over my mind.
I'll sit there and do this
research thinking about it
phase for a year before I even
think about what kind of game
it might be.
And during that time, I
will even build models of it
or draw pictures of it or try to
recreate it in different forms,
tangibly.
And that again just
kind of puts my brain
in a little bit different
spin, a little bit
different perspective,
and new ideas
will pop up just
as a result of me
building a model of something.
Spore, the original concept,
was based on a couple of things.
I did a box design, an
original box design,
actually I called
it Sim Everything.
But there were two
things that really
fascinated me especially.
Number one was an
old film, Charles
and Ray Eames "Powers of Ten".
FILM NARRATION: We begin
with a scene one meter wide.
Now every 10 seconds we
will look from 10 times
farther away, and our field of
view will be 10 times wider.
WILL WRIGHT: It
was the same thing.
Starting with an atomic scale,
every one a powers of 10
bigger and bigger and bigger.
I love that idea of
scale across the galaxy,
across the universe.
And within that
dimension of scale,
that the most interesting
thing at every single scale
that we know of is life.
Everything else is
fairly deterministic,
fairly predictable,
dry, but life
is the one unpredictable aspect
in every single scale starting
at the cellular level.
The other big inspiration
was basically astrobiology--
the idea of how prevalent
is life out the galaxy
and what forms might it take?
And so it was those two
ideas that came together
and I was really
thinking about, can I
tell a story about
the journey of life
from the cellular level
up to galactic expansion
and make that kind of
game like, like a toy?
As a designer I tend to go with
my gut feel in terms of that's
going to be something cool, and
I can't always express exactly
on what dimensions
it's going to be cool,
but I hope that my instincts
will bring me to a place
where a wide range of
people will enjoy it.
And I wasn't always that way.
It took me a while
to realize that.
When I was first working
on SimCity by myself
I showed it to a
few people and they
thought it was kind of cool.
I showed it to eventual
partner, Jeff Braun,
and he was like oh yes, we have
to do, let's start a company.
And we started Maxim
and did SimCity.
But in my mind, even at that
point, I was thinking okay,
this is a game that maybe a few
strategy gamers or architects
maybe might enjoy.
It didn't occur to me that
a wide range of people
would enjoy that.
To Jeff it did.
Jeff kind of understood that
I think more than I did.
After that, I started learning
to trust my instincts,
that if I really find
this cool for some reason
or I'm gravitating
toward that, just
trust that we can find a
way to bring other people
and they'll enjoy it as well.
It's very hard, as
a designer, for me
to design for somebody else.
This is how that person
thinks, this is what they want,
this is what they believe.
It's easy to do
for myself and then
figure out why am I enjoying
this, why am I motivated?
And what about other
people's thought process
will let them see this and
enjoy it and experience