[MUSIC PLAYING]
Once I have an idea for a
game, I start making prototypes
as soon as I can.
The early prototyping
is probably
the most important stage.
We're trying to imagine
different types of rules
that might be
applied to the system
that we're basing the game on.
You're basically
trying everything
you can think of for how to
turn this concept into a game,
whatever it takes for
you to cheaply get
a sense of that's
fun, that's not fun.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Well, a prototype is
usually interactive.
Not always, but usually.
And we're taking like some
little bit or part of the game
that we have a question about.
Should we go this
way or that way?
And it might be an
interaction question.
Is it better to have the
controls work like this
or like that?
It might be a visualization
or a graphics question.
Should we do this point of
view, that point of view?
Should it be this
style, that style?
But it's something that we
feel like we can't answer
unless we actually touch
and play with and interact
with a little bit.
Even if it's just turning
the world around and looking
at different camera angles.
And that's when we
decide, OK, we're
going to build a
prototype and we're
going to build the simplest
possible thing we can
that will help us
answer that question.
As I'm playing with this
one little piece in hand
and imagining the rest
of the experience,
can answer that question?
Oh yeah, this would be
much better top down.
This would be much better 3D.
This would be much better with
that kind of player control.
But you know, it really needs
to be answering a question
as cheaply as possible.
You don't want to go spend
weeks and weeks building this.
You want to build the cheapest,
simplest little thing that you
can build that you can
sit back and say, OK, I'm
pretty confident now
that we go this way.
As we get further down
the path, it's, you know,
can somebody learn how
to use this interface?
And we can find out what
the failure states are,
how we need to change it
to make it work better.
And even further
down the road, it's,
how engaging is this to players?
And that's a much, much
more open-ended question
and a much broader
range of answers
that, for certain people,
this is very motivating.
Most people, it isn't.
Or it's somewhat motivating
for a lot of people,
but if we did this, it would
be much more motivating.
Or, you know, the
social component
is working well here,
but not the individual.
So those are much more I'd
say subjective in terms
of interpreting the results.
The very initial ones are very
clear usually in terms of,
OK, we go with A instead
of B. And I think,
you know, we think
of it in those terms.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Prototyping can take
different forms.
I mean, sometimes it's cutting
up little pieces of paper
and these are now game units.
And you have, basically, rules,
and you can move your thing two
spaces every turn, and you might
have a very simple turn-based
two player game and you're
moving the pieces of paper
around.
Other times it might be a
more constructive experience
where you're actually drawing
something on a piece of paper,
and you have rules about
how much you can draw,
and you add up how many
things you've drawn
and what the cost is,
and you're actually
doing your own little kind
of economic bookkeeping
along side of it.
You know, what we call paper
prototyping isn't so much
it has to be paper.
It really more means that
it's off the computer.
You know, you're not
really programming,
but you're doing it with
tangible little objects.
One thing that I tried
starting a long time ago
was when I was first
coming up with the game,
I was trying to pitch it
around, I would actually
make two or three different
box designs myself.
I'd just put, you know,
print the stuff out, glue it
to the side of a box,
put them up there,
and show them to people.
Which one of these
games would you like?
It's all the same game
in my mind, but you know,
these are three different ways
of kind of informing, you know,
what the game is about
and presenting it.
In some sense, that's
a marketing prototype.
And I would see that, oh,
people really get box B,
but A and C they
don't like at all.
That would just
tell me a little bit
about how somebody initially
thinks about this whole idea
and which direction I should
go in terms of communicating.
So that's kind
of, in some sense,
a communications prototype.
Later on, as you
start kind of playing
with how we present the player
or what's the interface,
you know, those are things
that are fairly simple.
And again, sometimes
these are things
you can just pull off
the shelf and say,
you know, this game
uses control scheme A,
that one uses control scheme B,
and they're both driving tanks.
Which one feels better?
As I'm imagining
the rest of my game,
which might be completely
different than these
off the shelf games.
But at least, in
terms of the controls,
I can sit there and imagine
my game with these controls.
So these prototypes
can take any form.
It's anytime you have
a question to answer
and you feel like if you
could build something,
whether it's a fake box, or
a control scheme prototype,
or even two games off
the shelf that you're
playing one little
part of, will it
help you figure out which
branch down that design tree
that you want to take?
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I found that when I make
games, a lot of times
it actually helps me to
build real, tangible things
from the game before I
actually build the game.
When I was actually working
on "The Sims" at some point
I decided I wanted to
have a little neighborhood
for the original Sims.
And you would pick a
house and build a house,
and then eventually,
you'd build a little house
in the neighborhood.
I actually first built a real
model of a little, you know,
a few houses and a
little landscape.
And this is the model I
actually built for "The Sims."
And this is actually
the original Sims,
what it looked like.
So it was actually a fairly
close representation.
For "SimAnt" I
built a giant ant.
And for everything
I've made, I've
tried to bring it
to the tangible.
And it helps me think
about it in certain ways
when I'm actually touching it.
And I wonder, like,
in the game, how
can I make it feel tangible?
How can I make the player
feel like they're actually
touching something real here?
[MUSIC PLAYING]
As we start building prototypes,
we might find, you know,
kind of sweet spots,
really fun things.
That's a really cool
dynamic, or I like that tool,
or it's really enjoyable
making this thing.
Then we start figuring
out, how can we
take those really good
spots and spread it out
through the rest of the design
and make it part of the spine?
On a game like
"Spore," you know,
we started building some of
the editors very early on.
And it was so fun building
things in the creature editor,
we decided, hey, let's see if
we can do a building editor.
Oh, and that's cool, so we
can do a vehicle editor.
And so we decided
that the editors
would be consistent
across all the levels.
They would operate
pretty much the same,
but each one was its
own special thing.
But yet it was kind
of a core activity
that of gave connection
across the different levels.
Because "Spore," really,
you know, otherwise, was
like, five different games
that happened to be connected.
But the editors gave kind
of thematic consistency
across there.
And player familiarity.
When I got to the
next level, I already
knew how to use the editor.
So I think we look
for things like that.
Or you know, even like
the tools in "Sim City."
When you're laying down
this, you know, that tool
operates pretty much the
same like, you know, roads
operate almost the same
as the water pipes.
You look for things
that you can kind
of leverage across the design
so once the player learns
one thing, they've
learned five things.
But also gives kind
of a consistent
feel to the whole experience.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Well, as a designer, I'm going
to look at these prototypes,
interact with them, and come up
with some decision about where
we should go.
I don't care what
they're built out of.
So typically, depending on the
programmer I was working with,
maybe they might
be very comfortable
throwing in a little code base
and they could very rapidly
iterate that.
So from my point
of view, whatever
was the least amount of friction
for the programmer creating
this.
Because at the end,
I just want to be
able to interact with
it for a few hours
and then make a decision.
And we're basically going
to throw that code away.
Or the programmer might
actually take that code base
and evolve it into
the next prototype.
There's so many
different programs.
It could be, you
know, JavaScript.
It could be Unity.
It could be hardcore
C. I don't care, again.
But that really depends
a lot on, you know,
the programmer and
their familiarity.
You know, again,
whatever is going--
they can create the fastest
possible thing for you
at the least possible cost.
So I'm totally agnostic in terms
of what platform or code base
it's built in.
As a student, you want
to learn prototyping.
Again, I would say
find some system
that you can program to some
degree, or script, whatever
you're familiar with, and then
imagine how you could actually
create some simple interactive
experience with that.
Do that a few times.
And now start imagining, OK,
how could I make that better?
What questions do
I need to answer?
So basically, this, again, is a
navigation instrument for you.
It's a compass to
help you figure out,
I want to go this
way or that way.
And just play with
simple rule sets.
You can kind of get
a sense of how you
navigate that kind of a tree.