[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: Games
and story I think
have a very interesting
relationship with each other,
and I see a lot
of game designers
that really are aspiring
to be storytellers.
And I've always thought that
the coolest stories are always
coming from the players.
I mean, it's nice
to have a backstory
or here's the world and all
that, but really you want
every player to basically
encounter their own story,
create their own story by
what they do in the game.
That's the really
interesting story for me.
But as creatures,
as organisms, we
are faced with this kind of
fundamental dilemma, which
is that we're here,
the world's out there.
Basically, we have a limited
bubble of experience,
things that we know
about the world,
will experience directly
about the world.
Basically, we take this
in through our senses.
We see the world, we
perceive it in certain ways.
It goes into our imagination.
We actually start building
little models of it.
And based upon how we
interpret the world around us,
it influences our behavior,
how we act out there.
Now, that limited
bubble of experience
is not really enough for us
to build very effective models
of the world.
And it's that experience
that we're building
these models of the world from.
So over time, actually
through evolution,
I think we've discovered
two other methods.
One is to have toy
experiences, where
we have symbolic experiences
and kind of abstract
that back into the real world.
The other one is to learn from
other people's experiences.
If my friend the cave
man comes back and says,
a tiger almost ate me
when I left the cave,
I didn't have that
experience, but I
know the next time I
leave that cave, I'm
going to look out for a tiger.
I was able to learn
from his experience
without having that
experience directly myself.
Now, over time,
through our culture,
we've come to call one of
these things play, these toy
experiences, and
the other one story.
These are both, though,
fundamentally educational
technologies.
I think this is why we enjoy
consuming these things,
because they actually
help us build
more elaborate, more
detailed, world models
with a limited experience base.
Now, story and play I
think have a really kind
of interesting two sides
of coin relationship here.
Some of the really
cool stories, the ones
that really capture
your imagination,
you can deconstruct into
characters, worlds, locations,
objects.
I watch my eight-year-old
playing with Star Wars LEGOs,
and he creates his own stories
with the storm troopers and all
the components from Star Wars--
and he kind of understands
that universe-- but now becomes
kind of a set of things for him
to play with.
I think some of the
best games where players
have a lot of
freedom, creativity,
lead to really cool stories.
The games are actually
generating stories
as the players play.
So in some sense, I think really
good stories can generate play
and really good play
can generate stories.
So I think the two are
kind of self supporting,
but they're very, very
different actually.
A lot of times you
hear that stories
have such a deep, emotional
connection whereas games
are flat.
I don't really
think that's true.
I think that games really
haven't matured as much.
But I think what it is
is that they have very
different emotional palates.
The emotional palette of film
is totally based upon empathy.
You can look at characters,
actually simulations
on the screen, which we
call actors pretending
to be these characters,
and they are basically
pretending to have emotions
and we're empathizing
with those emotions.
And so when they feel
sad, we feel that sadness.
When they're happy,
we feel happy.
Games, the emotional palette
is based upon agency.
The fact that I did it.
That I'm responsible,
I have accountability,
I'm the one that pushed the
joystick in that direction.
So I think that the
kind of emotions
that we can actually get out
of games are very different.
Things like guilt, pride,
accomplishment, teamwork
are things I've
felt in gaming I've
never felt in linear media,
because they were things that I
was actively involved with.
I remember when I played Black
and White the first time.
You have this creature
you're basically raising
and you can discipline
it or reward it
and I just started slapping
it to see what happened
and it got really downtrodden
and sad and all that
and I actually felt so
bad, even though I knew
it was a digital character.
But I felt so bad, and I felt
guilty for having done that.
There was a much earlier
game called Choplifter where
you flew this little
helicopter around,
you were rescuing these
little tiny people,
which were really
like 10 pixels high,
and I'd pick them
up in the helicopter
and bringing them out.
They'd get out after
I rescued them.
They'd jump out of the
helicopter and wave at me,
and I felt so proud.
And it was 10 wide
pixels I'd rescued.
But it was just funny that
it was able to kind of tweak
that circuit in my head.
A feeling of
accomplishment and pride.
And again, this is
something I've never
really felt watching a movie.
I've felt indirectly that
some character in the movie
felt proud or
accomplished or guilty.
But I didn't directly feel
I was responsible for it.
So I think that is the
primary distinguishing factor
between the emotional
palette in both.
As we were getting closer
to finishing the very
first version of The Sims--
we were of course bringing
people in, watching
them play it, just observing--
and as designers, we were
sitting back and watching
them play the game.
And as they were
playing the game
they were telling each other
the story of what was happening.
And it was hilarious.
I really enjoyed
hearing the stories.
And it was based upon what was
actually happening in the game,
but they would elaborate
and they would add details
and they gave it almost themes.
And it was just
fascinating to me
how readily people would
build a story around this.
I think it's a
fundamental way for us
to convey things to another
person is through story.
And so we decided that
we should-- at the very
last minute, we
decide we were going
to put a feature in so
players could basically
capture screenshots,
write text, and basically
build a little comic book, a
little illustrated comic book,
and then upload
it with one click.
They didn't have to know
anything about the web.
It was just built into the game.
Capture a story, write it under
the pictures, press a button,
it goes on the web.
And so we had a section of our
website with player stories,
and it became immensely popular.
And initially it was kind
of predictable silly stories
about superheroes or whatever.
But very rapidly, we started
seeing these very heartfelt,
deep, real stories.
There was one of the early
ones was a woman who got out
of an abusive relationship.
And she was trying
to tell that story
to inspire other women
in the same position.
Other ones were how this guy
had a horrible senior year
in high school.
Some of these were
just like almost rants.
One was a rant about
how they hated this one
particular Starbucks
in New York City
because the homeless
people would go in there
and drink the cream.
Just weird things like that.
It was amazing that these were
people that probably never
would have written these
things down at all.
They didn't really
have a creative outlet.
But once they started
playing the game
and they started actually
recreating these things
and they found how
easy it was to share,
and also these people
would post these stories
and other people would
comment about them, rate them.
And for a lot of
these people who've
never once been told
they were creative
or done anything interesting,
to just have five people,
random people, say
that was really cool,
made them tremendously
motivated.
They would go back and do
much more elaborate stories
after that.
It took very little positive
reinforcement or recognition
for these people to dive in.
And obviously, these people had
things they wanted to express.
So basically, this game for them
turned into a creative tool,
a tool of self-expression.
And so we later kind of
developed that in The Sims
where you're capturing movies
and much more elaborate things.
And of course,
along side of games
there's been this really
interesting field of machinima
where people are actually
using game engines to tell
stories very, very cheaply.
And so that's something,
for the same reason,
has been growing up
along side of games