[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: More
than anything else,
I've found the psychology to be
the really tricky, challenging
part of game design.
The technology is
advancing every year.
What we can do on
modern computers
makes me as a designer
feel almost unlimited.
You can do amazing things
on these electronics.
Player psychology though,
human brains are not advancing.
They're the same as they have
been a hundred years ago.
We have to learn how it works.
What are the inner
workings of that computer
and how can we exploit it
and use it to our advantage?
There's actually a great book,
I think it's out of print now,
it's called "Maps of the Mind".
Each page was kind of
a visual representation
of one psychological theory.
It might be Maslow's
Pyramid or Freud and the Id.
Each one of them was
a different way, a bit
different perspective, on the
human mind and human psychology
and the way it worked.
Each one is kind of a tool
and has its particular purpose
and works well in certain
situations and not well
in others.
None of them are really
the right approach
that I'm going to
religiously adhere to.
But each one contains
something valuable
that might be of use
to me in the future.
Maslow's Pyramid turned out
to be very useful for The Sims
for instance.
[VIDEO GAME AUDIO]
The vary base core
of The Sims had
to do with feeding the
motives of The Sims--
hunger, entertainment,
sleep, all those things.
We started building very,
very simple little prototypes
that was just a set of
sliders and buttons.
I could press a button for
food, sleep, entertainment,
and basically trying to
balance these little sliders.
At some point, we decided one
of the major goals in The Sims
would be to have them actually
go to work and earn money
so you can go out and buy
more junk for your house.
Now, we basically had a reason
to get all these sliders up
to some state that they go
to work in a good state.
The better their state is,
the more money they earn.
So we're connecting
these base motives
to the larger aspirations,
which is exactly what Maslow's
Pyramid was all about.
The game designer is
really kind of playing
with the player's psychology.
By giving them certain
freedoms, certain limitations,
certain goals
states, you're trying
to get them into a
certain motivation
within this little world
that you've crafted
and make them want
to do things or want
to avoid things happening.
You basically want to set up
this structure in their head
that they're motivated to
do this and avoid that.
But you want to have
an environment where
they start feeling strong
motivations for their actions.
And then, now it's up
to them to start testing
their model against your model.
They start building that
mental model against your game.
I think it was PT Barnum
that said something like,
no entrepreneur ever went broke
overestimating the intelligence
of the American public.
Kind of my version of that
is, no game designer ever
went wrong by overestimating
the narcissism of their players.
And so the more it
is about the player,
the more the player
is celebrated,
the more the player is the
center of that universe,
generally, the
more they like it.
At the very beginning, one
of the chief fundamental
components of game
design, one of the skills
that you really want to
master as a game designer,
is the ability to build a mental
model in your player's head.
And this is really
kind of an art form.
This is something I've
learned from magic actually,
from magicians, is that when
a magician is performing
a trick, what they're
actually doing
is they're getting the
viewers, the audience,
to craft a mental model
of what's going on,
but they're getting
them to craft
exactly the wrong mental model.
Such that, you think
this is in my hand,
you think this is my hand, I
pull the handkerchief back,
it's not.
I've actually, thought a
lot of different techniques
as a magician, got you to build
an incorrect mental model,
and then when I
do the reveal, you
see that hey, my
mental model was wrong.
In fact, what the
magician was doing
was some other
manipulation over here.
And as a game designer,
we take that kind
of approach in some ways.
We're actually having
our players interact
with little pieces of computer
memory and code and interface
buttons, but in
their head they're
building an entirely
different model.
There's a world that they're
in with verbs and nouns
and affordances and agency
and actions and possibilities
and goal states.
That's what we're actually
building in our player's head.
And so in some sense,
the game designer
is a much more elaborate
magician doing this.
We're modeling
things all the time.
You're modeling other
people all the time.
I'm imagining what my
friend is thinking about me.
I'm imagining what
they know about me
and I try to be
consistent with that.
So I'm not only building
a model of my friend,
but I am building a model
of their model of me.
It's recursive.
I can remember
what they have seen
me do, how they've
see me behave,
and I have a very rough sense
of what their model of me
is and I try to be
consistent with that.
So this modeling is pretty deep
and recursive in that sense.
You can put any kid in
front of a video game
and right off the bat they
start mashing buttons, looking
at what's happening,
they observe, and it's
very much the scientific
process where they are doing
hypothesis, experiment,
look at the result,
go back refine the hypothesis,
experiment, look at the result.
It's that iterative
scientific process.
And that is basically model
building of a different sort.
Now, in building
models we take in a lot
of data, a lot of examples.
And from that, we
started looking
for patterns in that data and
things that are different,
things that are the same,
and after that we start
building abstractions
out of that--
these what we call schema.
And basically,
these are patterns
that we see in the world.
Any kid can tell
you the difference
between a dog and a
cat, and that's a schema
that we have internally.
And it's really a very
fine set of features
to distinguish the difference
between a dog and a cat.
But it's a schema that
we have, and so we
can look at any new
dog or cat and say
right off the bat it's a dog
or a cat against our schema.
Now, from that we started
building more elaborate things
called models.
These schema,
these patterns, now
become the components of the
models that we're building.
And that now influences
our behavior.
We behave against these models,
basically running scenarios.
Should I do this or that?
Should I get this
job or that job?
Should I say A or B?
And so all of our
behavior really
is based against us playing
these models in our head
about what we should do.
Now schema are really
interesting in that we
have schema for some
different things.
For instance, in
a restaurant, we
have this rough idea
of things that happen
when we go into a restaurant.
Not all these things always
happen, but in general, that's
a pretty good schema
for what to expect
when I walk into a restaurant.
Some of the schema that
we are dealing with.
Classification, who are the
good guys and the bad guys?
Causality, if you find a
pot of gold, you'll be rich.
Empathy, if you see a hungry
dog, you feel bad for it.
Agency, if you have control,
you can command your fate.
We have schema for all of
these different things.
And you're controlling
the player's schema
in some sense as a designer by
what you present them with, how
it operates, how it behaves.
When I see five turtles come at
me in a row and all attack me,
I start saying, OK, turtles
are a bad thing in this game.
That's a schema I'm building
as I play the game, part
of a model building.
And games, in some sense,
are generating these worlds
from the models.
So a game is really almost
the reverse of science.
Science is really taking all
this data from the world,
compressing it down into a
very concise, small rule set--
laws of physics.
Games take a very
concise codebase
and try to expand it into a
wide range of possibilities
that the player's going
to encounter in your game.
And then the player is trying
to reverse engineer that process
and now build a concise
representation of that.
So it's really kind
of interesting the way
these models are
coming and going
against the data and the
operation of the world.
But again, these
mental models are key,
I think, for a game
designer to realize
that's what they're building.
The mental model that we're
trying to create in the player
is something that may or may not
have a purpose really for you.
I might be building
a mental model
for some player of SimCity
about how cities work.
But I know, as a
designer of SimCity,
that that model is not
going to be correct.
There are things
about SimCity that
do not match the real world.
A lot of times,
games and filmmakers
as well will actually
build a model
that they know is
incorrect, because that's
what the players expect.
SimCity 2000 I know that if
the nuclear power plant caught
on fire there'd be a giant
nuclear explosion, which
doesn't happen.
It doesn't happen that way.
There's fallout, but
no nuclear explosion.
But all the players
expected that.
And when it didn't happen they
were saying, why didn't it
blow up?
So we made it behave that way.
In movies, you see people
shooting guns all the time
and never hitting each
other, or cars always
blow up in the crash.
All these things that you're
building the wrong model
in the player's head
compared to reality,
but as an enjoyable experience,
they kind of expected--
why didn't the car blow up?
So I'd say that what
is correct is really
the open question here.
Are you trying to build--
if I'm trying to
build a training
simulator for an
airline pilot, then
yes, I want that simulator
to actually train
them to build a model of the
way that plane really behaves,
and that's my target.
As an entertainment designer,
and if I'm designing
a city simulator and--
most of these
players are not going
to be designing
a city like this.
In fact, real cities are
not designed with one person
as the overlord like that.
It's much more political.
So I'm not that concerned that
we take liberties like that.
As an interactive experience,
we want this whole thing
to be centered on the player.
And understanding that
every player is different
is kind of key to that.
We want every player to be
able to take their own path,
have some freedom,
agency, within our games.
So we need to start thinking
about how the players see
themselves, their identity.
Now, everybody wraps a lot of
things around who they are.
When you present
yourself to other people,
depending on the context,
there's a place we live,
your neighbors.
I'm from Ohio, whatever it is.
Your job, your profession,
your skill set.
Hobbies, things that you do.
Or brands, products that you
maybe have some allegiance to.
All these things are
components of your identity.
And when you're interacting
with other people,
these are ways in which
you mark yourself.
You kind of surround
yourself with these things
saying this is part of
what defines who I am.
Now, we actually have a lot
of very personal aspects
to our identity,
but also, we have
communities that we live in.
Sometimes real
geographic communities,
other times online communities.
Some of these are
based upon locations,
some are based upon
interest, profession.
And then there's
the world around us
that we all kind of share what's
going on in the wider world.
It's almost like this
target with successive rings
going outward.
The innermost ring
being the most personal,
the thing that most
defines me as most unique.
Going to the very general.
We all live in the same world.
Now, we find that as
players get into games,
they kind of all come
in in the same way.
They're all kind
of casual players.
I'm going to check this
out, see what it's like.
Some people really get into it.
Other people might play it for
a little while, put it aside,
this game isn't for me.
But the players that
kind of keep going down
that path into your
game have a trajectory,
and depending on what
kind of game it is,
they can take different paths
into that what a lot of times
becomes a community.
For The Sims, we
actually had a lot
of casual players
started to turn
into what we called collectors.
They would go on
the web and they
found a lot of other people
had made objects or characters
that they could download
into their game,
and so they would start
collecting specific things.
Some people would actually
kind of specialize
their collections.
I want to do Wild West
stuff or Star Wars things
or whatever it is.
Other people were
actually the ones
starting to build these
collections on their web sites.
And at first they would make
a few objects, make a website,
but then other
people would start
contributing to their website.
Some of these websites
grew very large
and even became subscription.
People were paying money
just to download content
that other players had created.
And the core creators that were
doing the really cool stuff
were the ones kind of
feeding these websites.
So there was kind of an
ecology that was happening here
over time as the player
got more and more involved,
and then it became more and
more part of their identity.
The ones that were
actually creating
this stuff for The Sims,
this was their hobby.
They spent many hours
doing this stuff.
And it was kind of how
they saw themselves
as a creator of
stuff for this game.
In a lot of ways, it's kind
of like an ecological pyramid,
and the numbers kind of
decrease as you go up,
but there's also a base to
that pyramid that's supporting
the upper people, the creators.
The very skilled people
who are making cool things
are supported by this very
wide base of casual players.
There's flow within this
ecology of recognition.
Casual players are saying,
oh, that person's stuff
is the best, or this
is the coolest website.
And that's what was fueling the
people building these things.
They just liked having
that recognition.
That whole thing has
given rise to very large
online communities around games.
And these communities--
a lot of times
the people involved
in these communities
don't even play
the game anymore.
That's actually kind
of interesting to me
is that the people that were
doing The Sims for instance,
some of them were running
big websites, creating
all this stuff, and
they hadn't played
the game in months or years.
But still, these were
people they knew,
they had relationships, they
had a place in this community,
they had recognition,
they had a reputation.
And for a lot of people, these
games become kind of a hook
into a social network of
sorts or different types
of social networks.
And there are other games that
are more competitive where
they're actually playing
professional sports
like in these games and there
are whole leagues and things
like that.
So these games, for
a lot of people,
became a doorway into
these communities,
which now becomes a
very integral part
of their identity, which is
kind of a different thing
than having the game just be
focused on what the player is
doing in the game.
But now the game is
kind of part of how
they think about themselves
and how they present themselves
to the world.
I've heard a lot of
stories from players
about how they've taken
their game experiences
and how it's changed their life.
For some people, they
became storytellers.
They started making a few
stories, either Machinima
or whatever, uploaded
it, and a lot of people
liked it and loved their style
and the stories they told.
And so it really pushed
them into creative writing
or filmmaking.
I've talked to a lot of
people who actually played
SimCity went into
civil engineering
just because they
enjoyed dealing
with that kind of system.
Other people that have
gone into biology because
of SimAnt, things like that.
So sometimes it's motivational.
And in fact, in education I
think the fundamental issue
we have in education isn't
so much how we teach kids,
but it's how we motivate kids.
If you can get a kid
motivated in a subject,
they have plenty of resources
to go learn it on their own.
In fact, I have
three boys at home,
and they're learning
more on YouTube
right now than they
are in school by far.
And they're following
their own interests.
Once they get motivated--
my 8-year-old wants to
learn about Minecraft,
and he finds these
Minecraft videos,
and he can learn at his own pace
exactly what wants to learn.
So once you can get them
motivated about something,
just get out of
their way basically.