[MUSIC PLAYING]
One thing the game
designers really should know
is that, you know,
it's about the player.
You know, it's a
player-centered experience.
And the player is the one
driving that experience.
You know, it's the difference
between being on a roller
coaster and being in a car,
behind the steering wheel.
Now that player, because they're
holding the steering wheel,
they're responsible
for where they go.
They have choice they
have decisions to make.
And because of that,
they take ownership.
And that totally changes their
relationship to whatever it is.
You know, the fact
that they were the ones
to steer left or right, and
because it went off the cliff,
it was their fault, or
because they, you know,
won the lottery, they
did it because they
picked those numbers.
So I think that that's the
first and foremost thing,
is that when somebody feels
like they're in control
of a process, they own it.
And it now has a fundamentally
more personal connection
to them than something
that's one size
fits all, here's the ride,
get on it, hope you enjoy it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Flow is kind of a state that
the player can get into.
And I think of it as
basically something
that's right at the
limit of your abilities.
It's pushing you mentally.
But it's not too
easy, not too hard.
If it's too hard, it seems
random, it seems arbitrary,
it's frustrating.
If it's too easy, it's
predictable, it's boring.
Flow is putting you right on
that edge of your abilities,
and really testing them.
I used to actually race cars.
And there was kind
of a rule of thumb
in racing that if you didn't
crash 10% of the time,
you weren't trying hard enough.
You need to design the
game such that failure is
interesting and understandable,
so that go back and say, aha,
now I need to avoid the turtles
or whatever it is in the game.
And then you kind of
build and grow that model.
But also you're
building your ability
to problem-solve and strategize.
Every player is can be
different, different abilities,
different skill sets.
In a lot of ways, you
want to make the game such
that the player is the one
adjusting the difficulty.
You know, they can choose to
go a little bit further, try
for this harder thing, or
stick with the easy stuff
until they're more comfortable.
So in some sense, a lot of it
can be kind of player-paced.
There are more
advanced systems that
are called DDA, or Dynamic
Difficulty Adjustment,
where the computer,
behind the scenes,
is kind of watching
with the player's doing.
And if they're failing
too much, the computer
can actually lower
the difficulty level,
or increase it, you
know, if they're not
being challenged enough.
But in a lot of games, you
know, by giving the player
enough freedom but
also enticing them
to try for the hard
things-- you know,
if you try for
this harder thing,
you might get this
bigger reward.
So at that point, the player can
kind of choose their own level,
and put themself
in the flow state.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
There is a whole topic known
as failure-based learning.
You know, and-- you know,
we have this-- you know,
failure is a loaded
term, in that
we think of failure as bad.
I don't want to fail.
There was a great story I heard.
It was an art teacher
in an art class--
it was actually a pottery class.
And at the beginning
of this class,
the beginning of the year,
he did divided the class
into two halves.
And the first half he
said, OK, your final grade
is going to be based upon
one pot that you make.
I want you to make the best
pot you could possibly make,
and your grade is going
to be based upon that.
The other half of the class,
he said, OK, your grade
is going to be based on
how many pots you make.
I don't care how bad they are.
Just the more you make,
the better your grade.
At the end of the
year, of course,
it turns out that the
half of the class that
was building the
most pots were also
building the best ones by far.
They had built so many bad pots,
and had iterated so many times,
they learned very rapidly.
And by the end of
the class, they
were building
these amazing pots.
Whereas the other half that
was spending all their time
thinking about one pot that
they were going to build,
you know, never got anywhere.
So it was the failure that
accelerated their learning
on the other half.
You know, and when
players play games,
again, they are failing
most of the time.
And again, if you can
make it understandable,
humorous, enjoyable
in some way, then that
can be an enjoyable
process, especially when
you get past that first
failure to the next level.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[CHARACTERS GROANING AND
GRUNTING]
So as a designer, we're
constructing this middle model
in the player.
And it's important that we
ramp that model up smoothly
and gradually for the player.
You don't want to pile all
this complexity on them right
at the beginning of the game.
It's overwhelming.
You should actually present
them a simpler model.
They can start building,
from that simple model,
layers and layers of complexity
onto it in their head
as they encounter more and
more things in the game,
either through, you know,
more elaborate world items,
monsters, opponents,
abilities, tools, whatever.
So the designer,
in some sense, is
responsible for ramping that
model in the player's head.
Now, when you're playing
an interactive experience,
you're actually going
through this set
of kind of nested loops
of success and failure.
When you first
start playing Mario,
you start mashing the
buttons, and you find out
that that button makes
him jump, this control
makes him move side to side.
About 10 seconds for you
to kind of figure that out.
So there's that
kind of 10 seconds,
I don't know how to control
Mario, then I succeed,
and finally know
how to control him,
which brings me kind of to
the next level of interaction,
which is maybe more a minute.
I started encountering
objects in the world.
Is that good?
Is that bad?
I learn from that.
And then you go from kind of a
very tactical, very granular,
to longer and longer loops
of success and failure.
Now, every level,
you're probably
going to encounter failure.
And the failure actually
is something that--
most people are spending
most of their time
in a game failing,
really, at different ways
and different loops here.
And it's not that you
don't want the player
to encounter
failure, but you want
them to understand
the failure, and build
a model around that failure
so that next time they
will succeed.
That's part of the
motivation, is now
I understand that that's
good and that's bad.
Next time I will not
get stuck by that.
Let me show you an example of
that on the whiteboard here.
In a game like "The
Sims," you know,
basically you have
little characters
that you're controlling here.
And initially, you need to
understand first of all,
just how to make them move,
and walk around, and interact
with things, you know.
So in some sense, that's kind
of like the very first game loop
we're dealing with here.
On one side of that,
you know, is failure.
And you know, this
is me not being
able to control my character.
And once I've learned how
to make them walk around,
interact with things, you
know, then I've succeeded.
And this is, you know, this
is called interaction loop,
you know.
After that, you know, I
start dealing with-- they
have these little needs.
They get hungry, they get
tired, they want social,
they want entertainment.
And those things fail.
So right off the bat, you
know, they're sitting there,
and they're crashing on
energy, they're bored,
they're basically unhappy.
And so the next level loop
I really have to kind of do
is figure out how to
bring that happiness up.
So that's kind of
like the happy loop.
And that's a little
bit longer timescale.
You know, that takes several
minutes within The Sims.
And again, you
know, there's kind
of a success side to that and
a failure side to that loop.
Now there are also things,
you know, within these loops.
And we kind of keep going.
You know, the next
one might be economic.
At some point, they want to
start improving their house,
getting a job, getting
skills, you know.
So let's call that Jobs.
You know, and that's an
even longer loop here.
But a lot of games like "The
Sims," or creative games,
you know, also
involve, basically,
orthogonal creativity.
You know, so in addition to
playing the game, in addition
to kind of dealing with
all these game loops,
I'm doing this weird stuff,
like telling a story with this,
or trying to
replicate my family,
or just exploring, seeing, I
wonder if my Sim could do that.
And so there are
probably, you know,
other loops that are in a
different dimension, really,
than this-- kind of
more like there--
that don't have a lot
to do with me succeeding
on the overall
game's success curve,
but have more to do with
the player exploring
their own creativity,
their own expressiveness.
And some players, you know,
get totally invested in this,
and eventually start
ignoring that, you know.
But most games have some version
of these different loops,
you know.
And it might be learn to shoot,
then learn to unlock the door,
then learn to defeat the
evil boss at the end.
You know, this is
pretty much, you know,
the same graph of the player
building up this mental model.
So the player's,
you know, model--
the player's up here,
controlling this game.
And you know, in their head,
you know, they're basically
building this mental model--
you know, kind of
one layer at a time--
of your game.
And those layers of
that model are very much
aligned to these
interaction layers.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
As players are going
through these loops,
and slowly building
this model, you know,
again, really it's that
most of what they're going
to experience is failure--
again, and again, and again--
which doesn't sound very fun.
But it's the game designer's
job to present that in a way
that's entertaining,
and informative,
and that it's not frustrating.
I don't want to
be failing on, you
know, exactly the
same thing over,
and over, and over, especially
when I know why I'm failing.
Some games-- you know,
some platform games, you
have to time it exactly
right, and it's really hard.
And those can kind of get
very frustrating, you know,
when you know that you
have to acquire the skill,
and you can't quite acquire it.
So you're not
failing because you
don't know what you need to do.
It's just that it's
so hard for you
to kind of get into that
skill set, that sweet spot,
for some people it
becomes frustrating.
So when somebody
fails in a game,
you want it to be
understandable,
you want to be something
that they can overcome
once they understand it.
Also, again, humor
can be a great tool
to alleviate the frustration.
You know, when somebody fills
in a certain very basic thing
in a game, sometimes
you want to actually
have a variety of failure
states that become humorous.
So at least when
they're failing again,
and again, and again, it's not
exactly the same repetition
over and over.
You know, you might just
have different animations
for the same failure.
But again, the humor, I think,
can be a great tool here.
But if presented
right, you know,
players get very
motivated, when they
understand why they failed, to
then go back and do it again.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
The kind of games
I tend to make tend
to be more system-level games.
And you know, they
frequently-- like, you know,
"Sim City" or "The Sims"
involve you constructing
something that,
you know, gets more
and more elaborate over time.
As you achieve success, and
your city grows, or your Sims,
you know, get more
stuff in their house,
you're adding more
complexity to their world.
You know, in "The Sims,"
there's kind of this promise
that, oh, you buy this
crap for your Sims,
and it'll make them happy.
Get them a big-screen TV
here, or a better bed there.
But in some sense,
as you acquire
more and more of these items,
they become time bombs.
Each one of these things
has a failure state,
or some maintenance
requirement, or whatever.
So as you fill your house with
all this junk, what you're
really doing is these
things are potential time
sinks down the road, which
add complexity to their world,
and make it much more
difficult to play the game.
Same with "Sim City," you
know, first you're just,
you know, zoning a few
little plots of land,
and building a few roads.
And you see a few things pop
up, and pretty soon, they
need power.
OK, you give them power.
Now they need water,
now they want a school,
now they want a
hospital, now-- you know.
And so as they make
progress in the game,
and the system is growing, the
complexity is growing as well.
And so it's a very natural,
smooth ramp in complexity.
It's not like, OK, you
finished level 1, now here's
level 2, where we're
adding two more rules.
It's, you know, very smoothly
based upon-- and in some sense,
the player is asking for it.
You know, as a player,
you know, gets their city
to that size, of course
they need a hospital now.
So it totally fits, and it
didn't feel arbitrary either.
It kind of feels
natural in that way.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
It's not just how much
difficulty is in the path,
but also how many
paths are there.
You know, I think that the
really interesting games
are ones that allow
different paths
towards some kind of success.
And in particular,
the kind of games I do
don't even make
success that explicit.
You know, in "The
Sims," you can decide
you want them to have a good
job, or want them to be happy.
Same in "Sim City,"
you can want,
you know, the biggest
city you can build,
or the happiest residents,
or the least crime.
So in some sense, the player
is choosing the goal state.
Now each one of
these goal states
is going to have kind of a
different path of difficulty.
And so for me it's
more about, there's
a landscape here of paths
that the player can take,
and each one has
different peaks.
But none of these have a
cliff, where you hit the cliff,
and all of a sudden, you know,
now it's really hard to get up.
You know, they all have kind of
different motivations of slope
up those achievement peaks.
And that's something that, you
know, again, it's really hard.
It's an emergent
property, so it's
very hard to just say, OK,
here's how we code that.
A lot of times, players will
find exploits around it.
Or it'll turn out
that, you know, again,
pressing the red button
is not that obvious.
So this is, again,
something we actually
will capture metrics on.
We will actually
have a lot of people,
as we start getting
more and more testers,
we're capturing metrics--
how long is somebody spinning
in that stage or this stage?
How many people are failing
on this point or that point?
And so that's stuff that you all
want to make fairly parametric,
that you can adjust fairly
granularly in testing.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Rewards in the game
can come in many forms.
You know, there's
just the advancement--
how far did I get in the game,
or there are special abilities
that you might gain that now
allow you to achieve things
you could not achieve before.
I think sometimes rewards are
a little overly-relied-upon,
you know, when you have
power-ups and stuff in a game.
It's just it gets, you
know, rote, boring,
a little too obvious.
I think a lot of the really
interesting player rewards
are things that they think
they came up with himself,
or they discovered
this thing in the game.
And I think discovery
is a huge part of this,
is that if you leave areas of
the game that are maybe closed
off to the player,
but at some point,
you know, just open one
of these little gates
and let them see that, hey,
there's a lot of stuff hidden
in here if you look
a little bit deeper
or try a little bit harder.
And players love that.
You see things-- you know,
people playing "Grand Theft
Auto" or whatever, and they
manage to get on top of places
they weren't supposed to
be able to, or do things--
exploits.
Then of course, they
make a movie of it,
and it becomes kind of
a machinima of sorts.
I remember back in
"Sim City 2000," which
is a very old game,
we had, you know,
of course landscape,
train, rivers, you know.
But we actually programmed in
that, you know, once in a very,
very seldom while-- like if you
were playing the game for 100
hours, it might
happen for, you know,
a few seconds in 100 hours--
we actually had this
little Loch Ness
Monster appear in the
water, pop his head out.
And there was kind of
rumors amongst the players
that, I think I saw a
monster in the water.
No, no, no, I've
never seen that.
Somebody, once, eventually
got a screenshot of it.
It was like this very
hard-to-achieve reward.
Just kind of
capturing a screenshot
of this one little thing.
And it didn't help them
in the game at all.
But they were so motivated
to do this, and capture it,
that it became--
actually a lot of
players were trying
to discover and take a picture
of the Loch Ness Monster.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MAN PURRING WITH PLEASURE]
[WOMAN MOANING]
Rewards are just a mechanism in
a game that you put in there,
you know, maybe to help guide
a player in a certain direction
or achieve certain levels.
But the incentive
in a game really
is coming from the
process of the player
playing that game--
whatever that is, you know.
And I think that's
something that's
coming internally
from the player,
not externally from
the game designer.
But the process that
they're going through--
and it might be a
creative process,
it might be a
skill-based process,
it might be a social,
you know, kind
of challenging process,
that's something
that the player kind of innately
has a desire to achieve.
And that's a much,
much broader thing,
and it's a much
deeper thing, too.
You know, I think
that's why people really
will get really
hooked on a game,
is their own internal incentive.
You know, I want to
get to a level 30
in "Warcraft," or this or that.
They come up with their own
goals, really, for that.
Rewards in a game are really
like these little mechanisms
that the, you
know, game designer
puts in there which kind
of moderate the gameplay.
So I'd say they're very,
very different things.
And the player
incentive is really