[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: As a
designer, you're
putting a player into
this world of yours,
and through their interactions
and freedom and agency that you
give them in your
world, you're actually
kind of developing a
language with the player.
The players are basically
learning this language
in playing the game,
and it's the designer
that's creating the world that
is defined by that language.
There's an interesting
aspect to games, which is--
and this idea was way
before computer games--
of the magic circle.
And this is the idea,
especially in social games,
that you have kids
come together and they
decide they're going to
play whatever, hopscotch,
and the players of the
game are basically now
within this thing we
call the magic circle.
They are bound by the
rules of that game.
Other people might be outside
observing, watching the game,
and they're not in that circle.
In some sense, you're kind of
building a temporary community
with the players within
that game and they're all
basically bound by the game
rules and living in that world
together.
This is, in some sense, one
of the fundamental parts
of game language.
Are you playing or not?
Who's playing in
that game right now?
As a language within
games, I think
that we do have the
same types of grammar
that real language has.
In the world,
things are basically
kind of nouns, verbs,
and adjectives.
I might go out the door to
see this dog barking at me.
The dog is basically the
noun, it's the thing.
The verb might be bite.
I'm afraid he's
going to bite me.
Adjective is mad.
He's a mad dog,
he's barking at me.
Based upon that, I will
you decide me run fast away
from the dog, whatever.
That you can almost interpret
everything in the world
according to these
parts of speech.
In a game, players will
encounter the same thing.
What is that?
What can it do?
What does my agency allow
me to do against it?
And so that's the
kind of language
that the players need to learn
in your game very rapidly
and feel very comfortable
and almost transparent
in learning that.
When you're designing what
the language of your game is--
the nouns, verbs, adjectives--
of course, it depends entirely
on the setting in which you're
putting a single player into.
You can describe a setting
or show a player a screen
and tell them, what would you
imagine wanting to do here?
I think that's a
good starting point.
As a player, what are the things
I think I should be able to do?
What things occur to
me right off the bat?
And you can actually
just talk to people
and show them the setting
and see what they say,
see what the most
common answers are.
As they move through
your space, however
that space is displayed,
things will occur to them.
I wish I could do that.
Can I move this?
Can I pick that up?
Can I put something there?
And so for a lot people,
it's just going to be--
once they immerse themselves
in this little world,
they're going to
be a set of things
that they would like to try.
And if you give
then a goals state,
say okay, try to do this, it's
going to be much more specific.
Oh, okay.
Well, in that case, can I
move, can I open that door,
do I need a key?
That's where you're
going to start
deciding how much
freedom or agency
does the player
have in this world?
What are the things in which
they're going to manipulate?
And what kind of
interface are we
going to basically
give the player
so they do that very naturally?
And you also need to present
these things in the world such
that it's fairly obvious
that these are nouns--
you can manipulate-- or
part of the game world, part
of the game actions.
And I think that you're
informing the player
about these things in a
lot of different ways.
Sometimes it's
just the art style.
These things stand out a little
bit against the background
and so they're important.
A lot of times you'll
have like the background
trees and landscape is
a little more muted,
whereas the foreground things
like maybe tanks and Jeeps
are more saturated in color.
So it could just be artistic.
It could be the way you
highlight these things,
the way they intimate.
So in some sense,
you're kind of informing
what are the important nouns
in a scene by the visuals.
And the verbs are going
to be very dependent
upon the interface and the
point of view of the game,
whether it's first person,
third person, whatever.
For instance, I show
somebody a train
and say, okay, you're going
to build a city here, and ask
them, what's the very first
thing that would occur to you?
And people might say roads
or houses or whatever it is.
But they'll start telling you
verbs they wouldn't expect
to play with in this place set.
If it's a first person
game and they're
trying to escape
something, they're
going to be looking for doors,
keys, a whole set of things
will occur to them, and a whole
set of verbs will occur them.
And at some point,
you're going to start
developing this language--
verbs, nouns, and adjectives.
Also part of the
language, metaphors
are very, very useful
as a tool for designers,
so that the player
can come in and have
at least some grounding
for what kind of a system
they're dealing with.
And even if it's not direct,
it can be an indirect metaphor.
Command and Conquer,
which is one of the games
I used to play a
lot, basically me
and my friend used to play
with our little model tanks
and make up rules and have
these whole little battles
with our little toy tanks.
And it was basically Command
and Conquer brought to life.
A game like Quake or Doom
or one of these first person
shooters, it's kind of like
kids running around playing
Cowboys and Indians.
It's the same basic
activity and you
know when you get
in there, oh yeah,
this feels just like that.
The Sims I used to
refer to as dollhouse.
Really, that's the
metaphor for The Sims.
When you see The Sims,
it's a little house
with little characters,
and it pretty much
is like an animated,
brought to life, dollhouse.
When I was building
SimCity, I really
kind of felt like in some sense
it was a digital train set.
People own these model train
sets, recreate little towns,
and I had several train
sets when I was a kid.
And I wanted SimCity
to kind of have
that feel of crafting this
little world that came
to life, this little automata.
But I designed it, I
built it, it had dynamics
and it could live
or grow or die.
But for me, that
metaphor of the train set
was kind of like a guiding
principle for SimCity,
and even when it came
to how we visualize it
and how the graphics look.
We tried to kind of make it
look like a little train set.
I reference a lot these kind
of childhood experiences,
whether it's Cowboys and Indians
or playing with model trains.
These aren't things that were
invented during my childhood.
These were actually
activities that
were probably around for
hundreds if not thousands
of years.
People were building small
recreations of real spaces
or playing games where they
ran around and played tag
or whatever.
These are kind of
basic aspects of play.
A lot of these
dynamics and activities
and thought
processes that people
are doing in digital
entertainment, digital games,
are things that they've
done before in other formats
before they had computers
and all that stuff.
I'm certainly not advocating
that every idea that you
come up with has to
have some precedent
either in your childhood or in
history or gaming in general.
In fact, I'm sure there are
a lot of very cool, unique
experiences that are totally
unique to this medium