[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT (VOICEOVER):
As you start
to refine your
prototypes, you'll
reach a stage where you
need to define an aesthetic.
The visual aesthetic
is going to add
a whole new layer of meaning
and depth to your game.
This is one of your primary ways
of communicating to the player.
Finding your own style is
up to you as the designer.
I would tend to approach, you
know, finding and discovering
an art style I think
very much in the same way
that I would approach, you
know, game concept research.
Basically go out and look.
You know, there are a
million references out there.
Not just games obviously.
You know, back in historical
fine art, or in whatever.
You could just imagine
all these different areas
to grab visual inspiration from.
You know, we got a huge
amount of material inspiration
from those comic book
covers from the '40s.
And that was a really
rich body of work
that had a very cohesive
style and feel to it.
You know, sometimes
it'll be something
that you find like that,
that you kind of reference,
and say, we want it to
kind of feel like that.
Other times, it might
be something kind
of up and coming.
It's funny how even,
you know, nowadays
I see kids playing
these retro games.
Or they play
"Minecraft," you know,
which is incredibly,
you know, basic visuals.
But, you know, like Lego, it
has become a style to them.
You go and look at these
Lego movies, which are great,
and it's amazing that they make
these amazingly entertaining,
very visually rich
movies, you know,
out of a Lego world,
rendered, and, of course,
animated, you know,
much more differently
than you can do with real LEGOs.
But yet, as a style
it's delightful.
So I think that there are a
lot of things that may not
obviously, right off
the bat, feel like, oh,
that's a good visual style.
But if you think
about certain things
a little more deeply
to the next level,
you know, how could
that be a style?
You know, what
would it look like?
How would it animate?
You might discover regions
that are very unique.
I kind of like the
games that I work on
to have almost a toy
like feel to them.
You know, like bringing up
a little bit more saturation
on the colors.
Maybe things being a
little bit more abstracted.
Feeling a little more, again,
you know, kind of model train
like.
To me that kind of makes it feel
more playful and approachable.
One of the things that I
really enjoy looking at
is things like tilt
shift photography,
you know, where they're
actually taking pictures
of the real world, and now
making it look like a model
by changing the depth of
field, and the saturation,
and a few other things.
It's funny how you can
take one of those photos,
the original photo.
And it's of some downtown area.
Do a tilt shift version of it.
And now it looks
like something that I
want to touch, and grab, and
play with, and manipulate.
Instantly I have this
instinct to go in and start
imagining things that I
would want to do with it.
In some sense, it's an
invitation to agency.
You know, it's
saying, this is a toy.
This is a model.
It's here for you to
manipulate, play with.
Go at it.
You know.
So I think in a
subtle way, to me,
by making it feel a little more
toy like or model like, you're
kind of getting the player
into that mindset that this is
something for you to interact
with, not something for you
to just sit back and look at.
One of the things I did on
"Spore" that I really enjoyed--
and this is in the
fairly early stages--
is I went back and I was
collecting, just downloading
hundreds of these images that
were appearing on the pulp
comic books back in
the '50s and '40s.
And these are like science
fiction stories or, you know,
whatever.
And it was always
like, you know,
some weird tentacled
alien holding
a blonde who's passed
out, and the spaceship
in the background.
The things in those
images, not just the way
they were rendered, but even
just the items, you know,
there was usually some kind of
alien, some kind of spacecraft,
some alien planet, some
muscle clad astronaut.
But I loved looking at just
the style of those comic book
covers.
Yeah.
In fact, we printed
them all out,
put them all over the office.
And it kind of became a guiding
principle for the entire game.
And it gave it a consistency.
And almost, you
know, I don't even
think it would be nostalgic
for any kid playing this.
They probably didn't
even see those covers.
But yet, there was
almost a whimsy
to it that it brought into the
game at a very subtle level.
The visual style
within my games,
you know, initially it was
on these 8-bit computers.
And, you know, we were counting
how many pixels we had,
how many colors.
And it was really
severely limited.
Over time, you know, those
limitations eased up more
and more, until,
at some point, we
were getting a high
powered graphics card
with pixel shaders and whatnot.
In which case, you know,
we got to the point
where we could achieve pretty
high levels of realism,
which I didn't really
feel like I needed.
But on the other hand, we
were able to use these things
in ways that were
kind of unexpected.
Like, for instance, in
"Spore" one of our programmers
discovered that--
I think it was Kate Compton--
that she could use the pixel
shaders and the graphics card
to actually simulate
turbulence on a gas giant.
And she was getting like these
beautiful turbulence patterns.
And it's just very simple
manipulations of the UV
coordinates within
the graphics card.
So I think that those kind
of opportunities, you know,
things that we never
would have-- you know,
if we had to just do that from
scratch, calculate it all out,
we never would've done it.
But also, things more like
getting the player more
involved and more creative.
So the fact that we could do
procedural animation in "Spore"
was really a result of the
horsepower and the programming.
And it reflected itself in
the fact that, you know,
the graphics looked
in the style.
But the really important part
was the player created it.
And, you know, at the point,
it doesn't even really
matter so much what style it is.
If a player created it, it's
a whole different ballgame.
And so I think I've
been, on the art side,
you know, kind of more
in the direction of what
can we do to have the
player more responsible?
More creative?
More involved in these assets?
You know, in a way that--
where it's natural and fun.
Well, I've actually had
the luck and privilege
to work with really
great art directors.
You know, and
generally, for me, it's
more been a matter of
their vision bringing
really good alternatives to me.
You know, so I usually have
two or three really good
alternatives to choose from.
And I don't feel like I can
really take the responsibility
for the quality of how that
ended up, because I really
think it was my art
director that, you know,
had a lot more to do
with it than I did.
But in general, you know, when
confronted with alternatives,
you know, I would tend to
say, OK, which one of these
feels more playful to me?
Which one of these
feels like something I
would want to go in, and pick
up, and grab, and manipulate?
That's the way I would just
kind of view it as a designer.
When we started working on
the very early ls of "Spore,"
the very first level is
microscopic, a little creature
swimming around in
a drop of water.
My art director I worked with
for many years, Ocean Quigley--
Ocean and I both, as
kids, had microscopes.
You know, I still
have a microscope.
And we started
thinking, OK, what
would this look like under
a microscope, under a slide?
And Ocean would actually
kind of prototype that.
And there was this thing when
you had the old microscopes
that, you know, as you move the
focus lever just a little bit,
you know, things here were
now going out of focus.
And things deeper
were going into focus.
You're actually
manipulating the Z plane
where the focus was set.
And so you were actually able
to move in that third dimension,
you know, through a drop of
water, or whatever it was.
And we both thought about that.
And then Ocean went back and
found a way to render it such
that he could take
any of the planes,
and focus or defocus it
at, you know, his whim.
And we could have several
of these in a row.
So you could have,
you know, layers
of this that were out of
focus, but only one layer that
was really in focus.
That actually kind of
brought up the idea that, OK,
maybe as you're playing
this cellular game
that you're actually
getting larger and larger.
In which case you'd be moving
from one plane to the next.
So as your thing
grew, we would now
defocus the layer
that you were on
and bring into
focus the layer that
was above you, which
were much bigger things
that you just saw as
fuzzy blobs before.
Then as soon as you grew to that
size, they became, you know,
in focus, and now part
of your game world.
So you were only
interacting with that layer
that was in focus.
So that was kind of a back
and forth thing that Ocean
and I did for a few
weeks, you know,
kind of coming up with and
then realizing that idea.
But it became kind of very
fundamental to the way
that part of the game worked.
Finding a good art
director is probably
going to be very similar to
finding a good sound director.
You want somebody who
listens, first of all,
and tries to understand,
you know, your vision.
Somebody who can come up
with ideas that you can't.
You know, maybe go
off in creative areas
that they are aware of because
of their specific expertise,
you know, whether it be
sound, or art, or whatever.
Bring them back to
you in a format,
you know, to where they
offer you some choice.
And I think that there's no,
you know, one size fits all.
Sometimes, you know, you'll want
a very, very particular style
as a designer.
And you don't
really want somebody
giving you five
other styles when
you know you want that style.
In which case you might,
you know, look for somebody
who specializes in that.
But at other times,
you know, you
might be a little more
open to, you know,
should it be more like
this or more like that?
Should it be more toy like?
More realistic?
Should it be darker?
Should it be more humorous?
I think that if you can speak
in that kind of a language,
you know, to anybody
on your team,
no matter what they're
doing, you know,
that I really think we want to
go for humor and whimsy here,
or I want it dark
and Gothic here,
if they can now interpret
that and come back to you
with really good alternatives
that feel right to you,
I mean, that's how you
know you've got a good one.
You know, if you're telling them
you want to go in this style,
but they keep pushing
you to Disney,
then, you know, they've kind
of got their own agenda,
or they've got their own dogma.
It also depends on
the size of your team.
You know, if it's a very small
team your art director is also
going to be one of your
artists, maybe your only artist.
If you're on a big
team, the art director
is really going to be more
managing a team of artists.
And so your art director
will have the opportunity
to find the right artist to
match that style for you.
Really you want somebody
that's going to mesh
with you, in particular.
I think that somebody who might
be a great art director for me
might be a really bad
choice for somebody else.
So, you know, first and
foremost, you have to have--
really kind of enjoy
collaborating with them.
You know, and I think
that's true of, you know,
most of your team.
That these are going
to be the people who
you're going to be working
alongside of for a long time.
You're going to be
putting a lot of time,
and passion, and
effort into this.
And if you don't
actually really enjoy
being around these people,
and enjoy working with them,
it's going to be work, you know.
But if you really
enjoy the process
of being with these people,
and collaborating, and creating
something with them, it's
going to be something