[MUSIC PLAYING]
{}
WILL WRIGHT: There are
tools, or mechanisms,
or patterns of
interaction that you can
use that you have the player--
this kind of creativity,
this kind of affordance,
this kind of agency.
Underneath the hood, you
know, the game is actually--
[BABY CRIES]
--doing some causal
connection between when
the player does
that, this happens,
or here's the limitation.
And it really kind of comes down
to an affordance or an action
that the player is
allowed in a game
and how the game
response to that action,
and it kind of defines
what the challenge is.
If it's a locked door,
what is the puzzle, or what
are the items needed
to unlock that door?
If it's an exploration
thing, what path
do you have to take through
this maze to get to the exit?
If it's a resource
allocation thing,
it's what are the
basic resources?
How they being consumed?
How are they being earned?
Each one of these is kind of
what we call a game mechanic.
They're like little closed
system of somehow interaction,
balance, economy that
you can connect together
to make a larger
interactive experience.
Mechanic is some kind
of process going on
between the player and the game
that you might attach metrics
to you.
Might attach a leaderboard
or scoring system to that.
But once you have that,
that process going on,
you can now use
that process either
to moderate the
player's progress.
You can use that process to,
you know, add difficulty.
You can use that process
to make the world more
interesting, more mysterious,
more kind of tangible.
You know, there
are a lot of ways
to use these kind of
what I'd call, like,
micro processes to build up
that larger process of here's
what it feels like
to be in that world.
In some sense, I think,
of this as the dynamics.
You know, as a player's
doing things in the game,
how is that game
responding to the player?
You know, what is the
conversation that the player's
having with the game system?
And each one of these mechanics
is kind of one type of phrase,
or interaction,
or you know, word
the player can kind of
express within that system
against the game, and the game
will respond in certain ways,
and the player's
kind of learning
to kind of converse
with the game system
through these mechanics.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
When we talk about
game mechanics,
you know, again, to
me these are parts.
OK, and you know, it
can be a part that's
been used many,
many times, or it
can be a brand new
part that you've
invented all on your own.
And to me, you know,
what really matters
is the whole that's
built out of these parts.
You know, so I might
have, let's say, you know,
a fuel injection unit, and an
engine, and a differential,
and wheels, and I start
putting these together
to make some kind of a car.
And maybe I decide I want
a flux converter, you know,
and I'm going to
invent a flux converter
and stick it in there.
That's great, you know,
but what really matters
is the entire car, you know.
How is that car going
to drive or not?
You know, with the
existing mechanics
that we have right
now, obviously we
can build, you know, a huge
number of different kind
of interactive experiences, but
every now and then, you know,
you might want that
flux converter.
You might want some
brand new thing.
I don't think it's that
you just kind of come up
with a cool mechanic and
say, how do I use it?
I think it's more like, here's
an interactive experience
that I want to create.
Now, what do I
need to create it?
And if it turns
out that, you know,
there's something
brand new, you know,
there's basically something you
need in this that you cannot
figure out an existing mechanic
that will provide that,
that's when you go
off and make your own.
I am very happy to go off
and make my own mechanics
if I need to.
I don't even really
think about it
so much in terms of, you know,
this is a new mechanic or not.
It's more like, this is the
right mechanic, you know?
Whether it was invented
by me or somebody else,
you know, I just, I think
there's always kind of,
like, the right part to fill
in that gap in your design.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
If we talk about
rules for a game,
I think that they are almost,
like, two kinds of rules.
You know, there are
the really overt rules
that you want to inform
the player about.
You know, you need to escape
the dungeon, or you know,
this is a torch, you
know, whatever it is,
you know, certain things you're
very clear with the player
about.
Right off the bat,
you're going to say, OK,
to control your character,
you use the [INAUDIBLE] keys,
or this, or that.
So again, some something
you're very overt about.
And other things that
they discover-- you know,
a trend that started
10, 15 years ago
is that part of the
gameplay, the early gameplay,
is the tutorial, and
you encounter objects,
you know, as part of directed
gameplay early on, and the game
itself is kind of teaching you
how to use a sword in "Zelda,"
how to do this, how to do
that, how to cast a spell.
But then there are
a lot of other ones
that you want to hide
from the player that
are under the hood,
that become mysterious.
And in a lot of ways,
you want your game world
to be kind of a black
box at some level.
And this is actually, it kind of
gets to the idea of immersion,
that a lot of times somebody
will look at a system--
when people look at the
simulation in "Sim City,"
they start imagining, you
know, this ungodly collection
of mathematics and things
calculating this incredibly
complicated city.
In fact, it's far,
far simpler than that.
You know, in fact, we found a
fairly nice emergent system,
so it was a fairly
simple set of rules
that kind of emerged into
the complexity of a city
simulation.
If players, you know,
saw under the hood,
in some sense it
would kind of destroy
a lot of the illusion
of complexity
there, the illusion of life.
It's very similar
to the same reason
why we didn't have
the Sims speak,
you know, in a known language
because as soon as they started
repeating the same
things over and over,
they would seem incredibly
simple and robotic.
But when you can't
quite understand them,
you tend to read in a lot more.
There was this thing that we
started calling "the simulator
effect" after watching
the first, you know,
kind of batch of players
playing "Sim City" a lot,
and then some of our
later games that--
They would write letters to
us, Oh, I love this game,
and they would
describe stuff that
happened to them in
the game in letters
they were writing to us.
And they would describe, you
know, things like, you know,
the airplane crashed over here,
and it hit the power line,
and it caused a surge there, and
then this thing caught on fire.
And they would describe
all these causal linkages
that did not exist in the game.
You know, I knew
they did not exist,
but in the player's
head, they did.
You know, nothing about the game
dissuaded them from the fact,
and so they were building
up their own models
of the way this
simulator was working,
you know, that were very
elaborate and interesting.
And that's when I
kind of realized
that there's certain parts
of a simulator like that
that you want to
keep a black box.
You know, the players,
you know, can actually
imagine their own simulation
usually far more interesting
than yours, you know, as
long as you present them
with enough scaffolding to
build that in their imagination.
And so we ended up calling that
"the simulator effect," that
when players are
imagining that your,
your world or your simulation is
more detailed, more rich, more
complicated than it actually
is, don't talk them out of it.
And so, you know, part
of exploring the world
is, in fact, kind of uncovering
these loops of complexity
in these rules, and so part of
learning the rules of the game
are actually embedded
in the game, which
is actually very natural
[MUSIC PLAYING]
There's this thing
called the Monte Carlo
method, which is
using chance basically
in the place of calculus.
You know, a lot of things
that would be simulated
in the natural
world, you know, we
have established mathematics,
which is linear calculus.
But it turns out that
for most of these things
with a computer, there's a whole
other approach that basically
can solve the same set of
problems, which is basically
throwing darts at a
dartboard, and you
have shapes on that dartboard
that are about, you know,
the right area.
I'm going to go
to the whiteboard
to kind of give you a simple
little illustration of this.
And just to keep
it very simple, you
know, let's assume
that we have some area
and that we have within
that area some regions.
You know, and maybe
this is the amount
of area developed, you know,
in "Sim City," or the areas
with police coverage,
whatever it is.
Now, normally if you
wanted to measure
what percentage of
this entire area
is occupied by these
blobs, you know,
there's some very
elaborate mathematics kind
of going down the
calculus path that you
would use to measure
that and give you
a pretty accurate answer.
But if you have a
computer, you know,
and computers are
very fast and good
at just doing simple
things repetitively,
it turns out there's a
much simpler technique,
and they call this the
Monte Carlo method, which
is that we just sit here, and
we just randomly throw darts
at this board.
You know, and then we just count
over time how many of the darts
land inside of these areas,
and how many land outside.
And you know, you throw a
few hundred darts at there,
you know, and it turns
out that, you know,
let's say out of 100 darts,
you know, 67 land outside
of these zones, and let's
say 33 land inside the zones.
That's the basic percentage.
You basically-- that's
33% of the area of that.
This is the kind of, you know,
simple mathematics, you know,
that we use a lot
in simulations.
And so this, in fact,
is relying very much
on these probabilities,
and it's the way
a lot of the emergence
that we get out of some
of these systems works as well.
So from the design
point of view,
it's amazing how you can build
super simple things like that
in place of what used to be very
kind of elaborate mathematics.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
There's another kind of chance,
though, that I encounter
as a designer, which
is that a lot of times
I'll be making something,
doing prototypes, whatever,
and something just
pops up unexpectedly.
You know, either we made a,
put a bug in the program,
or it's not behaving
the way I thought,
or something happens
that surprises me.
And through pure chance, I might
trip over some new mechanic,
or some new feature.
Or that reminds me of this;
let's try that, you know.
And this is like serendipity.
This is me, you know, kind
of accidentally discovering
something very cool, you
know, either in prototyping,
or testing, or
just even on paper
as I'm kind of thinking
through a design that
causes me to go off in a
totally different direction,
you know, tangent to where
I was going initially.
Now, this is often the
designer's point of view, you
how, kind of how you use
probability to your advantage.
You know, from the
player's point of view,
you know, again, there'll
be a lot of things happening
in your game that
might be purely random,
you know, and you know
that they're random.
The players are always going to
be trying to assign causality
to something.
You know, if all of a
sudden that torch goes out,
or there's a sound over there,
the player in their head
is going to be
building some model of,
what caused that to happen?
Was it something I did?
Is it some something
that caters it,
foreshadowing of some event?
And I think that
you actually want
kind of a balance
there a little,
you know, kind of
[INAUDIBLE] noise
so that there's some stuff
happening in the world that,
again, remains kind of
a black box to them,
whether, you know, from
their point of view
it's random chance, or it's
some elaborate, deep, you know,
behavior of your, you know,
your world the player is going
to assume it's some deep
behavior of your world,
I think, in most cases.
But if it's something that
the player did, and you
want clear feedback that
the player did this,
and the door
unlocked, that's when
you have to make sure you're
getting above that, that noise
level, and it's totally
signaled to the player.
And so you need to make sure
that the feedback you're
giving to the player
is signal and not
noise against this kind
of random world churning.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Well, because my games don't
have an overt in-state,
you know, I don't
think it really
changes the nature
of wanting to present
an interesting, challenging
kind of creative world.
I don't think that--
you know, I think
that's kind of
almost, worldbuilding
is almost a different
kind of level to that.
The chance and probability--
for a player, you know, again,
it can depend on the game.
If, you know, you're
playing Casino games,
you know, you're
kind of expecting
these things to be based
around chance and probability.
If you're playing something
like a first-person shooter,
you're kind of imagining that,
you know, if I aim at that guy,
it's going to hit that guy.
You know, I don't want a
chance of having a dud bullet,
or my bullet, you know,
going off target just
through random chance.
So I want my actions
to be clearly,
you know, kind of almost
deterministic in that sense.
So I think it depends
on the feature
of your world as to what
you're talking about.
If it's something like
"Sim City," and, you know,
when does a fire occur?
You know, that actually is a
little bit of a combination.
It's a combination
of, how much am
I done with my fire services?
But there's still a chance.
It's changing the probability
of a fire actually happening.
It could still happen even
if I have good fire coverage,
but the chance is lower.
And you know, for
the player, you know,
that's kind of the expectation
coming into a world like that,
and so really, I
think at that point
you're really kind
of falling back into,
what feels like an
expectation of the player?
You don't want the world
to feel like, you know,
arbitrary things are happening
for absolutely no reason.
You know, so even when a
fire occurs in "Sim City"
when there's a low
probability, the player
can imagine that occurring.
You know, it's not an
unimaginable situation.
What you really
don't want to do is
you don't want the
game to feel capricious
in terms of killing the
player for no obvious reason.
You know, that, you know,
is really a major no-no.
The player always wants to feel
like their success or failure
is coming back to their agency.
You know, it's
their fault. They're
the ones responsible
for their own fate.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Depending on the kind
of game you're doing,
you know, it does put the player
into a certain kind of mindset,
and they build a
certain kind of model,
whether it's like a first-person
kind of game with exploration
and combat, or it's a
third-person game with resource
management, you know,
they all, at some level,
share a set of features, share,
you know, certain amounts
of player agency.
They share world dynamics.
You know, so that's the level
at which these things are all
pretty common across there.
But you know, I
think there are so
many game mechanics that have
been used and so many more yet
to be discovered.
I think the designer
will develop an intuition
for which one of
these things they
want to put into
their palette of tools
and which ones they want to
become a master at because I
think that certain game
designers, you know,
get very specialized
and very good,
you know, within certain
kind of mechanics,
using certain parts
to build their games.
And over time, you know, you'll
start expanding that palette.
You'll start trying other ones.
You'll play other games, games
that you would not normally
play, and just to kind
of get a sense of what
those mechanics feel like.
Is that a tool that
I could use, a part
that I can use next time
I build, you know, one
of my game engines?
I think for most designers,
you know, get familiar.
Get some mastery
and skill at, you
know, using a certain
kind of mechanics.
At the same time, always
be looking at new ones
and trying to imagine,
you know, could I