WILL WRIGHT (VOICEOVER): A
lot of aspiring game designers
come to me with ideas
and their designs.
And I'm very familiar
with kind of looking
at them with fresh eyes,
and maybe giving them
a different perspective on
where they might go with it.
So we've invited an
aspiring game designer
to come share a game she's
currently working on.
I'll be looking at
her game, trying
to get a sense of where
she wants to go with it,
and giving her feedback on it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So "Morey" is a side
scrolling puzzle platformer.
OK.
And the premise
is that you play
as this woman named Nina who has
been stranded on this abandoned
space colony.
And she's trying to
find the equipment
she needs to get back home.
OK.
So the gameplay is definitely
like a traditional Metroidvania
game.
All right.
And the premise, a
lot of the upgrades
are you're changing
around gravity.
Changing gravity?
Yes.
So you can change it
up, down, left, right.
So you're jumping, and
the gravity allows you--
OK.
Let's take a look at it.
Sure.
We can take a look here.
So as you can see, we've
entered this giant room.
And you can change
gravity around.
WILL WRIGHT: Oh, you're
changing the angle of gravity.
GAME DESIGNER: Yes Yeah.
WILL WRIGHT: Oh.
I see.
OK.
GAME DESIGNER: So if you
fall too far, you can die.
So that's kind of
like the main thing.
Because the camera
doesn't rotate.
So you have to
turn in your head.
OK.
Right.
All right.
So at this point,
she's just kind of--
So you're actually
pressing something on here
to change gravity?
And you can pick one
of the four directions?
Yes.
Exactly.
All right.
I mean, right off the
bat, looking at this game,
it looks cooler to me now
than when you first pitched it
to me just a few seconds ago.
You started by saying it's a
side scrolling, da, da, da, da,
da.
Immediately in my
head I think Mario.
Whatever.
It brings a lot of baggage.
Sure.
I think-- and I
don't really care about
the character's name.
But if you say she's stranded
on this ship, exploring it,
but she gets altered
gravity, all of a sudden
that sounds kind of interesting,
intriguing, something
I've never heard.
I think maybe just start
with that and seeing it,
and now it looks just
so much cooler to me.
OK.
And I like the
style a lot too.
Thank you.
Yeah.
So the idea is you are
running around trying to find
like scraps that you need.
WILL WRIGHT: It's a bit dark.
And that's part of
the game mechanics
is that you really need a
light to kind of see things?
GAME DESIGNER: Yes.
WILL WRIGHT: OK.
So one of the mechanics,
or one of the things
you're upgrading is that
eventually you'll find a light.
You don't always start with it.
All right.
So there's like
a lot of danger
of just kind of wandering
around in the darkness.
In the dark.
OK.
Yeah.
Mhm.
Now, I'm not
hearing any sound.
Is that just part of the game
you haven't developed yet?
Right.
Exactly.
OK.
Because I think
when you're dealing
with limited perception,
like this flashlight,
sound is going to be
a huge part of that.
You hear something
scary or creaking.
You don't know if
it's good or bad.
It might be a door.
Or it might be a monster.
Who knows what?
But I think the
sound is going to be
just as important as the
visuals for a game like this.
Oh, yeah.
Definitely.
Especially when you're
running around in the dark.
Exactly.
But that's one of your
primary senses now.
So yeah.
For this puzzle specifically,
you're supposed to like go up,
and these boxes
will fall upward.
And then you have to like
race to finish the other side
before they fall back down.
OK.
So that would be
a huge part of where
sound is going to be like in.
And it feels like you
should do that fairly soon,
because you've obviously
pretty established here
on the visuals and some
of the game mechanics.
And if you're lacking
the sound, you're
lacking like 30% of the
experience right now.
So even if you just kind
of stub in some sound,
I would stub it in as
quickly as possible.
Sure.
OK.
Yeah.
So that's like-- it's
a pretty short demo.
OK.
So if you want to play it.
What was the
inspiration for this?
Yeah.
Let me move it around.
Oh, I just moved
gravity way over there.
Oh, I killed myself.
Oh, so that's how
you change gravity.
Right?
Yeah.
So WASD is to move.
Oh, gotcha.
OK.
GAME DESIGNER: So I love games
like "Limbo" and "Inside."
Oh, you might have
disappeared there.
WILL WRIGHT: Oh, I forgot
that I can go that way.
Oh, jeez.
WILL WRIGHT: This is actually
kind of fun, failing.
Good.
That's excellent.
No.
I think that's actually, for
me, one of the important parts
is not just that I'm
failing, but it's
presented in a humorous way.
I think humor is
one of the really
superpowers that game designers
have at their disposal.
They don't always use.
A lot of times people
will be looking
for extremely elaborate
technical solutions
to something, where, in fact,
just a little bit of humor
can solve it.
There was a door there.
Right?
Or maybe not.
So if I change gravity--
GAME DESIGNER: If you can
make it to the other side,
there's a door.
WILL WRIGHT: Oh, I see.
OK.
You will-- those
boxes are deadly.
Yeah.
I really do like the
look of the world.
I notice, there's
almost like a raster
scan quality to
the graphics here.
Is that on purpose?
GAME DESIGNER: Yes.
So that is a post
processing effect.
WILL WRIGHT: Yeah.
So the idea is-- and this will
kind of unfold in the story--
that you're being
watched by somebody.
OK.
So I wanted to
do an effect that
was sort of subtle, like maybe
you didn't notice it at first.
Right.
And the story would kind of
give you meaning to it later.
All right.
And so one of your
primary mechanics
here is changing gravity.
Right.
The orientation of gravity.
Which seems like a pretty
rich thing to explore.
How much have you tried
different level designs
against that?
I mean, do you have like a
level editor right now for this?
So yeah.
The system is set up so I can
pretty easily build things out.
Right.
And that's where
I've just gotten.
So I've just gotten to the point
where like the vertical slice
is complete.
Because it kind of feels
like you have a fairly open
ended design space
now of how to play
with that mechanic
of changing gravity.
Exactly.
And now, as a designer, what
you want to be doing is trying
a lot of different
level designs,
just experimenting to find out
which ones really work with
that and which ones don't.
And that's going to be a lot
of learning on your part.
Right.
You know.
And then kind of leaning
into the ones that
work well so that
you're really maximizing
that dynamic, the game mechanic.
Yeah.
You know, I think that and
the sound design feel like,
to me, the two areas you should
really be focusing on right now
as a designer.
Have you put this in
front of other people?
Yes.
All right.
And what is the most
typical confusing thing
at first for a new player?
So in my initial
play tests, I think
I had puzzles that were probably
more complicated than a game
like this needed to be.
OK.
So it was a lot
of struggle to get
through those mechanic wise.
Like I haven't found
people being frustrated
with the gravity and stuff.
And is this basically
kind of a puzzle game
where there's one solution?
You have to, you know, unlock
that door, unlock that door?
Kind of a gated experience?
Right.
And that's something I kind
of have to test out still,
because part of the mechanic
is you can jump around
to any part of the ship.
Right.
Once you find these checkpoints.
All right.
So theoretically you could
run through a puzzle backwards.
All right.
And so it still has to be
like solvable to get back.
Right.
That makes the design thing
a little bit more tricky.
Right.
Exactly.
Hm.
And just in your overall vision
of this as a product, how long
do you think an average
player's going to spend,
playing this all
the way through?
I'm aiming for
about three hours.
Three hours?
OK.
A pretty short experience.
Yeah.
Well, that's
fairly long, though.
I mean, for this
kind of puzzle game.
OK.
You know, do you have
a sense of how many
levels, or how big
of a space you're
going to have to
build out for it
to be a three hour experience?
So how I've been
thinking about it is I
broke it down by each of the
upgrades that you're getting.
All right.
And based on the
upgrade, my thought
is like, OK, well, how
cool is this upgrade?
And how much time do I really
want to make the player--
Right.
Like to earn it.
And tell me what happens
when you get these upgrades.
Do they actually change
your abilities in the game?
Like you were talking about
getting a better flashlight,
and stuff like that.
They will change
your abilities.
Like the gravity ability
itself is something
that you will unlock.
Oh, I see.
OK.
So as you move forward
through this ship,
you get to places
where you have to have
these upgrades to complete
the level, presumably.
Exactly.
OK.
Yeah.
And is it always going to
be basically kind of a linear,
I need this.
Then I open B. Then I need that.
And then I open C?
Or is there some
combinations that
can give you shortcuts or
different paths through there?
Because that would make it
a much more replayable game.
Right.
And that's kind of a big
question between how much time
do you want to spend
opening more player
opportunities in this, versus
having it be replayable,
you know.
I'm not sure if
this is something
you intend a player just to
sit down, play for three hours,
and then put away.
That was fun.
Or if it's something, you
know, where you want them--
you're going back
and trying it again.
You know, in some
of the Mario games
if you collect all
the coins on a level,
you know, you get
other things unlocked.
You know.
So that's something you
could think of down the road.
You don't have to
think of right now.
But in terms of the
overall player experience,
I think you should
be thinking about.
I have thought about,
at least in the sense
I do like the idea of
them like strategizing.
Cause when you look
at the map, you
can see where like the scrap
is that you need to collect.
Right.
So you can like know that, OK,
well, this part of the ship I'm
being blocked because I
can't do this ability.
Right.
And there's all
that scrap there.
And then maybe this part
of the ship is also locked,
and there's all this scrap.
So they have to judge like
what is the best thing for them
to do at that moment.
Yeah.
Hm.
Huh.
Interesting idea.
You know, I think that--
and just one last question.
Is the gravity thing like
your primary game dynamic?
Is that really what you
think distinguishes this game
versus other games like this?
Yeah.
OK.
And, you know, obviously
you have some back story.
But that's, you know, the
back story that everybody's
going to have obviously.
But I think that you
could do a whole lot
with sound design in this
that I'm not seeing right now.
I think that you
have the opportunity
to do a lot of really
interesting level design.
But you're going
to have to explore
that space as a designer.
You know, and whatever you're
using for a level editor,
you want to make as, you know,
kind of seamless and easy
to use as possible.
Even if it's just
a prototype, you
don't have the full
rendering of the character.
If you have like a
little toy prototype
of being able to do this in a
very easy to use level editor,
I think you could probably
explore that space much more
efficiently than getting
it into the full game.
You know, maybe, maybe not.
It's just a thought.
Sure.
Yeah.
And just the
very last thing is,
you know, I think
that I would refine
your pitch a little bit
more, and don't start
with, it's a side scroller.
OK.
You know, start with
something like, it's
a game about gravity.
Yeah.
You know.
Or something like that
that right off the bat
is like, oh, OK, gravity.
Sounds kind of cool
and interesting.
And, you know,
eventually-- in fact,
it's not necessarily
a side scroller,
cause you're going up
and down, and, you know,
all different directions.
But it's a cool idea.
I love the visuals
in it right now.
Thank you.
Sure.
Yeah.
Thanks.