[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: As we get further
down the development process,
the prototyping we're
doing is far more granular.
There are a lot of
things that you can do,
and a very small
subset of that is what
you should do for the player.
Scoping really is
going to come down
to what is the right sweet spot
for complexity and interest.
And so you try to
find that sweet spot
with scoping and prototyping
as one of your tools
for discovering that.
For "Spore," we did
50 or 60 prototypes
of different areas
of science that we
might have included in "Spore."
And again, most of
them were not included.
After playing with
the prototypes,
we decided either
it didn't really
fit in with the overall
concept, or that system
as a little toy, this wasn't
a very fun toy to play with.
But the ones that
were fun to play with,
we figured out, OK,
which one of these can
we now click together and
build into a larger experience.
And then eventually, they
turned into gameplay prototypes,
where actually there
is a game there.
One of the prototypes that
we developed for "Spore"
had a scripting language.
And in fact, I could take
the same little code base--
I, as the designer, could go in
and change the scripting of it
and change the rules within
the simple prototype.
And so I, in fact, was doing
a lot of the programming
on these prototypes to
explore different rule sets.
And in fact, I was able to
recreate very simple versions
of "Sim City" and
a few other games
within these "Spore" prototypes.
And some of them were using
very interesting systems
and typologies.
Some were network-based, others
were grid [INAUDIBLE] based.
And the fact that as a
designer I could very quickly
go on and script--
over one evening,
I could try five or six
different rule sets,
play with them for a while,
gravitate toward an area.
Once they got roughly
in some area I liked,
I could take it back to
the programmer and say,
now build me a better
version of this.
Or maybe it had some limitation,
I wanted to add a little--
couple more commands to
the scripting language.
But, in fact, I was doing
some of the programming
on the last half
of the prototype.
The programmer would give
me a little scripting engine
and code base that I could
script and change the rules on.
So again, it very rapidly
allowed me as a designer
to explore different rule sets.
A lot of times, I would
work with design teams.
And every week, there
would be a triage session,
and we would say, OK,
what are the biggest
risks of this project?
They could be
technological risks,
they could be design risks,
they could be production risks.
And then we step
back and say, OK,
how do we mitigate
that most effectively?
Sometimes a technological risk--
can we actually build this?
Let's build a prototype and see.
If it's a design risk, let's
see if we can find some--
build a prototype or
find some other game
that shows us this will be fun.
Can the production team
manage these assets
in time, whatever it is?
And hopefully, every
week we're trying
to basically attack the
top things on that list
to where they get
lower on the list.
Now something else becomes
the top design risk.
So I think that as you're
going through iteration,
it's continually that process
of attacking the highest risk
items.
One of the typical
aspects of risk
in this kind of development is
that the longer you delay it,
the more expensive it is.
If I could mitigate
that risk this month,
it's going to cost me $10.
If I wait three
months to mitigate it,
it's going to cost
me $100, because
of all of these other things
that have to change around it.
So again, this is
about efficiency.
How efficiently can I
prune that design tree?
And I want every
pruning of every branch
to be as expedient and
as efficient as possible.
And a lot of times, you
really want to put it off.
You really want to say, oh,
I know it's going to work.
But if you can
mitigate it early,
it gives you more
confidence later on
that you're on the right path.
There's so many times when
you're developing something
and it gets to some
point where it's really
starting to coalesce and
starting to feel pretty good,
but it feels that no
matter where you push it,
from that direction gets worse.
And this is you being
stuck in a local maxima.
And at that point, it can be
kind of apparent intellectually
to you that what you
really need to do is,
again, rip this thing
out, add that thing--
do some major change to it.
And you feel like
it's going to go here.
You're not sure, but
you're pretty sure.
But you know that you're
stuck here on this peak.
And that's a very hard thing
for you to kind of actually
take that hit and try
it, and maybe when
you do that, it's now worse.
But with a little bit of
iteration around there,
you find that, in fact,
you are on a taller slope.
But that's a very kind of
stressful kind of process
to go through, especially
with a team who's
invested a lot of time and
effort to get you here.
Now, really, you always do have
the opportunity to kind of fall
back if this is a total
failure over here--
come back to this thing and
try a different direction--
but that's incredibly expensive.
In my experience, all the very
best games, and all the games
I've worked on that ended up as
hits were things where we went
through that several
times, where we really
had to kind of take this
hit and say, OK, look,
we're going to have to do
something pretty radically
different here, and I think
it'll get us on a taller slope.
In most cases it did.
A few cases it didn't, and
we had to kind of go back
to do it twice.
But it's almost like you're kind
of dropping little paratroopers
in to do recon.
Each one of these
is very expensive,
but if they land on a slope,
they can now tell you, oh, it's
a good slope or a bad slope.
But I think that's
really the difference
between making a
really good kind
of mediocre game and a hit.
Tuning can be very,
very challenging,
and in fact, it's really
more a process of discovery.
And what I was doing for a lot
of things, like for "Sim City,"
I would actually
build test patterns.
I would say, I would expect
with this pattern of roads
or buildings, I would expect to
see this result on the traffic
layer in my head, then I
would actually draw these out.
This is kind of
what I would expect.
And then I would run the model.
It would be nothing like that,
and it wasn't apparent to me
how I would change it
to make it like that.
But instead, what
I found was, I had
to make it easy to just
explore that space--
change the rules very
rapidly, very quickly
and look at the result, to
zero in on the right rule set.
And again, because it's
an immersion system,
there's no really predictive
way to know which way to go.
It's more like you had
to learn to explore
this space very, very rapidly.
And in more of just kind of
typical parametric tuning,
Sid Meier had actually
a really good rule
of thumb, which is
that whenever you're
tuning your variable on a game,
don't move it by 10%, 20%.
Double it or half it initially.
And usually, it's
going to be way off.
So you double it or half
it, whichever direction
you need to go until
you're in the region,
then you can do the tuning.
But really, you're
probably way off to begin
with on almost everything.
And don't be afraid, even once
you have it running, to try it.
Just for the hell of it,
try doubling some value,
and see maybe--
the result might surprise you.
It might not be something
you were looking for,
but it might be
something very cool
that you discover that way.
Most of the
prototypes that we've
created for the
games I worked on
were failures, which is good,
because, again, they're helping
us prune design branches.
Do we want to go that way?
No.
If you actually look, once I've
taken this branching decision
tree all the way down, most
of the branches can be pruned.
They're failures.
We don't want to go that way.
We did some really
cool prototypes
for "Spore" of the
galactic dynamics,
the balance between
interstellar matter and stars--
which I can spend quite a
while talking about it--
but it's a very cool dynamic
of the way stars are formed.
The gas cools, it coalesces,
gathers into molecular clouds
and starts more star
formation, which propagates
a wave around the galaxy.
Very, very cool dynamics.
But as we started scoping
the rest of the game,
we realized this
really just had no part
in the context of
the rest of the game,
with the kind of point
of view the player had,
the tools, and all that.
So that was-- would've been
a very cool part of "Spore",
but, in fact, would've
been a very cool part
of a different
game, not "Spore."
And that's what we determined.
That's a cool game,
but it's not "Spore."
It's really hard
when you've invested
a lot of time and effort
into one of your just
passionate features
or components,
and either through
prototyping, testing,
whatever, it just doesn't have
a place in the original design.
Emotionally, I think you need to
kind of sit back as a designer
and say, OK, am I
designing something that--
for myself aesthetically,
or something
that I really want to impact
a large number of people?
Other times, it'll
really surprise you.
The very first
game I did involved
flying this little helicopter
around this world and bombing
things.
One of the things I
built as part of that
was this thing where I
could scroll on and create
the world to bomb.
And that thing, which was
originally going to be
a throwaway-- this is the editor
I built for bombing the world--
later, I was so into that--
I had so much fun playing with
that little world builder,
I took that and it
turned into "Sim City."
So what would have been a
throwaway prototype actually
evolved into my first big hit.
So sometimes if that thing
that you really personally care
about doesn't have a
place in your design,
that doesn't mean it doesn't
have a place somewhere
else in some other design.
It might be that's going to be
the thing that you eventually
turn into what it
should have been,
or maybe even you jump ship
and you go with that instead
and throw away
your original idea.
I mean, there's no hard
and fast rule for this.
And again, that's a lot
times very hard emotionally
when you've invested that
much in a certain direction
to throw it away.
But that's something
that's, I think--
every field, you
need to kind of learn
when to fail and
recognize that failure,
and sometimes celebrate it.
Don't say, oh my gosh,
poor me, I failed.
It's more like, OK, I failed,
let's learn from this.
Let's make it a
monument to learning.
In your design, at
some point you're
going to have to finish it--
finish building it.
You have to scope your design.
It's important to not
overreach, but at the same time,
you don't want to
make it too simple.
You want to achieve
something kind of cool.
But it's really kind of a sweet
spot of diminishing returns
in some sense, but
also it's surprising
how the simplest
little things in a game
sometimes can be the biggest
features that people just love,
that you spent no time at all.
And a lot of times, you'll
spend all this time and effort
on some elaborate thing
that you think will be cool,
and it turns out
to just fall flat.
If you can discover that
prototyping early on,
that's the best way
to deal with it.
But overall in terms
of scope, I think
you want to put the
player into an experience
where they have an
understanding of the boundaries
to some degree.
And again, it's almost like you
can put a kid into any game,
and within a few minutes,
they can kind of intuit how
open-ended that game is--
how much freedom and how much
agency they have in that game.
If you put a tiger in a
cage, the first thing he does
is walk around the perimeter
to define his space.
You know, how big is my world?
A lot of times, people
over-engineer things,
and programmers
tend to do that--
what if you decide
you want this later,
so I'm going to go
ahead and put it in now.
And they'll build something
twice as complex as what
you actually need for the game.
And this happens all
the time, especially
on the programming side.
The artists, I think, are a
little bit better about that.
Kind of understanding
hey, here's
the resolution we're
working at, here's
the way the animations behave.
And they're pretty good
at hitting their mark,
in terms of the sweet spot--
amount of time and effort
and budget spent on it.
I think the designer has to
have some understanding--
almost this psychology--
of the different components
of your game team--
this is the way
programmers think,
this is the way artists think,
this is the way the writers
and the sound people think--
and make sure that nobody--
no one side of that is
spending way too much relative
to the others.
So I think a lot of it
really is a more balancing
act across the different
components of your game design.
So players are going
to come into your game
with this expectation as well.
They're going to see
it's an open-ended game.
I expect to be able to
do this many things,
I expect the world
to be this big.
Especially if somebody
says, oh, I like your idea,
I like your idea.
And then you ask them
describe it back to you
and see which parts of your idea
that they're actually repeating
back to you, and are
they adding things to it
or removing stuff from it.
As we're going through this
process of game design,
one thing that I found
incredibly useful--
and a lot of design teams
do this-- is basically
a form of triage.
The designers-- once they have
some handle around what this
game might be--
will come up with
a set of features--
it'd be cool if it had
this, that, and the other.
Designers will actually
put value judgments--
that would be really
cool, that's kind
of cool, that's so-so.
And so designers might
go in and give the A, B,
and C in terms of
this is what we
would like to have in the game.
Then you bring it
to the engineers,
and the engineers will assign
a cost to each of these things.
That's a seven.
That's a one.
That's a 10, that's really hard.
And so then you have to kind
of look at the two together.
You have to say, the
designers think that's an A,
but the engineers
say it's 10, hard.
This one, the designers
say it's an A,
but the engineers say it's two.
So that's a much better
return investment.
So basically, you're going for
the low-hanging fruit here.
And you use this to
reorder the list,
and say, OK, we're going
to go for the things
the designers want the
most and the engineers
say will cost the least.
And you read over the list.
Now imagine if we just
had those features.
Is that something viable?
Probably not.
So we keep going through this
over and over again, and--
But still, this might
really influence the order
in which we build
this, because we
can have something playable
much more early if we pick
the things that are a
little bit easier, faster
for the programmers
to produce, even
as just milestone prototypes.
There have been examples--
I mean situations where it was
so important to the designers,
the cost was almost irrelevant.
It was really could
we do it or not
and can we afford that cost.
When we did "Spore," we
really wanted the players
design the creatures,
and we wanted
to have a wide variety
of possible creatures.
And we basically
couldn't figure out
how to animate these
things, because we
didn't know what they were yet.
Typically, animation
is very data driven--
the skeleton, that's moving,
has two feet, a head.
In this case, we
had no idea how many
legs does this creature
have, what's its shape,
where does the spine go.
So we kind of realized
early on that we
had to crack this nut
of procedural animation
to make it even viable.
And without that, we couldn't
go down that path at all.
And so we kind of
stopped everything--
got some very skilled
people, very smart people
working on this problem
for a few months.
And after a few months, they had
actually said, we can do this,
and they were actually
showing us examples--
prototypes they had built
where they were doing it.
And once we were convinced
that they could do it
and it wasn't an
expensive thing to do,
we decided to go down
that design path.
So that was one where it was
basically imperative to have
that feature, and we just had
to find out if we could do it.
Other times, there were
things in a game where--
like in "Sim City," we wanted
to have boats and water traffic
in "Sim City 2000."
And because the way we were
doing the type of graphics,
we would have had to
go back and really
change a lot of the
graphics system to do that.
And the value was very low for
that version of "Sim City."
We eventually added
later versions.
That was one where the
design value of the feature
was really pretty low and
the cost was really high.
And it depends also on
all the other features
you currently have.
You can't take any one
feature in isolation.
You have to say, OK, how does
that influence everything else?
Ideally, every time you
add something to a game,
it's like a force multiplier.
It's making the other
stuff even cooler,
making the world seem even
richer, or more emergent.
So it's important
that, as a designer,
you're always keeping in
mind the entire design,