[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: Inside of each
of us, there's a subconscious.
There's a whole region of who
you are that is, in some sense,
inaccessible to you, but
drives your behavior.
The game I'm working
on now is called Proxi.
And my core motivation
there is, can I
build a gameplay experience,
an entertainment experience,
where the computer is actively
trying to gain a deeper
understanding of the player?
Primarily through the
player's past experiences,
through their memories,
can I kind of interpret
the memories of your life, the
most important memories that
made you who you
are, and from that,
come to some understanding
of how you think?
What makes you behave
the way you behave.
Why you connect these
certain things in your mind
that most people don't connect.
What drives your interests.
You know, how much
can I get a computer
to learn that
about you, and then
try to build a representational
avatar of your id,
of your subconscious, that
you can now interact with.
And as it learns more
and more about you,
it kind of, in some
sense, comes to life
and can now interact
with other people's ids
kind of asynchronously.
It can go off in the world
and interact with your friends
or with, you know,
real or historic
or fictional
characters, you know?
How does your proxy get along
with Homer Simpson's proxy or,
you know, the pope's
proxy, or Mother Teresa.
I want to know, can we
build a map of that?
Can we start to understand it?
Can we build, you know,
a structural description
of how this thing works and
the connections it makes?
And what makes you different
from another person?
How is your id different
than that person's id?
How does it make you
behave in a situation
differently than they behave?
If we can start getting that
level of understanding--
And we're-- you know, I
think that analyzing memories
and life experience
is the path there.
And I'm not sure about this.
This is just kind of my--
my theory.
But that's kind of what we're
trying to do with Proxi.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Today, we're going to walk
through the process of creating
a game prototype.
Basically, we're
always doing this
to answer some specific
question about the design
that we're working on.
I'm here with my
programmer Zecmo,
and we're working on
this project here.
And in this project, the
user is creating memories
that come into this
world and basically turn
into this kind of landscape.
And this is what we have so far.
We're trying to figure out
how should these memories come
into the world.
Right now when I
create a memory,
it just kind of pops randomly
into the world, right?
Yeah.
WILL WRIGHT: Yeah,
it feels like it
should be more tangible,
though, like this world really
should have more rules and
more specific interactions.
So I want to prototype
something where
we try different ways to bring
new memories into the world
here.
I've been kind of thinking
about the idea of maybe
they come in on boats because
it's mostly ocean here.
Yeah.
And they can wander
around and try
to find a good place
to land or something.
Yeah.
So we could actually maybe
have, when I create a memory,
it actually is on a little
boat coming into the world.
And it sails around kind of
looking for a place to live,
you know?
I'm seeing here, you know,
seeing this little boat,
and I want to put it somewhere.
And as I'm looking
at this world,
I get the opportunity-- in fact,
I have to offload the memory.
And as I do, it will actually
kind of change the terrain.
It'll actually make continents
bigger, change the form.
And then the boat just
kind of disappears.
The boat's really just kind
of, like, the messenger.
But then it feels
more tangible, right?
Yeah.
So I think if we can kind
of prototype this, you know,
this little world with,
you know, landscapes,
but at the same time, have
new memories come in as boats
and let me kind of manipulate
the memories off the boats,
let's just see how that feels.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So show me how this works.
Yeah.
So the players just
created a new memory,
and they've come back.
And so we're going to simulate
this with a simple button
press.
WILL WRIGHT: All right.
ZECMO: And so here's a
new memory they just made.
WILL WRIGHT: OK.
And what do I do with it?
ZECMO: Yeah, so
it's running around.
Hopefully, you want to touch it.
WILL WRIGHT: Do I grab it?
OK.
Oh, I see.
So I pulled the memory off.
Oh, it made an island.
ZECMO: It made some
terrain, right?
WILL WRIGHT: OK.
So can I put more boats in here?
ZECMO: Yeah.
So they made a
couple new memories.
WILL WRIGHT: Oh, two boats.
ZECMO: Yeah.
And then they made two, and then
they came back to this area.
WILL WRIGHT: And
so basically, I'm
grabbing the memory
off the boat.
Oh, I see.
As I move it around, I get a
sense of the landscape, huh?
It tries some
good feedback so you
know where the connections are.
Oh, and I actually
get to see the terrain
before I release it.
Yeah.
OK, that's different.
That's kind of cool.
I like the tangibility of this.
These boats could have a
lot more elaborate rules
if we wanted to.
Pathfinding, sure.
There'll be the shipwrecks.
We could have collisions.
The boats, you know, maybe
have pathfinding and gravitate
towards certain
areas where it thinks
it wants the memory to be.
ZECMO: I could totally have
that in another iteration, sure.
WILL WRIGHT: Yeah.
So this is adding a certain
level of tangibility
to our world and, you
know, kind of going
with that landscape metaphor
a little bit more heavily.
I'm going to play with
this a bit longer,
but I think this is actually
a good direction for us
to go now.
I think maybe we're done
with this prototype.
I'd like to play with
it a little bit longer
and figure out, you
know, do we want
to elaborate on this prototype
or maybe go to another one.
But I think right now
this feels much-- oh, I
got a turtle this time.
ZECMO: Yeah, you
know, I had some time.
I finished a little
early, so I thought,
I'll throw in a little
fun thing like that.
WILL WRIGHT: Well
actually, I mean,
that's an interesting idea.
It could be that the memory
type is somehow related
to the vessel, you know?
Hadn't thought about that.
But just playing
with this prototype,
just because you threw
that in there, it
makes me think that, you
know, somehow the system could
actually look at the
memory type you're doing,
put it on a sailing
ship, on a motorboat,
on a turtle, whatever, so
it could have different kind
of classes of memory.
ZECMO: Yeah, I could
definitely add that.
If we want to iterate
on this one more time,
that would not be
hard to test out.
WILL WRIGHT: OK.
We might do one more
iteration on this prototype.
But I think this clearly
kind of answers--
this feels a lot better
than it was before.
ZECMO: Yeah, definitely.
And it's a fairly
simple code fix,
right, I mean, to
actually realize this?
Yeah.
I could do it.
In less than a day,
I could knock out
what you're talking about.
Sure.
WILL WRIGHT: So this case,
we've established basically
a resolution to this question
of how new memories come
into the world.
And just playing with
this for a few minutes,
I can clearly see that it
feels much better than what
we were doing before.
And not only that, but
based on just some things
that Zecmo threw in
there, it kind of
inspired me to think in a
different design direction
slightly.
So I'd say this, you know, was
a very worthwhile prototype
for the amount of time spent.
And again, it's not like
we spent a lot of time
on this prototype, but it
gives us much more clarity
on going down the design branch.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So I think that
prototypes like this
are really helping us explore
the space much faster and more
efficiently.
We're still basically in
an overhead world here.
And I think one of
the other things we're
going to want to prototype
is different renderings
of the world, whether
we go to 3D, isometric,
with a full camera
rotation and all that.
It's going to be a real
balance there, I think,
between legibility of
the world and, you know,
the player being able to do
interesting exciting things
in there without having to worry
about the camera angle, right?
Well if we're looking
at doing a 3D version,
I could take another day or two
to do a very simple version,
where it's just simple objects,
basic terrain generation
and just dragging things around,
and see how we like that.
If we could do it
without the user getting
too involved in the--
well, the camera
manipulation is the key.
So perhaps just lock it to,
like, 90 degrees, 45 degrees.
It sort of frees them
from that constraint,
but it focuses on just where
you're placing it in the world.
Right.
But also, this landscape, you
know, it's kind of a mnemonic.
So as I get a sense of that
landscape, all of a sudden,
you rotate it, it
looks different to me.
And, you know, the memory that
I put in the upper right corner
is now in the lower left corner.
And so that's why
I'm a little reticent
to go to full 3D, or at least
constrain the camera direction,
but we can still
kind of tilt it back.
You know, get some pitch on it.
OK.
So no rotation.
Yeah.
Just locked orientation.
I got you.
And just have that sort
of gradual pitch, that--
Yeah.
And probably-- we're definitely
gonna want some amount of zoom
in, so the zoom might
be relative to the pitch
of the camera.
So maybe one of the things
we might want to prototype
is a world like this
where I can now, you know,
zoom in, have the camera
pitch change with the zoom,
pull back out, get
the overhead map.
Then I think we've gone a long
way toward establishing kind
of the user interaction
and the look
and feel that we now have to
kind of produce, you know,
at a production level.
Yeah.
I think the simple
restrictions would help maybe
produce it faster.
So that's the idea.
Yeah.
And, you know,
again, we don't want
to spend more than a few
days, a week at the most, on,
you know, prototyping that.
Yeah.
And if we had that
plus this prototype,
now we're well on
our way to kind
of knowing what's happening
in that world, what
the affordances are, how
the user's, you know,
picking the camera angle
and all that stuff.
And yeah, I think it won't
take too many more prototypes
like this to get pretty
far down the design tree,
and we can actually start
committing real resources
to it.