[MUSIC PLAYING]
Well, as you work on a
project, in early stages,
you're going to want to
just get a sense of what
does this thing feel like
for me to interact with,
or the other people
on my team, how
do we feel about
interacting with this very
simple little system?
Sometimes it might not even
be a prototype that we made,
or it might be a game
we pulled off the shelf.
What do we like about
that game or this game?
Those are the cheapest
prototypes, really,
if you can find some other game
that has some aspect of what
you want to include.
Then, as you start
building something,
you start building not just the
system, but also the interface,
the player controls.
Typically you'll want to bring
in a few people who play games,
but they've never
seen this, just
to figure out the interface.
Can they understand the
control scheme you've got?
Does that make sense to them?
Can they understand reading
the topography, the landscape?
Do they have some sense of
what they're supposed to do?
what occurs to them as you drop
them into this environment?
So it actually can become
a fairly granular process.
It's not like we build
the game, build the game,
now we start playtesting.
It's really like we're
building prototypes
from the very beginning that
we are testing ourselves,
and then over time,
starting to test little game
parts with a few
people, here and there.
And eventually, we're bringing
in larger groups and maybe even
at some point
hundreds of thousands,
capturing metrics and building
these fairly complex diagrams
of them moving through
the game space.
This is the first
time you really
have a little bit of a peek
into the player's mind about how
they're going to interact with
this thing that you've built.
As a designer, you kind
of had this idea all along
that I'm going to
give them this.
They're going to be
able to do A, B, and C.
They're going to try
to get to D, whatever.
This is what you're imagining.
And as I am a
designer, I'm trying
to imagine, what would I enjoy?
How would I think about this?
But I put it in front
of somebody else,
and right off the bat,
you start learning things.
That maybe that wasn't
as easy as you thought.
Or they're not
even trying to get
to D. They're trying to get to
F, over there, for some reason.
And you go back and
revisit your assumptions
or maybe ask them why.
What did they see that caused
them to think that way.
Or maybe there
was just something
they thought of
that you didn't that
would be really cool to try.
And then again, you're learning.
So I think that this is
where for the first time,
the designers are taking this
concept out of their head
and trying to put it
into other people's heads
and seeing how it fits.
It's frequently very
hard to kind of imagine
the way other people are
going to see or understand
what you've made in a game.
And there's really
no replacement
for actually testing it.
We did a lot of what we called
Kleenex testing, where we'd
bring people in who had
never seen the game before,
put them in front of it with
absolutely no instructions,
and just watch what
they started doing.
And see where they fail.
See what's obvious.
A lot of times, it's
so obvious to you
that they should
press the red button,
but it will not even occur to
them to press the red button.
And you sit there and
watch 10 people not
press the red button, and
you start realizing, okay,
that's not the typical
person's understanding
of the way this thing works.
One thing that
was very important
is we put two people
in front one computer.
If you put one person
in front of a computer,
they'll sit there,
but they don't talk.
They get very quiet.
You don't know what
they're thinking.
If you take two people-- and
they have to know each other.
They might be friends
or spouses or whatever.
They'll be talking non-stop.
Press the red button!
No, not the red one.
That makes that happen.
Oh, no it doesn't.
And they'll be explaining to
each other what they think.
And so those two
people, you can just
sit back and listen to
what they're saying,
and you understand
how they understand
the game in front of them.
After we use these people and
learn these things, we go back,
we make the red button
more prominent or whatever.
Then we never use them again.
We bring in a
whole different set
of people, who, again, have
never seen the game before.
So they're kind of unpolluted.
That's why we call
it Kleenex testing.
We use the tester once
and then throw them away.
But there's really no
replacement for that.
And it's amazing as a designer
how frustrating, in some ways,
it is to sit back and
watch these people not
do the obvious thing you were
sure they were going to do.
Instead, they're all
doing this other thing.
And you have to adapt to that
and start realizing, okay.
Well, the model that they're
coming to this game with
is different than
what I was thinking.
So that's probably the
most important thing.
Playtests, usually
it's a large room.
The designers are sitting
back a few feet away.
And there'll be five or six
different workstations set up.
In front of each workstation,
we'll have two people.
Again, people that know
each other, friends,
spouses, whatever.
We put each group down.
We give them some
very, very rough sense.
Here's a game about
controlling little people,
or here's a game
about building cities.
And then we just turn it on.
And from that point
on, we don't say a word
unless they have some
technical problem.
They'll sit there as a pair
and try to basically figure out
how the game works.
What do we do here?
What does that do?
Maybe that will
make this happen.
And the designers will
kind of rotate and just
be listening over the
shoulder of each group.
The designers also,
at that point,
are not interacting
with each other.
Typically, this will be a
design team of three or four
designers, and we're all
coming to our own conclusions
independently,
observing this group.
After it's all
over, the designers
will sit down and
collate their notes.
And then we will come
together as design group
and say, what did you see?
What were our biggest issues?
And usually it's pretty
clear that there'll
be one or two or three
things that we all agree on.
We all agree that
that was not obvious.
This was too hard.
They didn't enjoy this part.
And those are the
things we focus
on for the next iteration, which
might be a few weeks from then.
And these become
design risks for us.
We're always mitigating
and triaging design risks.
These are now the
top three design
risks we've discovered
from our playtesting.
We will make action items.
How can we basically
mitigate those risks
effectively very rapidly?
Do that, and the next
time we bring in a group,
we see if we were right.
And if we were
right, the next group
is going to have
three different risks.
And we're repeating
that over and over,
always basically looking
at the top risks,
the top thing people
were not getting,
not enjoying, getting confused
about, whatever it might be,
and basically attacking it.
To test the engagement,
you have to have so much
of this, really, kind of
coming together as a whole.
And it's so far down the path
that the early testing has
really nothing to do with that.
The early testing
is do they know
how to operate this
windshield wiper
or that headlight control.
That's not going to tell
you how well the car drives.
As a designer,
though, this is where
I think your vision has
to carry you through.
Not just your vision,
but your ability
to communicate that vision
to the other stakeholders
in the project.
That I know that if we can
get the windshield wipers
working and the steering
wheel and the brakes all
that, that way over
here somewhere,
this is going to be a
really cool car to drive.
And that really is going
to be more, right now,
instinct and salesmanship
on your part as a designer.
As you get later on
in the process now,
and you have your
working windshield wiper
control, and your
steering wheel,
and your brakes and
all that, now you
need to put those things
together and actually say,
okay.
Now let's start getting some
sense that this actually
will be engaging.
And as soon as
possible, try to get
some set of these things working
together as a whole, such
that you can sit back and see
another person actually enjoy
it and start building
the model and start
trying to head for the goals and
get that flow state that you're
really trying to
achieve as a designer.
When you put a tester
in front of your game,
they are not going to sit
there and tell you exactly
what you're hoping to hear.
You know, they're
having an experience,
and you can, again, by putting
them with somebody else,
have them verbalize
their experience.
But as a designer, you have
to kind of decipher that.
You have to understand
when they say,
I think it's really
frustrating doing this,
but what they might
really mean is
they wish they had another
option to do that instead.
So a lot of times, what
they will express directly--
a lot of times,
they'll come back
and say, oh, I want
X, Y, and Z. They'll
start describing solutions to
you rather than the problem.
I would love this game if I
only had a jet pack and a laser
beam.
But in fact, what
they really mean
is that they don't like getting
stuck on the ground level
when they want to
climb that mountain.
So you have to distinguish
them offering you
solutions from what do the
solutions-- what problem does
that actually point back to?
And that's the problem you
need to solve as a designer.
Because probably
their solutions suck,
but the problem they're
referencing doesn't.
That problem is real.
Well, when you're
looking to playtest,
the signal to noise
issue really is
going to be a matter
in substantive data.
If you do enough testing
with enough people,
you'll start to be
able to distinguish
the signal from the noise just
because that's consistent.
The noise is all over
the place, random.
But when the same
five people are all
saying they didn't know
to press the red button,
but then they give you
totally different feedback
on everything else, you
know that the red button
is definitely a signal.
And I think that signal comes
in two dimensions, which
is why I was kind of saying that
you want to listen to what all
these groups have in common.
What problems and frustrations
are they all having in common.
But also, as designers, when
you go back and compare notes,
what problem do
all the designers
agree that it's pointing to.
Because this
designer might think,
oh, that problem is
their character creator.
No, this problem is
their navigation system.
But if all the
designers could agree
that those results point
to the same problem,
now that's a signal, for sure.
Too often, you're expecting your
players to be game designers.
When a player is
describing to you
that in their head, if
you had a garbage system,
it would be so much
cooler, they're
imagining it a
certain way that's
probably not the way
it works or the way
you're thinking about it.
But if you could
understand why they're
saying that, what limitation
or failure or flat spot
are they hitting that makes them
think that that addition would
make it better,
then that's good.
And a lot of times,
sometimes they're
telling you to add
stuff, and in fact, it's
about removing stuff.
A lot of times, you
got too much stuff.
Too much noise from the
player's point of view.
One of my favorite quotes
is about Japanese gardening.
It's that your garden is not
complete until there is nothing
else that you can remove.
Engagement is one
of those things
that has a very wide range.
When we initially
have prototypes,
and we bring players
in to try it out,
it's more a matter of
getting them to stay there
in front of the computer.
Keep playing, keep
playing, keep playing it.
Towards the end, if you're
really starting to nail it,
it's a matter of you trying
to pull them away from it.
Okay, time to stop.
Time to stop.
I think, right
off the bat, there
are a couple of very
simple little tricks.
A lot of times, if I'm
showing somebody a game,
and I'm actually playing it
and explaining how it works,
if they all of a sudden
want to grab their mouse
and say, let me try, let me try,
or if I see a game somebody is
showing me, and all of a
sudden, I feel the urge to hey,
let me see if I can do it,
that's a great measure,
right there.
Right off the bat, just by
watching somebody play it,
I've understood enough
to think that I want
to go in and try something.
I have some of the model.
In fact, this starts even before
you see somebody playing it.
It starts maybe when you see
the box or see an ad for it.
At that point, you're starting
to say, hey, that sounds fun.
That sounds kind of cool.
I want to try it.
So that's a certain level
of engagement, right there.
And then later down the road, if
you have something really good,
you'll start having
people write you back
that I was up all night
playing this thing,
and I couldn't stop.
And I didn't realize it was
5:00 in the morning, whatever.
That means you really
kind of nailed it.
But I think along
the way, again,
there are going to be certain
players that maybe just love
what you've made,
a few that hate it.
Or maybe it's the other way
around, most people hate it,
but a few love it.
And you need to be willing
to kind of experiment
by changing a few
rules, a few parameters,
and making the game a
little more dynamic in terms
of the player choosing to
try and balance that out.
And there's really no substitute
for capturing metrics.
If you can capture metrics
on a large number of players,
you can really balance
this out nicely
over a wide range of people.
It used to be much
more anecdotal.
We would sit and
watch 10 people do it
and try to go with
our gut instinct.
And engagement and
difficulty, some of it
could be player moderated.
The player chooses to
go down this path, which
is more difficult,
or they choose
to just sit back
here and enjoy this.
If they're enjoying it,
again, that's engagement.
It didn't have to be
challenging to be engaging.
Some people like to do
creative, weird experiments,
and they find that
very engaging.
Other players are going to
want a continual challenge all
the time as fast as possible.
Letting that be player moderated
is probably the best choice.
There are things
where we actually
see the players trying
to make an achievement
and getting frustrated.
They're failing too often.
And that's where I think the
metrics come in a little more
heavily.
You can actually kind of
measure how many people
are failing it on
the first time,
the second time, the third time.
And I think that's
something where
it's a little more
metric driven,
but also it's
player categorized.
Certain players are going to go
down that path, other ones are
going to be different.
So the metrics will
be very different
for those types of players.
And that's where as a designer,
you have to sit back and say,
okay.
Here we're dealing with
the trophy seekers,
here we're dealing
with the socializers.
Whatever it is,
however you choose
to categorize your
different players,
you need to understand
that they're going
to have different metrics.
Sid Meier had a great quote.
It's that some games you
design for the players,
and some games you
design for yourself.
And I experienced that, I think,
with a game I did way back,
called "Sim Earth."
I got fascinated with
building this elaborate model
of the planet Earth, and
the climate, and the oceans,
and the lifeforms, and
everything, the geology.
And it was a pretty cool
little model for its time,
running on a PC.
And it had all these
little controls
where you could adjust
things about the planet.
But it was very
complex as a model.
And I really enjoyed
playing with that model.
But later I realized,
as we were putting
this in front of
players, it was kind of
like putting them in the cockpit
of a 747 that's in a tailspin,
heading to the ground, and
all the gauges are spinning.
No matter what they do,
it's going to crash.
And they try everything they can
think of, and it still crashes.
You know.
That's kind of what it
felt like to the players.
I got so caught up in the
idea of building this little
know planetary model on
a computer for myself.
And I think that kind of
reinforces the idea of testing.
But also, as a
game designer, you
have to be able to kind of
go back to the drawing board
when you see people interpret
what you've done in a totally
different direction.
"The Sims" is a better
example of that, where I was
so fixated on the architecture.
And then we started putting
in front of a few people
and saw how
fascinated they were.
And it makes sense that they
were fascinated, basically,
messing with these little Sims.
The house was a
backdrop for it, and it
was one of the
kind of challenges
and became an integral
part of the gameplay.
But the real focus of the game
that the average player came
to it with was on
messing with the people.
And so as a game designer, I
had to kind of sit back and say,
okay, look.
I think that really
is the way I need
to go with this, which I did.
So I think you need to be able
to revisit your assumptions
at the very beginning when
you see the way people are
interpreting what you've done.
I think in terms
of the people we
would tap to bring
in, initially, it's
going to be a pretty
wide range of people,
but still we have some
sense of this is a game
that older people
enjoy, younger.
Once we get a sense of,
like, where it's really
hitting the mark, we
can get a little bit
more specific about the kind
of people we want to bring in.
We want to bring in
more women or more
younger players,
whatever that is.
And get more details in terms
of also maybe these are people
that are really creative.
They're not so much
achievers, but they
want to do creative stuff in
there, more storytelling, more
customization, more
personalization.
This other group might
be more into advancement
and showing off in
the social groupings.
Whatever it is.
But that's something
that you kind of, again,
discover over time.
And then as a designer,
you can say, okay.
We're going to go
down that path,
or we're really going to
focus on these people,
or maybe we want
to keep it broad.
We actually want
to kind of bring
in those other people
that weren't as interested
and try to keep these
at the same time.
That's when you're
making a design decision
as to which demographic group
you're going to be going after.
But even then, the demographics
are frequently very misleading.
But the Sims, again, we
initially sold this to gamers.
And gamers thought, oh,
it's a weird new thing.
I'll try it out.
They played it for a few weeks.
And what happened is these
were mostly teenage boys,
and what happened
is their sisters
were watching them play.
Their sisters, for
the very first time,
said, hey, I want to try it.
They bring it to their
hand-me-down computer.
And that turned out
to be our big hit,
initially, for "The Sims,"
was 12-year-old girls.
So you can't always predict.
And even if you can
predict, you might not
hit that target demographic
right off the bat.
There might be actually
kind of a viral component
to how it spreads to them.
Because these 12-year-old
girls were not
going into computer stores
and buying computer games.
They just happened to see it
on their brother's computer.
In my experience,
focus group testing
has been pretty
close to useless.
You know, so many times--
we had a focus group
many, many years ago.
And we had like
four game designs
that we were basically
just describing
to this audience of gamers.
And one of those
four was "The Sims."
We described each of
these game concepts, what
it would be like to play,
would they be interested, would
they want to play it.
The other three, they all liked.
That was great.
"The Sims" was the one
idea they all hated.
No, I would never play that.
Never touch it.
I don't even remember
the other three
games, what they ended
up being, but I know
they weren't a big hit at all.
So in that sense, you're kind
of expecting your players
to be designers.
Because when we were
describing "The Sims" to them,
I know they could not
unpack it in their head
and be playing in
their imagination
the game that I was envisioning.
And there was no easy way for
us to communicate it to them.
So it doesn't surprise
me they hated it,
because the game
that they designed
based on the description
was horrible.
And I think that's one of the
real limits of focus group
testing.
Play testing, on the
other hand, as soon
as we brought a few people
in, the same type of people,
same demographic, we put
them in front of the system,
where they can manipulate people
and live their little lives,
they loved it.
They really had fun
getting in and doing it.
So in that case,
they weren't doing
the heavy lifting of imagining
how this would actually work.
You know, we had
already done that.
Now they were actually
in the experience.
People have
different definitions
of what a beta test is.
You know, in my mind,
I tend to think,
you know, a beta
test is basically
roughly your complete game,
with all the components, all
the functionality, in it, that
you're handing over to people,
usually a fairly
large group of people,
and you're basically
confirming that it
has the right kind of
motivational hooks,
the right player
agency involvement
that you thought it would.
Also a much more mundane aspect
is you're discovering bugs.
Where is it crashing?
What are people doing
with it to cause it
to do things you didn't intend.
And it might be a hard
crash, or might be they
just kind of got stuck
in this game space
that you didn't ever expect
that they would get into.
And a lot of times,
you'll discover things
in beta testing that are
serendipitous upside.
You know, that, wow, I never
thought players would do that,
and it actually works,
and it's kind of cool.
So there might be
things that you
decide to lean into as a
result of beta testing,
but that's not the
primary purpose.
I think the primary
purpose is making sure
that in general, this thing is
behaving the way you thought
it would, at scale.
And that the players
might be fanning out
in different
directions in there.
At this point, you finally
have an opportunity
to get a sense of
how many players are
going this way versus that way.
Maybe in playtesting, it might
have been five versus four,
and in beta testing, it turns
out to be 5,000 versus 1,000.
Maybe the ratios are way
off from what you thought.
But for the first
time, you really
get at-scale testing,
both for bugs, exploits,