[GEAR TURNING]
[ALARM GOING OFF]
[NATURE EFFECTS]
MICHAEL CORMIER: Sound design
is a huge potential force
multiplier.
Sound design can take a really
good game and make it great.
[RELOADING]
If you ask a player
why the game is great,
they probably
won't even tell you
it's because of
the sound design.
[SCREAMS]
If it is really that
good, it'll probably
be unconscious to the player.
[BLADE SPINNING]
But yet, it's influencing
their emotional state.
They're actually experiencing
the graphics as being better
or the gameplay as being better.
And everything
seems better to them
because the sound design
is kind of putting them
in the right state of mind.
So the sound design,
I think, is kind
of queuing up the
player's imagination
in the right state
for everything else
to do its thing.
[AMBIENT SOUNDS]
The sound design is
usually the thing
that gets the short shrift
in a lot of game designs.
It's kind of like, we know we
have to do the programming,
we know we have to do the
art, the UI, and all that.
Oh, by the way, we need
to do sound at some point.
But more and more, I
think sound is becoming
one of the really primary,
upfront components
of a lot of games.
More and more games are
actually based upon music,
or that's the overt
theme of the game.
I think sound design--
if I'm including music as well--
is at least as tricky as the
art side of things nowadays
and at least as rich.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I think the primary
indicator for me
as to the quality
of sound design
is whether I turn
the sound off or not.
[CHUCKLES]
There are a lot of games
where it's just like, that
is annoying as hell.
And I turn it off.
Maybe the game is fun
and I enjoy the game.
But really great sound design
is something that I notice.
I'd say that good sound
design is something
that, OK, it's tolerable.
It's nice.
It informs me.
It serves its purpose.
Every now and then, I play a
game where the sound design
just blows me away.
There was an old, old game--
I think it was "Clive
Barker's Undying."
It was a horror game.
And you're going
through this old house.
And it's dark.
And it was a first-person
kind of scary game.
And most of the
sound design in there
was the wind howling; some
of the windows were open;
you were seeing
drapes move; creaking.
And it was done so
well, the blending
between the creaking
of your footsteps
and the creaking of the wind.
And every now and then,
a monster would pop out.
[GUNSHOTS]
But it would be a little bit
slightly different creek.
And you were starting to
imagine all these things
in the soundscape that you
were about to encounter.
And so they were really
tweaking your imagination
with the sound design
in a beautiful way.
And every now and
then, I see a game
that does something like that.
That, really, the
sound is really
adding a whole level
of dynamics to what
I'm building in my imagination.
And I think that's an indicator
of great sound design.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Within sound design, there
are a lot of components to it.
You'll have sound effects
within your world.
Typically, you'll have music.
You'll have a lot of
times user interface sound
effects, which are very
different from the in-world
sound effects.
Voices, voice acting.
So across all these
things, you're
going to have to have somebody
that kind of understands
all these components at some
level and brings them together.
Now, from the design
point of view,
the designer can kind of
say, I want these things
to sound realistic
or deep, and I
want the interface to be quiet,
or I want the voice acting
to be like this.
That's something
where you really
need almost a jack of
all trades for your main
or only sound person--
somebody who's
pretty comfortable
at doing a lot of
different things.
Again, I was lucky to work with
a guy named Kent Jolly, who
was my sound director.
And he would basically
oversee the music
and the sound effects.
A lot of games,
the sound is going
to be very localized,
very in the world.
These are the objects in
the world making noise.
And as you move
the camera around,
they need to kind of
fade up and fade down.
A lot of it is very kind
of tactical like that.
Other times, it's more global.
It's like, I want to
have this zen experience.
And I want to hear this
soothing music as I play this.
And all the sound effects are
going to blend into the music.
So there's a pretty wide
variety of approaches
depending on what kind
of game you're doing
that you would take to sound.
But I think that your
sound director probably
has the opportunity
to present you
with even more options
than your art director,
because it's pretty easy
and quick to prototype
some of these things
on the sound side.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I think for the sound to really
immerse the player effectively
in a game, it has to live
alongside the art and even
the player interactions.
But it has to feel like
it's part of the same world.
If the sound feels
cohesive with what
you're seeing on the screen,
then it comes together.
And that's when, all
of a sudden, this
becomes a real tangible world
and I can kind of mentally
displace myself into it.
So I think that you can't
just deal with the sound
apart from the art.
The two basically have to live
in the same kind of universe
together.
What's this world is made of?
What's the scale of this world?
Is it whimsical?
Is it serious?
Is it spooky?
Is it fantastical?
So I think that there's
the style of the sound.
But there's also,
how overt is it?
Is this a very foreground sound?
Is it a background ambience?
Is it something that
sounds very consistent
through the whole world or is
it something that indicates
something special here?
That kind of thing, again, it's
very brittle in a way in that,
it's a little bit too
much, and it totally
blows it; a little bit too
little, and you don't hear it.
And there's a very,
very narrow sweet spot
I think you have to achieve on
the sound design, especially
when you're putting
sounds against each other.
On the music side, that
is kind of a much more
subjective decision I think
on the designer's part.
But one of the things we
watned to do in "Spore," again,
was to make each one these
worlds seem unique and special.
And we couldn't
really have music
coming from these
little cities that
were supposed to be on different
planets playing the same tune.
So we took a stab at it.
And I'd say
reasonably successful,
we had a generative
music system.
We actually had Brian Eno
come in and help us design
the musical system in "Spore."
And he'd been actually
doing generative music
for many years.
And he worked with my
sound director Kent Jolly.
Kent was actually
coding up these systems
that Brian had been
doing manually.
And so in fact, in
"Spore," you can actually
open the little
city hall building
and adjust the parameters
of the procedural music.
But every city in fact has
a different little melody
played because it's
all computer generated.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
In "Spore," in fact, depending
on where the camera is--
how high it is
above the ground--
you get kind of different
layers of effects
that would come in and out.
Way up high, you'd get more
environmental wind effects.
Like you're up in the clouds.
As you came in, you'd
start hearing things--
creatures, people, whatever--
moving on the ground, vehicles.
If you came all the way
down to ground level,
there was another
kind of ambience
of almost like gravel blowing
across the train or wind going
through leaves,
that kind of thing.
But it's actually a
fairly technical system.
And I think more and more
of the sound design in games
is getting to that
level of sophistication.
And so I would kind
of describe to Kent,
well, I think that
should sound more
like we're going into space.
What would it
sound like if I was
going from the
atmosphere with a camera
all the way out in space?
What would the sound
do at that point?
And we basically had to cut
out all the environmental sound
effects.
And we actually went
to music at that point.
And there was a whole different
soundtrack for the music
depending on what scale
you were at in space.
So we kind of figured
out, where does
the music inhabit different
parts of the game,
and what is the
transition-- really,
the transition between
those is the trickier part.
Because especially if the
player is moving or moving
the camera between these, you
want a very smooth, seamless
sound design.
And that's why sound feels
kind of more brittle in a way.
It's pretty obvious that
when this object goes
behind that object,
it is occluded.
The visuals are pretty
obvious in terms
of where they should appear
and when they should appear.
The sound is a lot less obvious.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
It seems like every
game, you kind of
expect it to have some
background song playing.
I think that when we
watch film and somebody
scores a film there,
there typically
is, even at a very,
very low ambient
level, a little bit of a
film score kind of running
through the whole thing.
So I think part of this
is maybe the expectation
we bring in from film.
I think that there's maybe this
thought that more is always
better, so the more
music we have playing
and the longer it plays,
the better the game is--
which isn't necessarily true.
I think it's, in
fact, a delicate thing
in terms of how you approach
it when you bring it
in to a product.
When I was working on "The
Sims," one of the things
I really wanted to
try-- and I did try.
And it was a failed try,
but it was fun to try.
And I wanted to
put laugh track in.
And in fact, I put a
laugh track in "The Sims"
during certain things.
And I actually started to study.
I spent some time--
a few weeks--
researching laugh
tracks, which turns out
to be this amazingly
secretive thing.
There are just a few
people that really
do most of the laugh tracks.
And they're very secretive
about how they do it.
And the machines they
use are custom-built.
It just surprised me that
it was such a black box.
But it just didn't work.
And it was because
it was so abrupt.
Because people were
building in their head
these whole little
stories of these people
doing these things.
And in the players'
stories, it would
be like, oh, her grandmother
just died because
of this, that, and the other--
all of a sudden, the
laugh track kicks in.
And so it would actually
interrupt and conflict
with their stories.
And so one of the reasons
why we took it out forever
was the fact that we
realized that it was stepping
on the players'
stories that seemed
like the most emotionally
engaging part of the product.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
One of the general things I've
found as a designer that's
actually very useful is
that, a lot of times,
we'll hit a problem that
seems almost intractable.
How do we solve this?
This really messy problem.
And so many times, we
just fall back on humor.
And humor is so
underused in some ways.
Some games are trying to
be comedies and all that.
But even just a little bit of
humor every now and then when
you're dealing with a hard
design problem sometimes
can make it work OK.
In "The Sims," they
had to pull things out
of drawers or whatever, which
is really hard to deal with.
So we had them always
reach behind their back
and pull it out of their
butt, whatever it was
that they needed in their hand.
And it became this humorous
little kind of cliche
about the Sims.
And the voice kind of
supported that a little bit--
the way they talked.
They sounded like little,
tiny strange people
speaking some weird
language that you've never
heard of before.
The unconscious metaphor we
were [INAUDIBLE] with-- this
is a dollhouse.
Then these wanted to be
like little, tiny people.
And they wanted to have
high-pitched little voices
and sound like little,
tiny people walking around
inside a little dollhouse.
Again, this is kind of a little
bit more subconscious, subtle.
But I think it kind
of supported the idea
that you're dealing
with a little toy
world in front of you
and little toy people
that you're manipulating.
[CHARACTERS SPEAKING GIBBERISH]
A friend of mine
designed this game
that we published called
"Sim Life" many years ago.
And it was an evolution game--
a fairly serious evolution game.
We're actually
tracking the genetics
of these little creatures.
And they could mutate
and evolve over time.
One thing we just threw
in at the last second
before we shipped the
game is that, whenever
two creatures came
and mated, at first,
they would just kind of do
this little mating animation
that was very PG.
He threw in the sound effect
that he made with his wife
I think.
But basically, it was
a little sound effect
that went like, ooh, la, la.
Just this silly little thing.
Ooh, la, la.
MICHAEL CORMIER:
And everybody who
played that game,
that was the one
thing they remember about it.
And every time they heard
that, they would just
laugh hysterically.
And for a lot of
players, that was
like 10% of the entertainment
value of that game
was that one little, tiny
sound effect that took him
five minutes to throw in there.
So it is really funny.
The whole game was so serious
that that one little bit
of humor really stood out to
people and surprised them.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
On a game like "The
Sims," we obviously wanted
to kind of hear the sims.
Initially, we
thought, do we want
to record people
saying real things?
No, that's going to
get way too repetitive.
It's going to
break the illusion.
Because really,
the idea was that,
if you were watching
people from a balcony
and you couldn't hear
what they were saying,
you could still kind of get a
sense of their emotional state
by the way they animate, they
gesture, their body language,
and the tone of
their voice-- not
what they were actually
saying, but the tone.
Are they excited
or are they sad?
Are they quiet, loud?
So we basically wanted
to go in and record
something that sounded real,
but was not understandable.
I initially brought in a few
voice actors using languages
that we just were not
very familiar with.
We first tried Estonian, because
Estonian sounds very strange.
It doesn't sound Slavic.
It doesn't sound European.
But we couldn't find enough
Estonian voice actors.
Then we found actually
a few voice actors
that actually spoke Navajo.
But that sounded actually a
little to American Indian.
Eventually, we found
these two voice actors
that were also improv comedians
that knew each other--
a man and a woman.
And we tried to describe
to them what we wanted.
And they just started kind
of speaking in this gibberish
to each other.
And we listened to
them do it for a while.
And we started actually
giving them a little bit
of sound direction.
I was on the soundstage with the
other designer, Claire Curtin.
And we were kind of saying,
OK, can you do a bit faster,
can you make it a little
bit more cartoonish.
And we were kind of giving
him a little bit of direction.
But the whole time, they were
kind of developing this whole--
[SPEAKING GIBBERISH]
--like, gibberish
language to the point
where they were kind of
speaking the same language.
The kind of things he was
saying sounded like the things
she was saying.
They were kind of
basically meeting.
They were starting
like random gibberish,
but they kind of
met in this area
where they sounded like they
were speaking the same thing
with a male and female voice.
[CHARACTERS SPEAKING GIBBERISH]
It was just through the
talent of those two actors
that we kind of zeroed in
on what we ended up with.
But that was very much kind of
a discovery in an exploration
that we were doing
on the soundstage.
[CHARACTERS SPEAKING GIBBERISH]