[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: Whenever I get
to the point where I decide,
OK, I'm building
a game about this,
I start imagining
how do I present
this idea to other people.
What am I kind of imagining
the process to feel like,
the activities, the
agency I have in this?
I'm starting to actually
play that game in my own head
at a more and more
detailed level,
while at the same time trying
to imagine, OK, how do I offload
or download that play experience
into somebody else effectively?
And that becomes kind
of a part of the pitch.
Whether you're trying to
communicate your design
vision to your team or to
executives or to your audience,
you need to kind of remember
why you want to do it.
What got you excited?
What is the key thing that's
really motivating you?
And then you step
back and say, OK,
how can I recreate that
process in that person's head?
How can I make them
see or understand
or feel the way I feel
about this design direction?
And maybe it's not the
explicit, overt description
of what your game
is going to be.
Maybe it's more a
getting into their head,
into the emotional
motivation that drives you.
And maybe it's more
about the creativity
you'll have in this,
or the expressiveness,
or what it's going to feel
like, this nostalgic--
go back to your childhood
playing this thing
that you used to play.
There might be a
lot of directions
you kind of take that.
But in some sense, like
game design itself,
you're hacking psychology.
You're trying to
imagine, what does it
take to make that person
feel the way I feel.
It's almost like
reverse empathy--
how do I push my feelings
into that person?
Interestingly, most of the hits
I've had-- the really big hits,
SimCity, The Sims--
were the ideas that I got
amazing amount of pushback
from with almost everybody
I described it to initially.
And at some point, I actually
had to kind of reformulate
the way I was thinking about
it to then communicate it
effectively.
And I did.
You know, I kind of
thought, OK, what
is it about the way I was
talking about this thing that's
not hitting the mark
in their head the way
it hits in my head?
And eventually, I found
ways to actually communicate
what I was really
thinking, which
wasn't an explicit description
of the game design,
but more the feeling I was
going to have playing this game.
And if I could now figure
out, OK, now how can I
make them imagine that feeling?
And what do I say to them
to imagine that feeling
that I would imagine
feeling playing this game?
So I took, like, one
step deeper, really.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Right off the bat,
as soon as you think,
oh, I have an idea for a
game, tell your friends.
See what they say.
Tell other people.
Tell people you meet.
And you can just observe and
learn from the result of what
they--
the questions they ask you,
what they seem interested in,
or they want to
know more about it,
or they want to talk
about something else.
You learn very rapidly.
And then when it comes
to the point of now
you're pitching the team
members or executives,
you will have refined that idea
quite a bit up to that point
already.
You don't want to wait until
you're actually pitching it
to somebody who matters.
Typically, we try to go for
what's called the elevator
pitch, eventually.
Initially, when I work
on a game, I'll sit there
and I'll describe
for 10 minutes,
oh, well, there's a game
where you do this, that,
and the other, and it works
like that, duh duh duh duh duh.
But eventually, you want to get
that down to, like, one minute
or 30 seconds.
There's no easy formula
for that at all.
I think repetition, or trying
a hundred different things is
probably the most
effective thing I found.
One thing that we would
do on the larger games,
we would go to a
trade show like E3.
And a lot of times,
we would be talking
about a game before
release, pretty early on,
to certain press members.
A lot of times I would be in
there giving a description
to interviewers, but
it would be every five
minutes a different
interviewer comes in.
And then another one comes
in, another one comes in,
another one comes in.
So that actually became a
great opportunity for me
to figure out how
to refine the pitch.
I would try a pitch
with this person.
I would notice them
getting kind of bored,
looking at their thing during
that part of the pitch.
They'd get wide-eyed
and look at me
attentively during
another part of the pitch.
So the next person
that came in the room,
I would expand on those
areas, prune the other ones,
try it on that person.
So I was actually iteratively
evolving the pitch rapidly
over the course of one day.
And that, I found,
actually-- we would also
across team members--
other designers
or team members who
might be there talking
to people about it.
And they would come back to
me and say, oh, they really
got interested when
they heard this part,
but they didn't seem to
care about that part.
So we'd actually compare notes,
and we'd actually together,
as a team, try to
refine that pitch.
OK, let's talk more about
this, lean into that,
lean away from there.
So the pitch is
something that I think
will be evolving over time.
Initially, you're going
to come up with this idea,
and you might tell somebody
at your company or a friend
or whatever, and that's going
to be the very first time.
And it's going to be horrible.
I mean, you're just not
going to convey it very well.
And maybe the idea in
your head isn't very well
formulated, either.
Maybe you just have a very
fuzzy idea of the kind of game
you're thinking of.
So in your head as well,
you are refining that model
and trying to make that
thing more and more fun.
As you interact and tell more
and more people about it,
I think you will naturally
evolve it, naturally
discover the most effective
way to communicate it.
And so I'd say
repetition is probably
the best rule of thumb.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Frequently, the game
designer is also
the person that's trying
to assemble the team that's
going to build this product.
And as you're
building that team,
one of the very first things--
skills-- that you
really have to have
is the ability to communicate
your design to your team.
And continually, even when
you're refining your idea
or changing it, you need to make
sure the team is aware of that.
And it's more understanding
the direction you're
going, not the destination.
And over time, as they come to
you with, should we do A or B?
And you start saying,
B, B, B, they'll
start learning to
predict your decisions.
And they'll start making more
and more of those decisions.
If they're unclear,
they'll still come to you.
So in some sense, you're
educating your entire team
ongoingly about
what the design is
and where it's going to head.
This is a more granular
version of the same process
you're going to use
to pitch your idea.
When you go out to
other people and try
to sell them on the idea,
to fund it or whatever,
you're going to basically
try to communicate
very clearly to them what's
in your head, what you're
imagining.
When I did The Sims, it
was a big challenge for me.
And I was-- within my own
company was rejected many
times, because I was describing
this game-- first of all,
I'd never--
after the product was
about halfway done,
I never once called
it this again,
but I used to call it Dollhouse.
That was the initial
name for the game.
And I found that it
was such a loaded term
that any male gamer, they
hear a game called Dollhouse,
they're not going
to play that game.
So that was one thing I learned.
Also, as I pitched this
to executives and stuff,
I was talking about
this cool game
where you're
managing these people
and they have limited
time and all this stuff.
But what they were
hearing was, here's
a game where you
take out the trash
and load the dishwasher, which
didn't sound very aspirational.
So I found that I had
to kind of rethink
the way I was presenting
the whole concept
and idea to somebody--
that no, it's little people.
You can mess with them, and they
live lives in your computer,
and it's up to you
to make them happy.
That was much more interesting,
rich kind of metaphor
for them to wrap
their heads around.
So you're not just
learning to pitch
to your design team or
your production team,
but also to people outside
within your company,
and then eventually
to the end consumer.
Eventually, you're going
to put an ad on the web
or in a box or whatever.
But you're going to have
to clearly and concisely
communicate to somebody
what this game is,
why they want to play it.
Because they're going to
start playing it in their head
as soon as they hear about it.
Before they even see
the game, as soon
as somebody describes it, oh,
you should check out this game,
it's about X, Y, and Z, they're
going to start imagining, OK,
that sounds kind of fun.
And they're actually playing
the game, a very simple version
of the game that they're
imagining in their head.
And that game has to be fun.
That's the first game
you're actually designing,
is the pitch.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
If you're pitching to your team
members, designers, whatnot,
they want to know--
they're going to want
to hear something that's
unique and interesting they're
going to be proud to build,
and something that's
buildable, because they're
going to be responsible for
actually having to build it,
and something that sounds
creatively challenging.
That's what they're looking for.
And so you have to pitch--
here's something that's going
to be really cool to build,
unique, people are going to
love it, and we can make it.
When you're pitching
to the executives--
it depends on the company, how
big it is and all this stuff--
but basically, whatever
the big hit was last year,
it's like that but better.
That's kind of the cliche.
Obviously, the most successful
genre in any format,
almost, is the sequel.
So if it's a
sequel, they're just
going to want to know that
you're going to execute it
well and not screw it up.
If it's an original
thing, they're
going to basically be
measuring against that.
Should I invest in
this original thing
or put more money
into the next version
of this popular franchise?
And at that point,
a lot of it's just
going to be based upon
your track record.
Now, as you're pitching
to an audience, of course,
now you're kind of
saying, try my game out.
Or in journalists is a
whole different thing--
pitching to a
journalist, they're
going to want to write an
interesting story, something
where they can actually exhibit
a fair amount of creativity
in their review or
their writing of it.
So if you give them
something where they can also
take a creative spin
in their writing,
that sounds more
attractive to them.
There's actually a
pretty big distinction,
I think, between
what I call the game
journalists and general media.
When you're pitching
to a game journalist,
they're going to be very jaded.
Everybody's coming
to them saying,
oh, I'm going to
build the next big hit
and it's going to be
duh, duh, duh, duh, duh.
And they're going to want
to hear something that,
to them, actually sounds
creative, unique, something
that really is fresh
within the game industry,
because they hear all these
ideas within the game industry.
But also they want to believe
that whoever is pitching
them can actually execute this.
A lot of people can
give a great pitch,
but they can never
build a product.
General media, I think it's
a little bit different story.
For them, it's going
to be more like,
why does my audience care?
You know, it's a game.
So there almost has
to be a hook into them
where, oh, people
that don't even
play games will be interested
in this because of x, y, and z.
Maybe it's topical,
or maybe it's
involving some new technology
or something, whatever it is.
But they almost
need another hook
to understand why their
wider audience is also
going to tune into this
thing that they kind of think
of as a niche product.
So I think you need to kind
of understand the motivations
of each of these groups.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
The pitching style I eventually
developed, which I'm not sure
is even that successful, is
trying to get people back
to the original topic.
You know, here's why
I think ants are cool.
Here's why I think it's cool
to construct little buildings
and put little people in them.
Here's why I think
evolution is cool.
So I try to usually start
with the topic, why I
think I got motivated in that.
And then kind of back
into-- and here's
a game where you get to
make this and do that.
And I found that the
more we can reference
the player in the
pitch, generally
the better the pitch went.
It's not like, here's a world in
which this happens, but here's
a world in which
you are the mayor,
and you get to decide
where to put the roads,
and you get to do this,
that, and the other.
So if you start to say,
these are the things
that you can do in
the game and make
that sound interesting,
that kind of reverses
the whole thing--
rather than, here's
this thing I want to sell you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
One of the fundamental
questions that you're probably
going to get, especially if
the pitch is very unrefined,
is why is that going to be fun?
Which is a hard
question to answer,
because if your
pitch really conveyed
what it needed to
convey, they wouldn't
be asking that question.
It would already be fun
in their imagination.
They wouldn't ask
you that question.
So that really indicates
a key part of your pitch,
you're missing.
People will try to triangulate
your idea against other games,
and they'll say, oh, is
it kind of like this game
but a little bit of that?
Or this game that's turn-based
instead of real-time?
In their mind, they're
kind of looking
at the landscape of all
the games they know about
and trying to figure out where
yours falls into that landscape
by finding landmarks nearby,
saying it's somewhere
between there and there.
And that's going
to be very common.
And if your game is not
in that landscape at all--
if it's an outlier over here--
that's both good and bad.
It's hard for them
to triangulate,
because they've never
seen anything like that.
But on the other
hand, it could feel
fresh if you could
pitch it the right way.
You can almost kind
of take the outliers
in that direction, say,
oh, it's kind of like this,
but we took it in a
totally different direction
that nobody's ever done before.
Now, if it's understandable
and you can basically,
again, download that it's
totally different in this way--
so they can actually
start imagining why
that's good, why that's fun--
that can be very successful.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
A lot of startup
pitches, somebody says,
OK, here's the cool new
trend that's just popped up
in social media or in
platforms or whatever it is,
and we're going
to be right on it.
We're going to be
riding that wave.
And so I think that the
people that are really
involved in these industries,
they're kind of jaded.
They know that every
pitch coming this month
is going to involve
Facebook or this or that,
or whatever the hot thing
of the month is going to be.
So I think that you have to be
a little bit careful about that
in particular.
I think you need to feel
like your thing, whatever
it is, is standing on its
own legs, on its own merits,
and it's not just
going to be successful
because it's part of this trend
that's happening this month.
There's another actually really
important part to, I think,
pitching, which is
that recognizing
when you've sold your idea.
Don't continue and unsell it.
A lot of times, if
you give somebody
a fairly brief
explanation of your idea,
leave a lot of blanks in there.
The person you're pitching to
will generally fill the blanks
in in your favor.
This is the way I would
fill in those blanks,
so you're probably going to
do it the way I would want to.
And so if you
leave those blanks,
they're going to imagine
those filled in the way they
would want to fill them in.
If you keep going
with your pitch
and start filling in those
blanks in a different direction
that they don't like, you
have now unsold the idea
after you just sold it to them.
So I think it's very important
to realize when to stop.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
The one thing that I think
is the biggest mistake
that I see is when
people lead with genre.
The first thing
they say is, I want
to build a first-person
shooter that
does duh, duh, duh, duh, duh.
To me, as soon as I
hear genre, in my mind
they've already basically
compartmentalized
how far they're going to go.
They're not even
willing to think of it
outside of that genre or
an expansion of the genre,
but they've already put
themselves in a box--
a fairly limited box that's
been very thoroughly explored.
Now, it's OK if it's a
first-person shooter.
That's fine.
But maybe it's a first-person
shooter with relationships
and social networks,
and there might be
a lot of other things involved.
But when they say first-person
shooter, in my mind
I'm automatically putting it
in the very limited little box
of experience.
I think other ones is people
tend to be too verbose.
They tend to add way too
many details way too early.
There was that saying
about, your garden
is not complete until there's
nothing else you can remove.
I think for your pitch, you want
to remove every possible word
that is unnecessary,
and refine it down
to that level of conciseness.
And those are, I think, the
two most common mistakes
I hear when people give pitches.
The third probably comes
more down to energy,
that if the person
giving you the pitch
doesn't really feel
excited about it,
and it's more like, oh,
yeah, I got this game idea,
it's going to be,
yeah, you know--
how can they expect me
to be excited about it?
But if somebody comes up to
me with a very concise idea,
they lead with the topic or
what's cool about it to them,
they don't say
anything unnecessary,