WILL WRIGHT (VOICEOVER): Now
let's check out another game
from a different
aspiring designer.
So my game is
"Flooded Market."
It's a multiplayer
strategy game where
you're going to enter
the cutthroat real estate
market of the sinking
city of San Francisco.
OK.
Yeah.
Cool.
So you're going to be
outbidding other players.
You're going to be renting.
You're going to be
renovating these properties.
And all the while, turn
by turn, climate change
is going to cause the
sea level to rise, as it
is in our starting screen.
So this is fast
global warming.
Yeah.
Accelerated global warming.
And as it moves up, it's going
to transform these properties
from their regular selves
into pristine, high quality,
beachfront property.
[LAUGHING]
And then destroy them
right afterwards.
And so you're trying to catch
that wave of inflated prices.
And that along with paying
off the right politicians
will let you--
So this is multiplayer.
It's multiplayer.
Up to 50 players
can play in a game.
We haven't tested
with 50 players.
But the system is
there to support it.
And the notion is that you
have all these players creating
an economy that you're
then going to try
to optimize and act inside of.
And, ideally, all
the player actions
are driving the simulation
while the simulation drives.
Well, right off the bat,
I love your intro screen.
Yeah.
I mean, it looks
fun already, just
looking at the intro screen.
Yeah.
The intro screen is to make
that striking first impression.
OK.
So let's see the game.
Yeah.
Let's get into it.
So you're playing.
We're going to
create a game here.
I like the pitch, by the way.
I mean, it's very
succinct, concise.
And it sounds fun.
Name this Will's Game.
So we're going to
launch in here.
So right now we're
going to kind of get
the gist, the lay of the land.
There's San Francisco, for
those who recognize it.
WILL WRIGHT: So you have a
real map of the real city.
GAME DESIGNER: Right.
Yeah.
We pulled from map
data to help get
elevations and locations,
and also house prices
to start off with.
WILL WRIGHT: All right.
GAME DESIGNER: So we
have a house downtown
that's worth $1.3 million.
It's five stars.
WILL WRIGHT: Are these
all things for sale?
GAME DESIGNER: These
are all things for sale.
Yeah.
So I have a budget.
And I'm choosing how to spend,
invest in real estate here.
GAME DESIGNER: That's right.
Yeah.
You have $3.8 million up here.
And let's say we could
even select this house.
We can bid on it.
This one, we can take
a look at, and say, OK.
It's got some nice views.
It's got a decent quality.
We can upgrade that
later if we want.
It's kind of getting
close to the water.
20% water level.
WILL WRIGHT: Yeah.
GAME DESIGNER: We can check.
Its elevations at 50 meters.
The water right
now is at 0 meters.
But that'll change as
soon as the turn ends,
which is fast approaching.
So this turn based?
Turn based game.
OK.
GAME DESIGNER: So we can
also place a bid here.
And then our first property.
What are you thinking?
Do you want to list it?
Get rid of it?
Do you want to upgrade it?
Do you want to start renting?
WILL WRIGHT: Let's upgrade it.
GAME DESIGNER: OK.
So we're going to put
that up to six stars.
And now it jumped
to $1.4 million.
But I really want to
go one turn to see how
far up the water's going to go.
GAME DESIGNER: Oh yeah.
Yeah.
So we can zoom out, if
I can zoom out here.
So the water only
went up two meters.
So we got some time.
That will increase
as the game goes on.
So it will be kind of
this building clock.
So I'm guessing there's kind
of like a sweet spot I want
to get in here where
I hold it long enough
for it to appreciate right
before it's inundated.
Yeah.
Exactly.
And it takes a couple
turns to kind of do
the actions you want, to
kind of flip these houses.
And so--
Now, am I buying and selling
these houses to other players,
or from the computer?
So you're doing both.
If no one bids on it, the
computer will pick up the slack
and buy it.
There's kind of this secret
economy guy who's making sure
that everyone gets paid.
Right.
But other players can buy
your house once you list it.
OK.
And so right now we have--
if we zoom out, we have all
these different player icons.
And those are all the
49 other AI players
that are playing with us.
WILL WRIGHT: OK.
GAME DESIGNER: And so
if I hit the End Turn,
you'll see them actually
kind of run around.
So they all move around the map,
buying and selling properties.
We can also do that.
These green properties are
the properties we can move to.
They're adjacent to downtown.
So we can hop over
here to Civic Center.
And now we have new properties
that we can buy in, new
neighbors we can buy
in, and new properties--
or new neighborhoods we can--
Oh, so we have a
location in this world.
Yeah.
We have this tiny little avatar.
And so that's going
to buy stuff near me.
Right.
OK.
So right now we're trying
to incorporate as much player
to player interaction
as possible.
Right.
Right now they're kind of
using this middleman that's
the simulation.
So I buy and sell properties.
I can upgrade and
affect properties.
And then other players can
interact with those properties.
But I can't interact
with players so much.
I can outbid them.
Right.
And if we--
I presume you played "Mule."
I have played "Mule."
Way, way back.
And they had that cool
auction interaction.
Yeah.
No.
That was--
I'm almost
expecting, you know,
some kind of like exciting
point here where I'm
trying to bid with other
players for a property that's
very desirable.
I think showcasing that might
be a good direction to go.
Or creating some sort of
moment where everyone's
throwing money at each other.
Dramatic tension.
Yeah.
And that could be
broadcasted out
to other players, where they get
to watch this battle of bucks
and dollars go back and forth.
Right.
It was actually also an
interesting combination
of kind of turn
based and real time.
Yeah.
That's true.
Because that part of
the auction was real time.
The rest of it was turn based.
Yeah.
So you had this constant
tension between whether or not
you were paying attention
to the real time
component of the game.
Yeah.
So and I'm playing this
online against other players?
You would be playing this.
Yeah.
How long is a turn?
So a turn is an average
of about 35 seconds.
In early turns you
have more time.
Oh.
So it's fast.
It's fast.
Yeah.
In the early turns
you have more time.
You have 45 seconds.
And then near the end of the
game you have about 25 seconds.
So that's a lot of
your dramatic tension
is how much you can
accomplish in 35, 40 seconds.
Right.
I'm not sure how
much of the game
I want to be about
time management.
Right.
I would like players to
feel comfortable enough
with the time they're
given to make the decisions
and choices they have.
Right.
So that was one of the
reasons why we limited it
to five properties.
So right now we have
two of five max.
Much easier to--
Yeah.
Previously you
didn't have a limit.
And I got up to 40 properties.
And so I had 45 seconds to make
decisions on 40 properties.
And I was having a very
stressful time of it.
Tell me a little bit about
what you've learned in testing.
So we've learned that
people really like--
they see houses
almost like people.
OK.
They see houses as having
identities and having stories,
and locations as having
those identities and stories.
They see this as a tragedy
playing out before them.
Right.
This is a train wreck happening.
And they're trying to
profit from it, which is
uncomfortable for some people.
You know, I think it's
going to have a whole lot
to do with the pacing of it.
OK.
You know, 35 seconds.
Is a new player going to
feel like it's overwhelming.
All the other people know
exactly what they're doing.
Yeah.
And I haven't even
started in 35 seconds.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Is there some way to
kind of moderate that?
Yeah.
Some delicate onboarding is
probably a good next step.
Because that'll also let
us get to new testers
without having to
sit them all down,
like the, and walk them
through all the steps.
I'm just wondering.
I've never really
seen a game like this.
But I could almost
imagine something
where you're interleaving.
The new players are in certain
zones where they get a minute.
And one of their turns
is equal to two turns
of an experienced player.
Oh.
So we could--
And so you keep
it in lockstep.
But the new players
actually get longer.
And they're on the
same time cycle.
But it's kind of interleaved.
Yeah.
And maybe they're--
OK.
I can certainly see some really
interesting balance point
being reached, that
we could even use them
as the generators of
content for the players who
are playing faster games.
So instead of having that
invisible economic agent
behind the--
And maybe they're buying
the cheaper properties.
Maybe the residential properties
are on this every other turn
time scale.
Yeah.
You have a minute.
When you get into
the more expensive
commercial properties,
it's every 30 seconds.
And that's the
experience player.
Yeah.
And so we have a way for them
to play together, but also
at their own pace.
At their own pace.
And they don't feel
like they're-- you know,
it doesn't feel too fast
for the beginning player,
or too slow for the
experienced player.
I hadn't thought of that.
I grew up playing
turn based games.
And some of these like, you
know, turn based war games,
I'd spend an hour sitting there,
planning every little thing.
You know, other times
they go a lot faster.
But when you're having to
wait for other players,
and I've done all my
stuff in 30 seconds,
and I'm waiting for the five
minute turn to end, you know,
it's incredibly boring.
[INAUDIBLE]
So I think
figuring out some way
to where players can
kind of select the time
scale at which
they're comfortable,
which also might be the level
of experience or risk, you know,
that they're
encountering in the game.
Can I zoom in to the
visuals, like where
the water's coming up?
Oh yeah.
I just want to--
Let's get in there.
Oh, yeah.
That's cool.
I like this.
GAME DESIGNER: Yeah.
So we can look around.
Can you rotate the map?
Or is it--
Right now it's staying
north to west to southeast.
WILL WRIGHT: OK.
GAME DESIGNER: And staying
kind of locked there.
WILL WRIGHT: But I can
kind of zoom in and see,
this is where I live while
the water's coming at you.
GAME DESIGNER: Yeah.
Yeah.
Look at that part.
You know, you mentioned
right at the beginning
that some players found
it a little macabre, or--
A little distressing.
Distressing.
Yeah.
I find that interesting.
And actually, I think
that's kind of cool.
Because that indicates a level
of emotional involvement,
that they're emotionally
involved in what this is.
Back when Kubrick did "Dr.
Strangelove," way back,
a lot of people criticized him
for making fun of nuclear war.
But at the same
time, he actually
got a whole generation
of kids, you
know, aware of how
stupid nuclear war was.
And emotionally
invested in it.
By making a dark
comedy about it.
You know.
Yeah.
And I think that's one of the
things that really attracts me
to this concept.
I think that the turn based
thing is kind of old school,
but it has a lot of
cool opportunities.
I really enjoy
turn based gaming.
And I think that there
might be some opportunities
to kind of do things
with turn based gaming
that haven't been done before.
And I think, in some
sense, you might
be able to attract a lot
more players to it, because--
If I have a spin
on that kind of thing
that they're expecting.
Yeah.
And keep it
approachable like this.
Yeah.
But I think it's a
very cool, unique idea.
And I think that, you
know, the biggest challenge
I would see right off the
bat is going to be moderating
the player involvement
and skill level such
that new players don't feel
overwhelmed by the pace
of the game.
Yeah.
Or the opportunities
that the other players
are taking from them.
You know, that you don't have
the experienced players preying
on the newbies.
Right.
But I really like the idea.
And I think your pitch was
very effective and intriguing
as well.
Cause right off the bat, you
didn't really talk about genre.
You just kind of talked
about, here's the topic.
Here's how it plays.
And in my mind, I was
starting to play the game.
And it sounded fun.
So and I think
it's a great idea.
And I think you'll
learn a lot, you