[MUSIC PLAYING]
As I think about
platforms, you know,
maybe I think about them in a
different way than most people.
But I think of the technology as
just one part of the platform.
I think just as important
is the cultural platform.
What kind of culture?
Is this being played
in China, in America?
Is it being played by
serious gamers in Germany?
And the third being the actual
demographic, the person.
Is this being played by
young girls, by older men,
by a whole family together?
Is it a very social experience?
So really they are almost
like three platforms
we're dealing with here.
There's the
technological platform,
the cultural platform, and the
kind of demographic platform.
Understanding all three
is totally important.
You know, I think
that we are getting
a lot of freedom on the
technological platform
that we did not have before.
If it's a really big
game, you can eventually
put it on any platform
you want to really.
You know, it's a matter
of where you start.
The other ones are really going
to be much more constrained
over time.
You know, if this game is really
targeting 12-year-old girls,
it doesn't matter whether
it's on an iPad or a PC.
That's kind of what the
game's DNA is about.
So I tend to think of all
three together as the platform.
The whole world has
changed so much,
you know, in terms of app
markets, mobile, tablets,
online.
And it looked, you know, with
console development and really
big PC game
development, you know,
the teams were getting
larger and larger,
and the budgets in the tens
of millions of dollars.
And all of a sudden, you know,
it looked like, you know,
we were doomed.
You know, you had
to have $50 million
and a team of 100
people design a game.
Now it's totally reversed.
Now we're back to where a small
group of passionate people
can create a cool game
on an iPad or whatever,
and release it pretty
effectively on the app store.
Now it's a matter of, you
know, press, marketing, and how
you actually get people to
download it and try it out.
But at least you
have the ability
to create and have it
available to people.
And also to learn about it, you
know, very quickly, and iterate
on it.
So the dynamics have
changed dramatically.
And I like that idea just
as a design point of view
that now I have the
opportunity to learn much more
effectively and much
faster from our players,
and shift directions-- you
know, pivot very easily.
Whereas before pivots
were incredibly expensive.
So to me-- and, you
know, also the fact
that it's now kind of more
ubiquitous, in terms of I
might have my laptop, my iPad or
my phone with me in my pocket.
I can have parts of the game
that are very interstitial.
I could pull out of my
pocket my phone and play
for a minute or two, go
home, pick up my iPad,
do something else.
But still play it, you
know, on a browser on my PC
if I want to.
So the fact that the game is
becoming kind of more platform
independent is very attractive
to me as a designer.
I think nowadays
we actually have
a much wider range of
potential business models
than we used to.
You know, it used to
be that you basically
had to put this in a
box and sell it for $40.
Unless it was
something that people
would pay $40 for, and go to the
store, and buy off the shelf,
you know, it wasn't
going to make sense.
Now we have a wide
range of ways.
Free to play.
Monetize incrementally.
You know, whatever it is.
But I think from the
design point of view,
you fundamentally have to create
a compelling, excellent, unique
experience.
And if you really hit
that mark, now you
have all number of
opportunities for monetizing it.
You know, I don't really
think in terms of,
let's first decide how we're
going to monetize this.
And now let's design it.
I think in terms of,
let's design something
that's going to be just
so damn cool that people
are going to want it.
And now we have this whole
range of ways in which we
can choose to monetize it.
You know, and over time, as
we're developing the game,
and the world around us is
changing very rapidly as well,
and looking at the
platforms we're on,
we can zero in on the
right monetary model.
Or we might even offer several
different monetary models.
There doesn't have
to be just one.
We have this wide range
of economic models
now, and how to
monetize your game.
And a lot of that's going to be
relative to your player base.
You know, who are
expecting to buy this game
or play this game.
And these people,
depending on who they are,
are going to have certain
comfort zones and certain kind
of uncomfort zones.
And some people,
they were coming
from "World of Warcraft."
And they're used to,
you know, subscription.
Other people aren't.
You know, for them they
have to download it for free
and be able to play
it for five hours
before they will
spend a dime on it.
That's going to
depend a lot on that.
So I think once you
start zeroing in
and you get a sense of who's
playing this game, what
their prior
experience is, and how
they are used to monetizing
their entertainment,
then you can figure out--
I think it's easier
to now adapt your game
design to that
monetary model than it
is to pick a monetary model,
and then force it on people
that are uncomfortable with it.
I tend to not want
to get too dependent
on specific affordances,
you know, through interface
or otherwise in a platform.
But if they're there,
happily use them.
And, again, the goal being that
the interface and my agency
through into this game
should be transparent.
So if anything actually
makes that agency
feel more transparent and
disappear in my head, fine.
I'll use it.
Whether it's VR, or whether
it's accelerometer on my phone,
or a joystick on my desktop.
I'd say that I would not want
to build a game concept that's
just built around the
accelerometer, for instance.
I mean, maybe parts of
the game can use that.
But not a critical part.
You know, if I happen
to have the phone.
But maybe I'm using
my iPad, and I
don't want to tilt the screen.
Whatever it might be.
So I would say that I would
use these things as kind
of like upside, or affordance--
what should I say?
Lower the friction of the
interaction with the player.
But not something that the game
features are totally dependent
upon.
But occasionally, you
know, I'll find things
like that that change the
way I feel about a game.
I've played a lot of
racing games on the PC.
And they're kind of
fun and all that.
And the first time I played
a racing game on my iPad,
I was actually holding
it, and then just
turning the whole iPad.
And it felt so much
more natural to me
than using a joystick
or the keyboard.
And I really enjoyed it.
I found that I actually
enjoyed racing games
on my iPad more, just cause
it felt so natural tilting it
back and forth.
So sometimes these
things will zero you
in on something that gets
you into a different dynamic
than you had before.
I always preferred
PC development,
just because it was, in some
ways, a lot more malleable.
It was easier to iterate,
easier to kind of try out
and go in different directions.
You know, the consoles were
in this very kind of lockstep
generation release cycles.
You know, every five years
would be the next Xbox
or the next Playstation.
The PC was something that
was kind of slowly ramping
the whole time.
And also the PC initially
was a much better platform
for social sharing,
and things like that.
People on their PCs were
connected to the network
much more readily,
until the consoles were.
And even the
consoles, typically it
was like these
walled gardens, where
if you did it on this
platform, you couldn't really
cross into that platform.
And a lot of licensing
restrictions, and things
like that.
So the PC, just
to me, was always
kind of a more free, open
ended design platform.
To become a console
developer you
also needed to buy an
expensive console system,
and so many workstations.
And, you know, there was
a lot of expense to it.
And we started my first
company, Maxis, on a shoestring.
And, we can always just buy
PCs cheap, get programmers.
So economically it was
a much easier entry.
But also, you know,
in the early days
we were actually developing most
of our stuff on the Macintosh
first.
And we would convert
it to the PC later.
The Macintosh was just
kind of a joy to program.
It was a very clean system.
It didn't have all the
different, you know,
video card and
configuration issues.
But there turned out to
be something else that
was actually really
to our benefit, which
is that, in the early days,
most of the journalists
out there had Macs, not PCs.
And since our games were
released on the Mac first,
they were some of the very
first decent games on the Mac.
And so writers that were writing
for these different magazines,
you know, they would
tend to, you know,
see our games as
one of the few they
could actually kind of try.
And then if they liked it a
lot, they would write about it.
Because that's what they
wrote on was the Mac.
You know, so our
first big break was--
I think it was in
"Newsweek" magazine.
The first full page
review of a computer game
was in "Newsweek."
And it was because the writer
happened to have a Mac.
And our game was available on
the Mac, one of the few games.
And he loved it and
he wrote about it.
So the Mac was kind of, in
a sense, a hidden advantage