[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: Within these
games, within these worlds,
there are a lot of moving
parts, a lot of dynamics.
You want this to be a rich,
interesting environment
for the player to explore.
My approach has always
been to step back and think
of this whole thing as a system.
What is the system
that's happening here?
And actually, when you get down
to the engineering of things
like simulations,
you really do need
to think of it as a system.
And you need to think about
it, what is my paradigm?
What is the way in which I'm
going to structure the world?
How is it going to operate?
What are the parts?
How do they interact
with each other?
Systems are interesting.
In some sense,
what they're going
to lead us to is this idea
that everybody in a game
is going to be exploring the
possibility space of that game.
Where are all the
possible states
that that world could be in?
For something like chess,
it's fairly obvious,
although it's a very
big, branching tree.
It's a branching tree.
Every move in chess leads to
another set of possible moves.
And you unfold that branching
tree of all the possible moves
of chess and you come up
with an astronomical number,
but it's still finite.
There are a finite number
of possible states in chess.
The very early games had
very simple branching trees,
very much like chess.
Basically, structure branching
trees that were explicitly
put there by the designer.
And this is very much
like one of those old
choose your own adventure books.
If you're going to go into
the cave, go to page 7.
If you're going to go to the
top of the hill, go to page 20.
But basically, the
writer's having
to fill out every possible
branch of that book.
So it's a very limited
structure, a very limited world
to explore.
Later games started doing what
I call gated experiences, a game
like, let's say, Quake or Doom.
You're within a level and
you have all this agency
and freedom within that
level, but until you
get through the level and get
to that locked door at the end,
basically, you're
in this little room,
this little, small regional
possibility of space.
Once you get through
that, it opens
another regional
possibility of space.
So you basically have
these little islands
of possibility of space
with gates between them.
And then there have been basic
hybrids of these two models
over time.
But then as players
and designers
started building more
open-ended simulations,
it opened up a lot more.
So as we started building
open-ended games--
sandbox games, Grand
Theft Auto, Sims--
we're actually looking
at a possibility of space
that's vast, large.
And this is when we
really have to now view it
as a system, not as a
branching tree of possibility.
We're not going to map
out every possibility.
What we're going to
do is we're going
to build a set of things
that interact in a way
to, basically, generate
these possibilities for us.
For the Sims, the
way I visualized
it was that, basically,
you had two directions you
could go for achievement.
You go for social achievement
or material achievement.
You could try to make a
lot of friends in the Sims,
build a big family,
have people like you.
Or you could try to
make a lot of money,
buy things for your
house, grow, acquire.
And really, the way I visualized
it was almost like a bowling
alley here, in that if I went
down one path or the other,
it was like getting
stuck in a gutter.
To achieve maximum
success, you had
to balance the two
achievements together
to get the highest
level of achievement,
which is right down the middle.
If you went too far to
one side or the other,
you'd actually get stuck on
a local maxim on either side.
So this is basically the
way I was visualizing
a certain region of
the possibility space
within the Sims the
players would encounter.
We use that as a guideline
for tuning the game.
After we actually were really
in deep tuning of the game--
we had thousands of
players playing it--
we, in fact, were actually
mapping the real possibility
of space they were
going through,
and we were actually looking at
how the players would fan out
across these dimensions.
These are graphs here
of the way players
were actually fanning out.
At first, we saw too
many on this side,
not enough on that side.
We changed the parameters
of the game a little bit
and actually evened
out so that these
were equally attractive
to a wide group
players, that whole space.
Going a little bit deeper, and
actually, how do we build this?
How do we think about it?
How do we engineer it?
I needed to find
two things here,
the way I think about them.
What is structure?
What is something made of?
What are its parts?
A structure of a
tree, it has a trunk.
It has branches.
It has leaves.
Then there are dynamics,
and this is process.
This is what happens over time.
In this case, it's what
can happen to a tree?
How does it grow?
Can you cut it down?
Can you turn it into firewood?
What happens over the seasons?
So those are all
the dynamics that
can happen to a
tree, which are very
different than the
structure of a tree.
From that, I started
imagining the different things
I use as a designer to
build these systems.
And structurally, I
basically think in terms
of three types of structure.
One is what I call agents.
These are objects that can move
around, interact in a world
somehow.
Next is networks.
These are things that are
connected through some type
of relationship formally.
And it could be relationships.
It could be economic.
It could be biological.
It could be anything.
And the last one is layers.
And this tends to
be more spatial.
Something like
Sim City, there's,
basically, the pollution layer.
There's the traffic layer.
These are things
that are specialized.
And everything in the
game, like Sim City,
is one of these three things.
It's either an agent,
a network, or layer.
The road, basically, is a
network of intersections
connecting areas.
Something like pollution,
crime are layers.
Cars moving around, people
around, even buildings
are agents, sitting on the
landscape with some identity
and some parameters.
So that's the typologies,
or the structure, of games,
the way I think of systems
Next, when we get into dynamics,
any of these topologies,
any one of these dynamics can
occur, things like propagation.
How does something
spread through that?
Growth, grouping, order,
allocation, mapping,
specialization, all
these are dynamics that
occur within these typologies.
In some sense, these
are now the verbs.
The topologies are
the nouns that we're
building the game out of.
These dynamics are the verbs.
And lastly, how do
we think about this?
What is our underlying metaphor
for bringing these things
together?
And that's what
I call paradigms.
Initially, there
were things way back
in the '40s called cybernetics.
But really, it was very simple
systems, like a thermostat.
And originally,
this was developed
for things like autopilot, a
very simple machine control.
Governors on steam
engines, even,
are an example of a
cybernetic system.
But in essence, it's a
very simple, little system
trying to seek a behavior,
seek some set point.
It might be temperature.
It might be the speed
of an engine, whatever.
It was only in the '50s,
when the very first
primitive computers
started coming around,
that the idea of system
dynamics came out.
A guy named Jay Forrester kind
of came up with this concept.
And it's almost hydrological.
It's almost based upon
a chemical refinery
in that in system dynamics,
you just basically have valves
and flows and containers.
A container might be population
or it might be number of cars.
A flow might be birth
rate or death rate.
And you have little algorithms
that will adjust the flows.
For the birth rate,
death rate, you
can see what the
population does over time.
And he would build these
very elaborate models
of very complicated systems,
things like the world--
food production.
Or in fact, he was
the first person
to actually build a city model
using this kind of paradigm.
The next one I'm
going to talk about
is cellular automata, which
really kind of came to its own
when PCs were really
starting to come out
and people had access
to cheaper computers.
Although, in fact,
cellular automata were
predated system dynamics.
Cellular automata are
basically the idea
that there's a grid and cells.
And these cells can
either be on or off
or have quantities in them.
But basically, all the
dynamics within that
are based upon the neighbors and
the behavior of the neighbors.
The simplest example of
this is a game called Life.
John Conway, a mathematician,
came up with this very simple
system, and it's a grid.
Actually, I'm going to
go to the whiteboard,
just to explain this because
it's actually quite simple.
So in Conway's Life, you
basically have a little world.
It's a grid.
Within this grid, every cell can
either have one of two states.
It's either alive, it is full,
or it's dead and it's off.
Now, the rules
for Life basically
say that if one cell, right
here, has exactly three
neighbors-- and we're counting
all the neighbors like that.
If there are exactly three
cells alive around it,
like so, this empty
cell now comes to life.
On the next turn, the
new cell appears here.
Now, if a given cell
is already alive
and it has three or two
neighbors, it stays there.
If it has less than two or
more than three, it dies.
So this one only has one
neighbor, so it dies.
So basically, that's the whole
rule set for Conway's Life.
Now, it sounds very simple.
You're just counting whether
it has two or three neighbors
and whether it comes
to life or dies.
Turns out that when
you turn this on
and you put a few
cells in there,
there's an explosion
of complexity.
All this stuff starts
happening, really unpredictable,
surprising stuff.
And people have studied
this thing for years.
I spent months studying.
In fact, I taught
myself programming
trying to program
Life and make it
faster and faster and faster.
As an example, if you
put this shape into Life
at the very beginning
and just start it,
it will explode into this whole
set of hundreds of things,
and start moving around
and have behavior.
And it's always exactly
the same every time.
It's deterministic.
But it's all a result of
the two simple little rules.
And this is one of the
best examples of emergence
that Conway, who programmed
this, discovered it.
There was no way he
could have predicted
the elaborate
behaviors that were
going to happen in this little
world based upon those two
rules.
It just emerges as
a result of that.
And it's emergent complexity.
So you have this amazingly
complex, little world
that's emerging out of this
incredibly simple, little rule
set.
Somebody asked me just recently
what my favorite game was,
and it's Go.
And the reason to Go
is my favorite game
is because Go has very
much the same property.
Go has two very simple
rules, one of which
almost never happens.
But yet the strategy of
Go is incredibly complex,
relative to the rules set.
And for me, that's a wonderful
aesthetic for game design.
When it's the simplest set of
rules that you can create that
leads to the widest
range of complexity
and the most interesting
world that you can explore,
with strategy and behavior.
Cellular automata actually
became a key part of Sim City
in the way it operates.
Basically, a lot of
complexity of Sim City
comes from this connected
to a system dynamics
model, like Jay Forrester had.
Again, Jay Forrester's model
was, basically, containers
with whatever.
Let's say population.
And then little valves
that would control.
This might be birth rate.
This might be death rate.
Later on, we might
have another one
that we add for migration,
whatever we want to.
Now, Jay Forrester came up with
this model, central dynamics,
and people started trying to
model a lot of different things
with it.
Back in the late
'60s, early '70s,
there was a group that
started building what they
called the World Dynamic model.
And they actually started
modeling the world economy,
food production, population
growth, all this stuff,
to get some sense of where
the world was headed.
In fact, they started a group
called the Club of Rome,
and there was a very
famous book published
called "The Limits to Growth."
And in that book,
they were basically
showing the results of
their world simulation
that they were
running around 1970.
And it was showing that
the world economy would
collapse around 1985 to 1990.
And food production,
people would starve.
And it didn't happen.
What turned out is they
looked back at the model
and they found that they were
off on a few little factors.
They didn't foresee the Green
Revolution, for instance,
that the efficiency of food
production per land area
was going to go up a little
bit more than they thought.
And what was surprising
was that that little
bit that they were off led to
an incredibly different result
than what really happened.
And that was really
our first inkling
into what became known
as chaos theory, the idea
that sometimes the initial
starting position of something
can lead to a totally
different outcome
if it's just a
little bit displaced.
A good way to think
about chaos theory,
we have basically, what
we call, chaotic systems
and stable systems.
If I take a bowl, for
instance, like that,
and I drop a marble into
it, it might land here
or I might drop it there.
Either way, it's going
to go around a little bit
and it's going to pretty
much end up at the bottom.
OK, that's a stable system.
A chaotic system, if we take
that bowl and we invert it,
like so, and we drop a ball
and displace it a little bit,
now if it lands here, it
might roll way off over here.
If it lands right there, it
might roll way off over there.
So this is really
a chaotic system,
where a very small change
in the initial position
can lead to a wildly
different outcome.
And that's what they discovered
in the World Dynamic model.
And all of a
sudden, chaos theory
started putting real
limits on things
that we could predict
with simulations.
Turns out that
things like weather,
and even other things
like [INAUDIBLE],,
tend to be chaotic so
that even if we have
a very detailed simulation
and we put a lot of horsepower
behind it, there's
still going to be
a very deep level
of unpredictability
to these kind of a system.
Another direction that
these paradigms have taken
is called network theory.
And a network is just anything
containing nodes and links,
like that.
Turns out you can visualize
so many things as a network.
You can visualize biological
systems and metabolic systems,
things within your body, the way
the chemicals and proteins flow
through your body.
Economics, social
systems, all these things
can be visualized as a network.
And of course,
including the internet.
Now, it turns out that
these networks have
some surprising properties.
Things are just not obvious.
One of those things
is that if you
have a disconnected
network, like this,
and you start randomly
connecting these things,
just randomly, it turns
out that all you need
is the average of about one
connection per node to have
a fully connected
network, basically,
for any sized network.
So over time, if I just do
one connection per node,
I almost always
end up with almost
a fully connected network.
Another surprising result is
that for any sized network,
above a very simple
one like this,
the distance, what they
call the graph width,
between any two
points in this network
is almost never
more than six steps.
So from point there to
point there, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And this is, of course, the six
degrees of Kevin Bacon thing,
that even across
the earth, they've
shown that I can find
any other person on earth
through six steps of people.
I know this person.
That person knows that person.
I can connect myself to almost
any other person on the planet.
So these are very non-intuitive
things, but actually,
as a designer, this is
part of your language
that you can use within your
game to build these systems.
You can represent any kind
of system in your game.
Using multiple
paradigms, you can
choose which paradigm is
best suited for my game
when I'm building a system.
And this occurs both at
the conceptual level,
but also at the
engineering level as well.
So these become a
lot of things that I
think of as a
designer of systems
that I use to build games.
On top of this, there are
also certain properties
that I find interesting to
think, in terms of dimensions
within the system.
One is local to global,
how much of local effects
versus global effects
and where do they meet.
In Sim City,
something like traffic
is very local to that
one spot on the road.
The overall tax rate
of the city is global.
And there's some things
that are in between.
What's the police
effectiveness within the city?
Order to disorder.
Things that are
very, very ordered
become very predictable,
and sometimes you
want that in the game.
Other things are totally
disordered, random, chaotic.
And even things like
cooperation to competition
is a dimension within a game.
You can have some games
that are very competitive,
others that are
very cooperative.
But there are also a lot of
spots in between those two.
And sometimes the game can
actually shift where one moment
you're playing cooperatively,
another time you're
playing competitively.
One of my favorite
old games is Mule.
And Mule had that
beautifully done,
where you're competing
with other players.
But in some sense, if you
don't cooperate with them
to some degree, the entire
colony collapses and so
you all lose.
And so I love the fact
that that game actually
had cooperation and competition
in the same game structure.
I tend to be a
very visual person.
In school, I didn't think math
was that interesting at all
until, at some point,
I started realizing
that I could basically
turn almost all of math
into geometry.
And I could take almost
any branch of math
and as soon as I could
imagine it as geometry,
I love it and it makes sense and
it's totally intuitive to me.
So that's just the way
I think about things,
is I tend to try to bring
it into the visual realm,
in essence.
There's a certain
part of my mind
that I think does very
good spatial reasoning.
Other people tend to
do better, I think,
with audio reasoning,
or something else.
But as a game designer,
I'm imagining, even
as a game player when
I come into a game,
I'm trying to imagine,
what are the things I
could do in this game?
How far can I go?
How hard is that?
In some sense, I'm
building a map.
Not an explicit overt
map of the terrain,
but a map of my abilities,
my agency, my freedom.
I always tend to visualize
that as some type of topology.
If it's a gated experience
maybe with rooms,
I see these as nodes
with connectors,
and that's just a way
for me to visualize
the topology of that structure.
It might be more free
floating agents moving around,
or it might be something very
rigid, like a cube or layers.
But even the
behavior, what we call
phase space in mathematics,
can be viewed as a topology.
A lot of the really cool
work in chaos theory
has come by visualizing
these systems,
collapsing a fairly complex
system down into something
that you can now
look at as a picture.
You take something as simple
as a pendulum swinging
back and forth.
And in the chaotic
system, basically, it's
going from know zero movement,
fast movement at the bottom,
back to zero movement.
One dimension is, let's
say, the kinetic energy,
and the other one is
the potential energy.
So the potential energy
is how high it is.
Kinetic energy is
how fast it's going.
If you imagine these
drawings of curved spacetime,
you put a planet on spacetime
and it bends it down here.
OK, so you're actually
bending space there.
Turns out time bends
exactly the same way.
So if something is going past
that planet through that bent
spacetime, the
timeline for that is
a lot longer than if the
planet weren't there.
And that's a really clear way
of visualizing time dilation,
relativity.
So I love the fact that
you can just take things
like that-- as soon as
you make the visual,
it's so instinctual and
intuitive, which is actually
a good lesson, I think,
for your players.
If you can take things
in your game that
seem overly complex at first
and make them more visual,
so the player can interpret
it with their intuition
rather than having to do
some more abstract reasoning,
you can make something
that's very complex actually
seem much more approachable.
Just to recap,
basically, we have
these things that we can
build our systems out of--
agents, networks, layers.
Layers tend to be more rigid.
Agents can be more flexible.
Topologies, that we can have
a structure from these things.
And these networks,
also, are not
just within the
systems of our games.
The overall context of
what we're dealing with--
the players, the world, the
way we distribute and market
games--
can also be viewed as networks.
We have the technology
networks of our computers
to be connected to the internet.
We have platform networks
of different types
of platforms, so their games by
play on this, or that, or iPad,
or PC.
We have formats networks.
What kind of games
are we playing?
Brain networks that we're
dealing with in the player.
And the social
networks that we're
dealing with in the
communities of the players.
So all these things, really,
these topologies and systems,
aren't just things
that we're going
to use to construct our
simulations in our games,
but these are also
things that we
can use to represent
and understand