[MUSIC PLAYING]
A design leader
on a team can take
a number of different roles.
You know, they can start
the vision for a design.
This is where I
think we should go.
They can be the one initially
pitching the team members.
You know, hey, doesn't
this sound cool?
Don't you want to come
build this with me?
At some point, you know, I
think if things are running kind
of nicely, you know,
that's when I start
feeling like a traffic cop.
I'm like, you know, all
the ideas are pretty good.
And it's more just
a matter of saying,
you know, let's do that
one now and this one later.
Let's give these two-- let's
build a prototype for that.
You know, it's more
a matter of that.
Sometimes you do have to
get dictatorial, you know,
and you have to just kind
of put your foot down.
A lot of times you'll get
stuck in this kind of standoff,
stalemate, and you just
have to make a decision.
And that's where
you just have to go
with your gut, your
intuition, and your instinct,
and say, OK, look, I'm just
going to resolve this now.
You try to avoid
that if you can.
But at the same
time, you're also--
you're not just leading
the design of your product.
But you're leading the
process of your design team.
You know, you're telling
your design team, OK, look,
this is how I want us
to resolve disputes.
Or this is how I want us
to make creative decisions.
And so you basically establish
a process, or an etiquette,
some kind of rules of the
road for how these design
decisions can get made, how you
want them to work on your team,
and what you want the team's
basically philosophy to be
for design.
You know, I've
always wanted to have
design spread out through
the entire team, if possible.
And so that's a philosophy that
you try to instill in the team.
So I think that's probably one
of the more important roles
the designer plays
that's kind of separate
from the actual product.
I've been talking about kind
of like the design team,
you know, almost like it's
separate from the rest
of the team, which it's not.
And, you know, on a lot of the
larger games I've worked on,
you know, we had several people
who were purely designers.
But yet, everybody on the team
was contributing to the design.
You know, all the way down
at some level any idea could
bubble up from anywhere.
So really, ideally, you
want to start actually
distributing a lot of the design
tasks through the entire team.
Because somebody
working down here
on the sound system, or that
guy on the graphics system
might have some
really creative ideas.
And they probably know
a lot more about the way
that thing actually
works, and what
you could do with it than you,
as a designer, might know.
As a designer you want to
have a rough idea of the way
all these things work.
But you're not going
to have necessarily
the specialized
knowledge of the way
that particular
cell shader works.
Or something like that.
Ideally, you want to find the
design talent within your team.
Learn to rely on it.
You know, basically make
it visible to other members
so it's not just that person
going around somebody's back.
But, you know, you really
respect that person's idea.
You want to go with it.
A lot of times people
will enter a game team
as a programmer, an
artist, or whatever,
but their real aspiration
is to be a designer.
You know, that's where
they really want to go.
And so if you could help
nurture that and help them
down that path,
you know, one day
you might end up with a
great designer alongside you,
or competing with you.
What I usually think when
I hear the word document,
I think of something
that you write down.
And then you print it out and
give everybody a copy of it.
You know, what I think is
typically much more useful
in game development is
something like a Wiki,
you know, where it's
changing all the time
to show the current thinking.
Because I think, you know,
even a game design is
going to be changing, you know,
if not daily, at least weekly.
Aspects of your game design are
always going to be changing.
And you don't want to
have everyone on your team
have to come back to you and
say, what's the plan this week?
But as you're making these
incremental or iterative
changes, you're
updating it on the Wiki,
you know, pretty consistently,
everybody can always
go back there and find out,
OK, what's the current plan
for our animation system?
Or this or that?
And we found that to
be pretty effective.
You know, just in terms of
time management and all that.
One thing I noticed, you know,
when I started doing games,
I was doing almost everything.
I was writing the manual, doing
the art, sound, and all that.
Then I started working
in small teams, you know,
four or five people.
Eventually it was
like 10, 20 people.
When I was-- the team was
around 10 or 20 people,
I found that we would spend
about three hours actually
doing work for every hour we
spent in meetings together.
As I started working on
larger and larger teams, up
toward 80 people, 90,
100, it was the inverse.
We were spending actually three
hours in meetings for every one
hour we spent at our
desk working, you know.
And that is, you know,
obviously top heavy.
And, you know, you're
wasting way too much time
on communication there.
But now we have
more and more tools
coming online that allow us to
collaborate more effectively
with a lot less effort.
We don't all have
to sit in a room
at the same time for an
hour, having a meeting
about something all the time.
You know, we can
actually eliminate
most of those meetings.
So these documents
really, I think
it's more a matter of
group memory, you know.
And that's what a Wiki, for
me, kind of is like, you know,
me and two other designers
decided we're going to do this.
We put it on the Wiki.
If, you know, somebody wants
to find out what we're doing,
they look at that.
Or if they have an issue with
that, then they look at it,
and they come to us
and say, hey, there's
a problem with what you decided.
Then we kind of revisit it.
But you kind of wait for
these things to happen.
And you basically
try to get everybody
on the team to respect
that mode of communication.
Well, criticism actually
it depends a lot
kind of on your background.
You know, we find the
artists on our team
are very familiar with
the idea of criticism,
because they go through art
critiques in art school,
and stuff like that.
You know, they're very
comfortable with that idea.
Programmers are not.
Programmers hate other
people looking at their code
and criticizing it.
You know, designers tend to be
somewhere in between really.
But I'd much rather feel
like an idea was tested
against criticism
and survived it,
then feel like it sailed
through unchallenged.
And if somebody comes to me
with a criticism of my design,
you know, at first I will try
to, you know, just kind of say,
OK, well, I'm glad that
you're at least speaking up.
And I might disagree.
But, you know, in
the back of my head
it might just sit
there for a while.
Sit there for a while.
You know, everybody
is going to have
an initial kind of
defensive reaction,
I think, to criticism.
And if you can just kind
of take a deep breath,
get past that defensive
reaction, even to yourself,
and imagine, OK, well, what
if that is a good idea?
You know, let me just
try to blank my mind,
live in a different world
where that's a great idea,
and imagine it that way.
If somebody comes to me
with creative criticism,
you know, real
constructive criticism,
and I really eventually
do think it's a good idea,
or they sell me on it--
and that's a big process
and a big part of it,
is when somebody's
criticizing it,
can they present an alternative?
You know, it's not OK
to just say, that's bad.
I don't like that.
But if they say, I think this
would be better than that.
And they could really sell me
that this is better than that.
Or maybe even sell other
members of the team.
You know, so maybe
I don't agree.
But maybe the other
designers start
saying, hey, I think that
is maybe a better idea.
And I'm trying to sell
my idea against that.
You know, now it's in
a Darwinian process.
And I think that's, you know,
a place I would like it to be.
You know, you don't
want an idea that
is getting through
nepotism, or favoritism,
or, you know, Will said it.
So it has to be.
But if you feel like
your idea went out
there in the thunderdome,
and battled the other ideas,
and came out the victor, then
I think that's a nice way
to approach it.
As long as you just don't
end up with a bloodbath
of ideas fighting forever.
You know, at some
point you do have
to kind of make a decision,
move forward with some path.
But you want the whole team to
feel good about that path too.
You don't want it to feel
like, everybody on the team
thought we should do this,
but the designer said that.
In any type of
collaborative endeavor,
you want somebody who is not
going to be too dogmatic.
But at the same time,
is going to have
a very clear, strong voice
for what they believe.
And it's going to be pretty--
they need to be pretty
clear about what they believe.
You know, not just that they
say, everything is great,
or I love all that.
Or that if they really
don't like something,
they just get quiet
and don't say anything.
I would rather them--
even if I think
they're wrong I
would much rather
them speak up and clearly
say what they think.
That's the thing that
I think is missing
kind of the most on
the teams I've built
is enough constructive
criticism.
You don't want people
just saying, OK,
we'll do whatever you
say, and go do it.
You know, I would love to
have people push back on me,
and do things like that.
And not just on the design.
You know, also just on the
team dynamics, and everything.
My art director I worked with
for many years, just quickly,
he became what we called the
canary, in that, you know,
we would have these big
team meetings all the time.
And at some point the
meeting would just kind of
drag on and on.
And there would
always be some point
in the meeting in which
Ocean would put up his hand.
Can I leave now?
And that basically we knew that
the meeting had hit diminishing
returns at that point.
Whenever Ocean left,
it was like the canary
died in the coal mine.
But actually, it turned out
to be a very valuable dynamic.
As soon as Ocean
left the meeting,
everybody, oh, Ocean left.
All right.
We're wasting our time here.
And we'd usually
stop the meeting.