[MUSIC PLAYING]
WILL WRIGHT: I
think recently we've
seen games evolve in an area
that was kind of unexpected,
let's say, 15 years
ago when we had
the rise of the app market,
and tablets, and smartphones.
We're seeing a lot
of what I would
call interstitial gaming now.
These are very short,
consumable game
experiences on a
small screen that I
can do in a few minutes
on my smartphone.
I'm seeing some of the most
creative games I've ever
seen appearing on tablets.
It's actually a really
nice format for gaming,
wherever you want to be.
And it's, you know,
something that
doesn't have the stigma of I'm
carrying around a game machine
everywhere because they're using
tablets for everything now.
So I think those
have allowed games
to reach a much wider audience.
And it's also allowed
diversification and exploration
of kind of indie games and
new experimental gameplay that
probably would not
have been economically
viable on the older platforms.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Going into the future,
I think, you know,
we have VR starting to become
more and more accessible.
You know, I've played a lot of
the VR games, which I enjoy.
And it's interesting.
As immersive as VR is though,
it's not the type of thing
where I'm going
to be up all night
like I was playing "Doom" in
a dark room for five hours.
There seems to be for almost
everybody a limited time
that you can kind of be
in that box in that world
and, you know, without starting
to feel really uncomfortable.
I think part of it is the fact
that you're totally blocked off
from the world around you.
And there's something,
you know, kind
of inherently
disconcerting about that.
And for that reason
and a few others,
I really think that there's
a much bigger potential,
you know, for gaming
in augmented reality.
Games now are-- I'm
consuming, you know,
without closing off
the world around me
and, in fact, are occurring
placed in the world around me.
They have maybe some
context even to where I am
and what I'm doing.
I think that the technology
there that I've seen
is still several years off.
But that stuff is
coming at us so rapidly.
You know, I wouldn't
be surprised
if I was seeing some really
cool creative stuff in about
five years from now, you know,
as the headsets get lighter,
more transparent, less kind of
social stigma with the Google
glasses and whatnot.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Alongside of augmented reality,
I think that AI, in fact,
really is going to make
the biggest impact by far.
I think that--
and when I say AI,
I don't mean
intelligent opponents.
But I mean an
intelligent game system
that is understanding
the player, that
is watching what the player
is doing, and understanding
what motivates the
player, what they enjoy,
what they don't like, topics
they find interesting,
things that it can pull in,
other people they might want
to meet or interact
with on certain topics.
I think that AI moderating
either as a game master
or even as a game designer
can fundamentally alter
the landscape of game design.
If you could imagine an
AI that could actually
craft a game uniquely
for you-- you know,
it might be that we all
start with the same kind
of generic game.
As we start playing, it
starts learning more about us.
There's a great book
by Neil Stephenson--
"Diamond Age."
And he describes this
magical book, which
is in fact a supercomputer that
understands this little girl,
understands the
world she lives in,
the context of her
day-to-day life
and starts teaching her
very effectively the things
that she needs to
know to survive.
She's like actually a
homeless girl on the streets.
But I can imagine
a gaming system
very much like that that
sits there and starts
customizing itself to you.
This is extreme
personalization-- basically,
if you had a master game
designer sitting over
your shoulder very quickly
and rapidly iterating,
reprogramming the game
around you to make
it more interesting to you.
If an AI could understand
you to that degree,
it could also find other people
that are that similar to you
and put you in a
shared experience.
So it could be that
it finds, you know,
what other people have had their
game world evolve to fit them
in exactly the same way
that you've had your game
world evolve to fit you and,
you know, all of a sudden put
together in the same world.
There might also be
collaborative experiences based
upon this kind of an idea where
the AI is trying to moderate,
you know, based upon
different people,
their shared vision or
which parts they share,
which parts they don't.
And, I mean, it might be this--
would be very interesting way to
kind of figure out which parts
of the vision we share,
which ones we don't.
And maybe the parts
we don't become ripe
for gameplay, you know.
So there are a lot of different
things this could lead to.
But step one is, can we build
an AI that really is trying
to understand the
player at a deeply
fundamental level the same
way a game designer tries to?
In some sense, it scares me.
I mean, it almost sounds
dangerous that, you know,
something like that could be so
addictive if it was effective.
I almost wonder if we
should somehow avoid it.
But I know we won't.
I know that if it's
possible, we will build it.
But I think that more
than anything else that
is going to be the most
interesting, disruptive,
fundamentally game changing
thing that's probably
going to happen in our field.
And I think that could happen
within 15 years or less.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
The most fundamental aspect
of the future of game design
is it like almost
everything else--
it's becoming more and
more unpredictable.
If you went back 100 years
ago and asked people what's
the world to be
like in 50 years,
I think they would
have given you
a pretty reasonable
description of the world,
you know, 50 years
later if you went back
let's say to the
1950s and said, what's
the world going be
like in 2000, I think
they would have been
quite a bit farther off,
but still in the ballpark.
You go to 2000 and ask, what's
the world be like in 2050,
I don't think we have
a clue or maybe we
had a little bit of a clue.
But, basically, the
future is increasingly
becoming less and
less predictable.
And this ties into this
kind of basic idea known
as the singularity.
In almost any dimension,
we measure humans.
You know, it could be
energy consumption.
It could be population.
It could be intelligence,
Whatever it is-- you know,
technology--
it's accelerating to
this asymptotic curve.
And so there are these
transformative technologies
approaching us.
And it might be biotechnology,
nanotechnology, AI.
Any one of these
things could radically
alter the world around us pretty
rapidly over a few decades.
And that's an indication
that our future is becoming
less and less predictable.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Game design is one on these
fields where, you know,
you're basically committing
yourself to lifelong learning,
you know, because it's not
only so rapidly advancing,
but, also, you have such
a wide palette of things
you can do within that field.
I think that-- you know,
don't get too dogmatic
about any approach, any
platform, any philosophy.
It's really about being
adaptable, and flexible,
and open-minded, and
looking ahead, not too far,
but far enough ahead to
get some sense of, OK, I
think in three years we're going
to be going there or there.
And assume that you're
standing on shaky ground.
You're not standing-- we
used to live in this world
where every four or five
years predictably there would
be another platform coming
out on the console side.
And then we would know that
five years, we need another one.
And it was like very
predictable, almost
deterministic world that we
lived in as game designers.
That's not so anymore.
Now, you know,
five years from now
there could be some platform
we're not even aware of right
now that's the big fad.
Things are moving that fast.
So that's probably
the best advice