[MUSIC PLAYING]
Well, thank you for going
through this entire course.
And I hope that from
this point on you'll
go out into your field,
whatever that is, and use
these new tools in your
toolbox to do something maybe
a little bit more
outside your own box
and create things that
even surprise yourself.
Really, more than
anything else, I'm
looking forward to seeing
the games that you'll create.
The generation
that's creating games
now has so many
opportunities, and the things
I'm seeing come out
right now are amazing.
And I really want to sit back,
have a comfortable retirement,
and play these cool
games that I only right
now can imagine but I
know that one day you
will make as designers.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
The possibility space for
your next game is huge.
So find something
you're passionate about
and start exploring.
Remember, look around you.
Your next idea might be
lurking somewhere nearby.
Go out and catch it.
I'll be here, anxiously
waiting, ready to play.